. >> GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE
WELCOME TO THE SEPTEMBER 30TH 2020 FIVE REGULAR MEETING OF
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL?
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENTS SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
PRESENT SUPERVISOR AND GUARDIAN AND GUARDIAN PRESENT SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER PRESENT SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD
PRESENT SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN PRESIDENT MANDEL MEN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR SAUTER
SAUTER PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL PRESENT
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON PRESENT.
>> MR. PRESIDENT ALL MEMBERS ARE PRESENT.
THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL
HOMELAND OF DRAMATIST ALONI WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL INHABITANTS OF
THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA. AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF
THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE RAW
MATERIAL OWNING HAVE NEVER CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR
RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS
WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL
TERRITORY. AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE
BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOMELANDS.
WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS,
ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE RAW MATERIAL ONLY COMMUNITY AND BY
AFFIRMING THEIR SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
COLLEAGUES WILL YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE? PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG
OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND TO THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH
IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD INDIVISIBLE WITH LIBERTY
AND JUSTICE. >> ON BEHALF OF OUR BOARD I
WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT S.F. GOV TV TODAY THAT IS
ESPECIALLY KALEENA MENDOZA. THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR
MEETINGS AND MAKE THE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE
PUBLIC ONLINE. MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY
COMMUNICATIONS? >> YES.
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOU ALL TO
ATTEND THIS MEETING IN PERSON HERE IN THE BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE
CHAMBER WITHIN CITY HALL ON THE SECOND FLOOR IN ROOM 250.
OR IF YOU'RE UNABLE TO MAKE IT TO THIS MEETING YOU CAN WATCH
THE PROCEEDINGS ON AS OF GOVEE TVS CHANNEL 26 OR VIEW THE LIVE
STREAM AT WW DOT SMG OR VTV.ORG.
IF YOU'D LIKE TO SUBMIT YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT IN WRITING YOU
CAN SEND AN EMAIL TO BOSE AT S.F. CAVORTING OR USE THE
POSTAL SERVICE AND ADDRESS THE ENVELOPE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. THE NUMBER ONE DOCTOR CARLTON B
GOODLATTE PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244 IN SAN FRANCISCO,
CALIFORNIA 94102. IF YOU NEED TO MAKE A FUTURE
REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION REQUEST UNDER THE AMERICANS
WITH DISABILITIES ACT OR TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE,
YOU CAN CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS
DAYS IN ADVANCE BY CALLING (415) 554-5184.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
LET'S GO TO OUR CONSENT AGENDA. PLEASE CALL ITEMS ONE AND TWO
TOGETHER. >> ITEMS ONE AND TWO ARE ON
CONSENT. THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED TO
BE ROUTINE IF A MEMBER OBJECTS AN ITEM MAY BE REMOVED
AND CONSIDERED SEPARATELY. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON ITEMS ONE AND TWO. SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR. EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL.
EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYE. SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO EYES SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
AND SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MANDOLIN EITHER ORI LEBANESE
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK PLEASE GO TO UNFINISHED BUSINESS.
ITEM THREE ITEM THREE THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
PLANNING CODE TO WAIVE CERTAIN DEVELOPMENT IMPACT FEES IN THE
MARKET AND OCTAVIA AREA PLAN AND TO AMEND THE VENICE
AND MARKET RESIDENTIAL SPECIAL USE DISTRICT TO PROVIDE THAT
THE MARKET AND OCTAVIA COMMUNITY ADVISORY COMMITTEE
SHALL SUNSET SIX MONTHS AFTER THE EFFECTIVE DATE OF THIS
ORDINANCE AND TO MAKE CONFORMING AMENDMENTS TO SOME
OF THE DEFINITIONS IN THE PLANNING CODE AND TO AFFIRM THE
SECOND DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM THREE SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR IS CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON NO SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO I SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER NO SUPERVISOR OF MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
AND SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MANDALAY MEN I THERE ARE NINE
EYES AND TWO NOS WITH SUPERVISORS WALTON AND FIELDER
VOTING NO THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK
PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER FOUR ITEM FOUR THIS IS AN ORDINANCE
TO APPROPRIATE 400,000 FROM THE GENERAL CITY RESPONSIBILITY
AND APPROXIMATELY 14,000 FROM THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS
AND TO APPROPRIATE FOR DISTRICT SEVEN PROJECTS IN THE AMOUNT OF
APPROXIMATELY 164,000 TO PUBLIC WORKS FOR MEDIAN IMPROVEMENTS
AND MODERATE HEIGHTS NEW CURB RAMPS IN THE WESTWOOD PARK
SIDEWALK REPAIR IN INGLESIDE TERRACE AND FOR WESTWOOD PARK
PILLARS 100,000 TO THE DEPARTMENT OF CHILDREN, YOUTH
AND THEIR FAMILIES FOR PLAYGROUND UPDATE AND BLACKTOP
AT WEST PORTAL ELEMENTARY SCHOOL AND FOR A MURAL
AND SIGNAGE UPDATES AT COMMODORE SLOAT ELEMENTARY
50,000 TO THE ARTS COMMISSION FOR MURAL A MURAL ON MONTEREY
BOULEVARD 50,000 TO THE OFFICE OF ECONOMIC AND WORKFORCE
DEVELOPMENT FOR A SERIES OF ART POP UPS ON OCEAN AVENUE
AND 50,000 TO THE MUNICIPAL TRANSPORTATION AGENCY FOR
DAYLIGHTING AND BOLLARDS IN SUNNYSIDE IN FISCAL YEAR
2025 THROUGH 2026 PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM FOR SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER EYES SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN
CHAN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO I SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
AND SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN I MANDOLIN I.
>> THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER FIVE
ITEM FIVE THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE BUSINESS AND TAX
REGULATIONS CODE TO REDUCE THE TAX RATES ON GROSS RECEIPTS
FROM TELECOMMUNICATIONS BUSINESS ACTIVITIES BY MOVING
THOSE ACTIVITIES FROM CATEGORY FIVE TO CATEGORY FOUR BEGINNING
JANUARY 1ST, 2026 FOR PURPOSES OF THE GROSS RECEIPTS TAX
AND THE HOMELESSNESS GROSS RECEIPTS TAX AND TO RETAIN
TAXPAYER'S ELIGIBILITY TO TAKE THE TAX CREDIT FOR OPENING A
PHYSICAL LOCATION IN DESIGNATED AREAS OF THE CITY AS APPLIED TO
GROSS RECEIPTS FROM TELECOMMUNICATIONS BUSINESS
ACTIVITIES AND PURSUANT TO THE BUSINESS AND TAX REGULATIONS
CODE AMENDING SECTION 2811 OF ARTICLE 28 REQUIRES AN APPROVAL
BY A SUPERMAJORITY VOTE OF AT LEAST EIGHT MEMBERS OF THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
FINALLY PASSED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER SIX ITEM SIX THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
SUBDIVISION CODE TO ESTABLISH PROCEDURES PERTAINING TO RESALE
PRICES CAPITAL IMPROVEMENT COSTS, MARKETING AND SALES
POLICIES FOR CONVEYANCE THROUGH INHERITANCE TITLE CHANGES
OWNING OCCUPYING AND REFINANCING BELOW MARKET
RATE CONDOMINIUM CONVERSION UNITS ALSO KNOWN AS BMR UNITS
AND TO CLARIFY EFFECTIVE DATES FOR REQUIREMENTS APPLICABLE TO
BMR UNITS UNDER SUBDIVISION CODE SECTION 1344 PURCHASED ON
OR AFTER OCTOBER 1ST, 2025 AND I THINK WE CAN DO THIS SAME
HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
FINALLY PASSED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER SEVEN ITEM SEVEN THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
BUILDING CODE TO REMOVE LOCAL REQUIREMENTS PERTAINING TO
COMMERCIAL LIGHTING, ROOFTOP MECHANICAL PENTHOUSES, DRIVEWAY
AND SIDEWALK LOAD LIMITS AND THE PROTECTION ACT TO
AFFIRM THE SECOND DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE
FINDINGS AND WE CAN DO THIS SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM EIGHT.
>> ITEM EIGHT THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE HEALTH
CODE TO CLARIFY THE CITY'S ENHANCED VENTILATION STANDARDS
BY CODIFYING THE REQUIREMENT THAT ALL NEW BUILDINGS
AND MAJOR RENOVATIONS OF BUILDINGS THAT CONTAIN A
SENSITIVE USE CERTIFY THAT THE BUILDINGS VENTILATION SYSTEM IS
CAPABLE OF MAINTAINING POSITIVE PRESSURE LIMITING APPLICABILITY
OF THE CITY'S ENHANCED VENTILATION STANDARD TO SINGLE
FAMILY HOMES EFFECTIVE JANUARY 1ST, 2026 TO ALIGN WITH STATE
LAW AND TO MAKE FINDINGS UNDER THE CALIFORNIA HEALTH
AND SAFETY CODE TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION AND TO
MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS. AND WE CAN DO THIS SAME HOUSE
SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED
. >> MADAME CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM NINE ITEM NINE THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO ORDER SUMMARY
VACATION OF A PUBLIC SERVICE EASEMENT FOR PUBLIC UTILITY
PURPOSES AT 112 KENSINGTON IN AND WAY TO AUTHORIZE THE
CITY TO QUIT CLAIM ITS INTEREST IN THE VACATION AREA THAT IS
ALSO ASSESSOR'S PARCEL BLOCK NUMBER 2923 AND LOT NUMBER 078
TO KEVIN JENKINS AND LALITHA CHANDRASHEKAR FOR 2002 AFFIRMS
IS THE SEQUEL DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE
FINDINGS WE'LL DO THIS SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO NEW BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEM TEN
ITEM TEN THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE
CODE AND LABOR AND EMPLOYMENT CODES TO UPDATE CITY CONTRACT
PROCESSES AND REQUIREMENTS. >> OKAY.
AND I THINK WE CAN DO THIS SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCES PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK
PLEASE CALL ITEM 11. >> ITEM 11 THIS IS A RESOLUTION
TO APPROVE THE 15TH MODIFICATION TO AN AIRPORT
CONTRACT FOR PROJECT MANAGEMENT SUPPORT SERVICES FOR THE
TERMINAL THREE WEST MODERNIZATION PROJECT WITH A W
C M J V TO INCREASE THE CONTRACT AMOUNT BY SEVEN 6
MILLION FOR A NEW AMOUNT OF 126 MILLION AND TO EXTEND THE
CONTRACT FOR SERVICES FOR AN ADDITIONAL FIVE YEARS A TOTAL
TERM NOW OF APRIL 12TH 2016 THROUGH DECEMBER 12TH 2030
AND SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 12. >> ITEM 12 THIS IS A RESOLUTION
TO APPROVE AND AUTHORIZE THE DIRECTOR OF PROPERTY ON BEHALF
OF THE FLEET MANAGEMENT DEPARTMENT KNOWN AS CENTRAL
SHOPS TO EXECUTE A LEASE AGREEMENT FOR 19 ZERO EIGHT
THROUGH 1950. IN HIS AVENUE FOR A SIX YEAR
TERM THROUGH SEPTEMBER 30TH 2031 WITH ONE FIVE YEAR OPTION
TO EXTEND THE TERM WITHIN HIS GROUP L C LLC AT A BASE RENT OF
APPROXIMATELY 632,000 PER YEAR WITH 3% ANNUAL RENT INCREASES.
ADDITIONALLY, THE CITY WILL CONTRIBUTE UP TO AN APPROXIMATE
349,000 FOR TENANT IMPROVEMENTS AND WE'LL DO THIS SAME HOUSE
SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 13 ITEM 13 RESOLUTION TO LEVY
PROPERTY TAXES AT A COMBINED RATE OF APPROXIMATELY $1 ON
EACH 100 VALUATION OF TAXABLE PROPERTY FOR THE CITY
AND COUNTY. THE UNIFIED SCHOOL DISTRICT THE
COUNTY OFFICE OF EDUCATION. THE COMMUNITY COLLEGE DISTRICT,
THE BAY AREA RAPID TRANSIT DISTRICT AND THE BAY AREA AIR
QUALITY MANAGEMENT DISTRICT AND TO ESTABLISH PASSTHROUGH
RATES PER 100 OF ASSESSED VALUE FOR RESIDENTIAL TENANTS
AND BASED ON TENANCY COMMENCEMENT DATES PURSUANT TO
THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE. CHAPTER 37 FOR THE FISCAL YEAR
ENDING JUNE 30TH 2026. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 14 ITEM 14 RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE
THE SAN FRANCISCO ANIMAL CARE AND CONTROL TO ENTER INTO A
COOPERATIVE AGREEMENT WITH THE PRESIDIO TRUST TO PROVIDE
ANIMAL CONTROL AND WELFARE SERVICES FOR AN ADDITIONAL AN
INITIAL TERM OF FIVE YEARS WITH AN OPTION TO EXTEND FOR AN
ADDITIONAL FIVE YEARS. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 15.
>> ITEM 15. ITEM 15 IS A RESOLUTION TO
APPROVE THE SECOND AMENDMENT TO THE AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE CITY
AND EDGEWOOD CENTER FOR CHILDREN AND FAMILIES TO
PROVIDE HOSPITAL DIVERSION AND CRISIS STABILIZATION UNIT
SERVICES. TO EXTEND THE TERM BY FOUR
YEARS AND NINE MONTHS FOR TOTAL TERM OF OCTOBER 1ST 2023
THROUGH JUNE 30TH OF 2030. AND TO INCREASE THE AMOUNT BY
APPROXIMATELY 22 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL AMOUNT OF
APPROXIMATELY 31.6 MILLION. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 16 ITEM 16 RESOLUTION TO
AUTHORIZE THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH TO ENTER INTO A
GRANT AGREEMENT FOR A TERM COMMENCING ON EXECUTION OF THE
GRANT AGREEMENT THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2027 BETWEEN THE CITY
AND COUNTY AND THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH CARE
SERVICES AND ITS THIRD PARTY ADMINISTRATOR ADVOCATES FOR
HUMAN POTENTIAL INC HAVING ANTICIPATED REVENUE TO THE CITY
OF 10 MILLION TO INCLUDE A PERMITTED AND RESTRICTED USE TO
AUTHORIZE TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND GRANT FUNDS TO AUTHORIZE THE
GRANT OR TO APPLY FOR A RECEIVER IN THE EVENT OF THE
CITY'S DEFAULT. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 17 ITEM 17 RESOLUTION TO
AUTHORIZE THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORT OF
HOUSING TO EXECUTE A SUBGROUP RENT AGREEMENT WITH THE URBAN
INSTITUTE FOR A TOTAL AMOUNT OF 200,000 OF JUST HOME COHORT
NUMBER ONE CONTINUATION FUNDS TO RETROACTIVELY ACCEPT
AND EXPEND THOSE GRANTS OF FUNDS TO SUPPORT CONTINUED
PROJECT MANAGEMENT OF THE JUST HOME PROGRAM FOR COSTS INCURRED
JUNE 15TH 2025 THROUGH SEPTEMBER 30TH 2026.
>> SAME HOUSE SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
18. >> ITEM 18 RESOLUTION TO
APPROVE AND AUTHORIZE THE DIRECTOR OF PROPERTY TO ACQUIRE
CERTAIN REAL PROPERTY LOCATED AT 1660 AND 1670 MISSION STREET
TO APPROVE AND AUTHORIZE AN AGREEMENT OF PURCHASE AND SALE
FOR REAL ESTATE FOR THE ACQUISITION OF THE PROPERTY FOR
THE PURCHASE PRICE OF APPROXIMATE 18.5 MILLION PLUS
AN ESTIMATED 30,000 FOR TYPICAL CLOSING COSTS FOR A TOTAL
AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 18.5 MILLION FROM 290 DIVISION LLC
1660 MISSION LLC AND SKYLINE CAPITAL, A WYOMING LIMITED
LIABILITY COMPANY AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION AND TO
MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION, THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL ITEM 19?
>> ITEM 19 WAS REFERRED WITHOUT RECOMMENDATION FROM THE BUDGET
AND FINANCE COMMITTEE. THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE
THE THIRD AMENDMENT TO THE GRANT AGREEMENT BETWEEN URBAN
ALCHEMY AND THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORT OF
HOUSING FOR SHELTER SERVICES AND OPERATIONS AT 711 POST
STREET. TO EXTEND THE TERM THE GRANT
TERM BY SIX MONTHS FOR A NEW TOTAL TERM OF MARCH 21ST 2022
THROUGH MARCH 31ST 2026 TO INCREASE THE AGREEMENT AMOUNT
BY APPROXIMATELY 4.9 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL AMOUNT OF 27.6
MILLION SUPERVISED OF SLAUGHTER.
>> YES. THANK YOU.
PRESIDENT BENJAMIN SORT OF BRIEFLY SPEAK ON THIS ITEM THAT
WAS REFERRED WITHOUT RECOMMENDATION FROM LAND USE.
THIS IS AN EXTENSION OF A CONTRACT FOR A HOMELESS SHELTER
IN MY DISTRICT IN LOWER HILL. WE'RE LOOKING AT A SIX MONTH
EXTENSION HERE AND I WILL BE SUPPORTING THIS BUT I DO HAVE
CONCERNS ABOUT THE PRACTICE OF URBAN ALCHEMY AT THIS SITE
IN PARTICULAR HAS BEEN FINDINGS THAT THERE'S BEEN MISMANAGEMENT
OF FUNDS FROM THIS SITE IN PARTICULAR AND I WANT TO
MAKE SURE THAT WE ARE NOT RUSHING INTO ANY LONG TERM
AGREEMENT AFTER THIS SIX MONTH EXTENSION.
SO KIND OF PUTTING THIS OUT TO FLAG THAT IT WILL BE LATER AT
ROLL CALL INTRODUCING A HEARING SO THAT WE HAVE A MEASURE OF
ACCOUNTABILITY TO MONITOR THE FINANCES OF THIS SITE
IN PARTICULAR BEFORE WE CONSIDER A LONGER TERM
EXTENSION. BUT FOR NOW AT THE SIX MONTH
SIX MONTH EXTENSION I WILL BE SUPPORTING IT WITH THOSE
COMMENTS WITH STANDING THANKS. >> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
COLLEAGUES, I'D LIKE TO ALSO SPEAK ON ITEM 19 ON THE GRANT
AGREEMENT AMENDMENT TO URBAN ALCHEMY AND ECHOING A SURPRISE
OF SADR'S COMMENTS I AGREE ACCOUNTABILITY IS KEY
AND RIGHTFULLY SO AND THERE IS CONCERN ABOUT NONPROFIT
MANAGEMENT AND FISCAL SUSTAINABILITY HERE AND IT
WOULD BE WISE FOR US AS A BODY TO DO OUR DUE DILIGENCE AND I
SUPPORT THIS NEED FOR IMPROVED FINANCIAL PRUDENCE FROM GROUPS
WITH CITY CONTRACTS. >> BUT I ALSO WANT TO ELEVATE A
BROADER POINT IRRESPECTIVE TO 7-ELEVEN POST MORE BROADLY ON
THE TIMING AND THE IMPACT OF THE WORK OF URBAN ALCHEMY
AND ITS IMPORTANCE TO THE COMMUNITY SAFETY
AND NEIGHBORHOOD CONDITIONS AND ELEVATE THAT I HEAR ALMOST
DAILY FROM RESIDENTS IN THE TENDERLOIN THAT THE VALUE THAT
UAI PROVIDES IS INCALCULABLE SO THEIR WORK IS DIFFICULT.
>> THESE EWHA AMBASSADORS ARE OFTEN IN SOME OF THE MOST
CHALLENGING PUBLIC SAFETY SITUATIONS AND IT'S NO SECRET
THAT THEY OPERATE IN ONE OF THE MOST CHALLENGING NEIGHBORHOODS
IN OUR CITY AND YET THEY SHOW UP, SMILE ON THEIR FACE, BRING
SAFETY TO OUR COMMUNITY AND BUILDING RELATIONSHIPS WITH
NEIGHBORS. >> NO ONE'S PERFECT AND THAT'S
WHY THIS PROGRAM WORKS. WHAT MAKES THEM SO EFFECTIVE IS
THEIR LIVED EXPERIENCE. URBAN ALCHEMY EMPLOYS FORMERLY
INCARCERATED INDIVIDUALS GIVING THEM A SECOND CHANCE
AND REDUCING RATES OF RECIDIVISM.
>> IT'S A WIN WIN. THIS MODEL AND ITS
EFFECTIVENESS EMBODY SAN FRANCISCO'S VALUES.
THIS IS A CITY THAT BELIEVES IN UPLIFTING THOSE AROUND US,
THAT BELIEVES IN SECOND CHANCES AND BELIEVES THIS IS A CITY FOR
ALL. >> AND FOR THE SUPERVISORS ON
THE BOARD WHO MAY DOUBT OR HAVE LIMITED EXPERIENCE WITH THE
NEIGHBORHOOD AND THE WORK OF URBAN ALCHEMY, I INVITE YOU TO
JOIN ME ON A WALK THROUGH THE HILL TO ENSURE THAT WE ARE
MAKING INFORMED DECISIONS RELATED TO THEIR SERVICES AS WE
ARE LOOKING TO HAVE THEM MADE. >> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD.
SO I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION. THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
AND MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL ITEMS 20 THROUGH 22
TOGETHER ITEMS 20 THROUGH 22 OR 3 RESOLUTIONS THAT RESPOND TO
THE PRESIDING JUDGE OF THE SUPERIOR COURT ON THE FINDINGS
AND RECOMMENDATIONS CONTAINED IN THREE 2024 THROUGH 2025
CIVIL GRAND JURY REPORTS. >> ITEM 20 IS ENTITLED CAPACITY
TO SERVE SETTINGS SOCIAL SERVICES NONPROFITS UP FOR
SUCCESS. ITEM 22 ENTITLED TEXAN THE CITY
GOVERNMENT OPPORTUNITY TO SEIZE THE I MOMENT AN ITEM 22 IS
ENTITLED FAILED VISION REVAMPING THE ROAD MAP TO SAFER
STREETS AND FOR ALL THREE ITEMS TO URGE THE MAYOR TO CAUSE THE
IMPLEMENTATION OF ACCEPTED FINDINGS AND RECOMMENDATIONS
THROUGH HIS DEPARTMENT HEADS AND THROUGH THAT EVENT THE
DEVELOPMENT OF THE ANNUAL BUDGET.
AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
>> MADAME CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 23 ITEM 23 THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PUBLIC WORKS CODE TO AUTHORIZE PUBLIC
WORKS TO PERFORM GRAFFITI ABATEMENT ON PRIVATE PROPERTIES
IN COMMERCIAL AREAS AT NO COST TO THE PROPERTY OWNERS SOLELY
AT THE PROPERTY OWNERS REQUEST AND UPON PROPERTY OWNERS
AUTHORIZATION AND PROPERTY OWNERS WAIVER OF CLAIMS
ASSOCIATED WITH THE GRAFFITI ABATEMENT AND TO AFFIRM THE
SECTION DETERMINATION WE'LL TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE SAME
CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST
READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 24 ITEM 24 THIS IS A
RESOLUTION TO EXPRESS INTEREST IN FORMING AN ENHANCED
INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCING DISTRICT TO SUPPORT FUNDING
AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND WELL-RESOURCED
NEIGHBORHOODS AND TO REQUEST TO THE COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE THE
OFFICE OF ECONOMIC WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT AND THE MAYOR'S
OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT TO EXPLORE OPTIONS
FOR ESTABLISHING AN IFC AND OTHER INNOVATIVE FINANCING
OPTIONS SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU PRESIDENT.
>> A COLLEAGUES I HOPE I CAN COUNT ON YOUR SUPPORT FOR THIS
RESOLUTION TO EXPLORE OPTIONS AND INTERESTS IN FORMING AN
EASIER FOR US TO SUPPORT AFFORDABLE HOUSING PRODUCTION
ON THE WEST SIDE AND OTHER NEIGHBORHOODS IN THE STATE
DEFINED WELL RESOURCED NEIGHBORHOODS AS WE ARE ALSO
DELIBERATING THE REZONING LEGISLATION THE CONCEPT OF AN E
I F D IS NOT NEW. IT ALLOWS US TO USE A PROPERTY
TAX GROWTH AND ACTUALLY ONLY PART OF THAT AS PER OUR CITY'S
POLICY TO SUPPORT FINANCIAL INFRASTRUCTURE PROJECTS IN THE
SHORT TERM AND AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS SOMETHING THAT THE
STATE ALLOWS US TO CONSIDER INFRASTRUCTURE AFFORDABLE
HOUSING IN SAN FRANCISCO HAS ALWAYS RELIED ON THE MARKET TO
PRODUCE TREES AND WE DO NEED TO LOOK AT OTHER FINANCING MODELS
IN ADDITION TO WHAT WE ALREADY HAVE.
THEY ARE MODELS THAT ARE COUNTERCYCLICAL THAT WILL WORK
EVEN IF THE MARKET IS DOWN SO THAT WE CAN CONTINUE TO BUILD
AFFORDABLE HOUSING WHICH OUR COMMUNITIES RELY ON BY VOTING
ON THIS RESOLUTION. IT DOES NOT BIND US TO DO ANY
PARTICULAR FORMATION OF GIFTS BUT IT SIMPLY URGES THE
DEPARTMENT TO PUT FORWARD THEIR THINKING SO THAT WE CAN
EVALUATE OUR OPTIONS IN THE FUTURE.
I WANT TO THANK THE COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE, THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE OF ECONOMIC AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT, THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING FOR THEIR WORK IN HELPING US
DETERMINE OPTIONS LATER THIS FALL SO THAT WE CAN ENGAGE
IN DISCUSSION ON WHAT MIGHT WORK BEST TO BRING THE
ESSENTIAL AFFORDABLE HOUSING UNITS THAT WE NEED ON THE WEST
SIDE. ONE THING I KNOW IN ALL OF OUR
REZONING CONVERSATIONS AND THE CONVERSATIONS THAT WE'RE HAVING
ABOUT THE HOUSING THAT WE NEED IN THE FUTURE IS THAT
AFFORDABLE HOUSING FINANCING IS A MUST.
WE NEED IT WE NEED IT ON THE WEST SIDE.
WE NEED IT ALL OVER SAN FRANCISCO AND WE NEED DIFFERENT
MECHANISMS SO THAT WE CAN ALWAYS GUARANTEE THAT
AFFORDABLE HOUSING PRODUCTION IS PART OF WHAT WE'RE DOING
ALWAYS IN ALL AREAS OF THE CITY.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
>> CHAIR MELGAR SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDELA
AND COLLEAGUES I WILL NOT BE IN SUPPORT OF THIS ITEM TODAY
OR THIS RESOLUTION TODAY FOR THE REASON BECAUSE I SEE THAT
THE BETTER VENUE TO REALLY INVEST IN AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS
TO CONTINUE TO FIGURE OUT WAYS LIKE AFFORDABLE HOUSING BY
WHICH WE HAVE DONE SUCCESSFULLY IN THE LAST FEW YEARS.
I REALLY THINK THAT THE NEXT STEP IS ACTUALLY BUILD THE
MOMENTUM FOR A REGIONAL HOUSING BOND FOR THAT REASON BECAUSE I
THINK AGAIN WE NEED AFFORDABLE HOUSING WHEN AFFORDABLE HOUSING
EVERYWHERE IN SAN FRANCISCO TO SAY THAT WE WILL ONLY BE HAVING
IN ON THE WELL RESOURCED NEIGHBORHOOD AND COLLECTING TAX
INCREMENT FROM THE WEST SIDE AND ONLY FOR THE WEST SIDE
INSTEAD OF THINKING ABOUT, YOU KNOW, PUBLIC DOLLARS LIKE THE
BOND AND BEING ABLE TO PROVIDE SOME FLEXIBILITY TO DIFFERENT
KINDS OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING DEPENDING ON THE NEEDS AND ALSO
LOCATIONS AVAILABILITY OF THOSE IS REALLY WHAT I'M LOOKING FOR
. >> SO I WOULD NOT BE IN SUPPORT
OF THAT TODAY. THANK YOU FOR THE CHAN CHAIR
MUGAR THANK YOU. >> I JUST WANTED TO POINT OUT
IN RESPONSE TO MY COLLEAGUE FROM DISTRICT ONE THAT THE
FORMATION IN LIFO IN NO WAY PRECLUDES A BOND.
IN FACT IT SHOULD BE BOTH AND IN NO WAY PRECLUDES THE THE
A REGIONAL BAY AREA FINANCING AGENCY MECHANISM TO FUND
AFFORDABLE HOUSING. IN FACT I THINK WE NEED MORE
THAN ONE. WE NEED MORE THAN THREE WE NEED
AS MANY WAYS TO FINANCE AFFORDABLE HOUSING AS POSSIBLE.
ALL OVER SAN FRANCISCO ROSA CHAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT
AMENDMENT I DISAGREE. I THINK THE REALITY IS THAT
LIKE WHEN WE HAVE TO LOOK AT OUR ENTIRE CAPACITY BOTH
IN DEBT CAPACITY AS WELL AS TAX REVENUE GENERATION I MEAN YOU
CAN SHAKE YOUR HEADS ALL YOU WANT BUT THE REALITY IS THAT WE
ACTUALLY WANT TO EVALUATE. WE KNOW THAT WHEN IT ACTUALLY
COLLECT TAX INCREMENT IT DOES TAKE SOME CAPACITY AWAY
IN TERMS OF TAX REVENUE GENERATED FOR THE ENTIRE CITY.
SO I DO NOT I AM I THINK WE HAVE DIFFERENT APPROACH AND I
REALLY FIRMLY BELIEVE THAT AND I AT THIS MOMENT ARE FOR
WHILE RESOURCE NEIGHBORHOODS AND DEDICATED ONLY TO
AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND THEN TO INSTEAD OF BEING ABLE TO FOCUS
ON AFFORDABLE HOUSING BOND AND TALK ABOUT OUR BUYING
CAPACITY AND POTENTIALLY EVEN A REGIONAL BOND I THINK IS TAKING
RESOURCES AWAY FROM DEVELOPING THAT I REALLY LOOK FORWARD TO
THE ENERGY AND THE CAPACITY THAT WE SHOULD REALLY DRIVE TO
A 2028 REGIONAL HOUSING BOND. WE FAILED, YOU KNOW, JUST NOW
LATE LAST YEAR THAT WE COULDN'T ACTUALLY HAVE IT TOGETHER.
IT ACTUALLY IS REALLY HURTING OUR ABILITY TO BUILD MORE
AFFORDABLE HOUSING. WE KNOW THAT ACCORDING TO THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT THAT WE
ARE RUNNING OUT OF MONEY FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND THAT YOU
HAVE TO SPEND THE TIME FOR EACH PROPOSAL WHICH ACTUALLY GOING
TO TAKE SO MUCH LONGER. AND AS WE ALL KNOW IS GOING TO
TAKE TWO DECADES, THREE DECADES TO REALLY SEE THAT YIELDING ANY
TIME THE REVENUE COMING BACK TO THE CITY WE SHOULD SPEND THE
TIME AND RESOURCES ON A REGIONAL HOUSING BOND INSTEAD.
I SENSE THAT THIS CONVERSATION WILL CONTINUE.
I SPEAKING LAST AND SEEING NO ONE ELSE ON THE IN THE QUEUE I
WILL JUST ADD I AM I AM GOING TO SUPPORT THIS RESOLUTION
TODAY AS A MEMBER OF YOUR CAPITAL, AS A MEMBER OF THE
CAPITAL PLANNING COMMITTEE I HAVE CONCERNS ABOUT THE CITY'S
HISTORIC UNDERINVESTMENT IN OUR CAPITAL NEEDS AND GOING FORWARD
I THINK THERE IS A CONVERSATION WE NEED TO HAVE NOT JUST ABOUT
HOUSING BUT ABOUT ALL OF THE CAPITAL NEEDS THAT WE'RE GOING
TO HAVE ON THE WEST SIDE AND THROUGHOUT THE CITY TO
SUPPORT THE SIGNIFICANT HOUSING DEVELOPMENT THAT WE ARE
CONTEMPLATING. AND SO BUT I AM SUPPORTING THIS
AS IT IS AN EXPRESSION OF INTEREST AND I THINK THE
BEGINNING NOT THE END OF A CONVERSATION.
BUT AS WE GO FORWARD WITH THAT CONVERSATION I THINK WE NEED TO
THIS IS A LITTLE DIFFERENT FROM SOME OF THE CONCERNS THAT HAVE
BEEN RAISED. I THINK WE NEED TO THINK ABOUT
THE BROADER ARRAY OF INFRASTRUCTURE NEEDS THAT WE
HISTORICALLY AS A CITY HAVE NOT INVESTED ENOUGH AND ARE ONLY
GOING TO GROW. AND WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK, CAN
YOU CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 24 SUPERVISOR MELGAR I MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SAUDER SORTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WILTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN NO
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO I SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
AND SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANAGEMENT I THERE ARE TEN EYES
AND ONE NO WITH SUPERVISOR CHAN VOTING NO.
>> ALL RIGHT THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO
OUR 230 SPECIAL ORDER. >> YES, THE 230 SPECIAL ORDER
IS THE RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATION FOR MERITORIOUS
SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO AND WE'RE
GOING TO START OFF TODAY WITH DISTRICT SEVEN SUPERVISOR
MELGAR. >> THANK YOU.
PRESIDENT. AND IF AT DR. THAT OLIVER
AEROTECH COULD COME UP, PLEASE .
OH MY GOODNESS. I CAN'T BELIEVE HOW BIG YOUR
SON AND COLLEAGUES ARE. OUR KIDS WENT TO PRESCHOOL
TOGETHER SO OH MY GOODNESS. AND TODAY I HAVE THE GREAT
HONOR TO PRESENT A SPECIAL COMMENDATION TO SOMEONE I
BELIEVE IS A GIFT TO OUR WORLD AND OUR CITY AND COUNTY IN OUR
COMMUNITY. >> DR. DIANA ATTACHÉ DIANA HAS
DEDICATED OVER 25 YEARS THROUGH HER WORK IN ADVANCING EQUITY
CENTER POLICY AND PUBLIC HEALTH VIOLENCE PREVENTION, CHILD
AND FAMILY WELL-BEING AND COMMUNITY EMPOWERMENT.
JEANETTE HAS ALWAYS CENTERED THE WORK AROUND EQUITY
AND CHANGE. SERVING UNDER FOUR CONSECUTIVE
MAYORS, SHE HELD ROLES AT THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH,
THE DEPARTMENT OF CHILDREN, YOUTH AND FAMILIES
AND COMMUNITY BASED ORGANIZATIONS SERVING YOUTH
AND IMMIGRANTS. MOST RECENTLY DIANA SERVED AS
THE DIRECTOR OF POLICY AND PUBLIC AFFAIRS FOR THE SAN
FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT WHERE SHE SUPPORTED FORMER
CHIEF SCOTT IN HISTORIC REFORMS THAT HAVE BEEN RECOGNIZED
NATIONALLY AS THE DAUGHTER OF IMMIGRANTS AND A FELLOW SARA
DANA. DIANA CARRIES WITH HER A STRONG
SENSE OF RESPONSIBILITY TO ENSURE THAT OUR LIVED
EXPERIENCES AND OUR CONTRIBUTIONS TO SOCIETY ARE
NOT ERASED THAT WE DESERVE A SEAT AT THE TABLE AS IF SHE WAS
NOT ALREADY DOING ENOUGH THINGS IN THE WORLD AS A WORKING MOM
HELPING TO GUIDE MASSIVE REFORMS IN OUR POLICE, SHE
DECIDED TO PURSUE HER PH.D. AT THE UNIVERSITY OF SAN FRANCISCO
IN ORGANIZATION IN LEADERSHIP AND GRADUATED WITH HONORS ON
TOP OF ALREADY HAVING A MASTER'S OF PUBLIC HEALTH.
SHE IS ALSO THE FOUNDER AND CEO OF 80 STRATEGIES, WHICH IS A
FIRM THAT SUPPORTS MISSION DRIVEN LEADERS
IN ORGANIZATIONS. I AM IN AWE OF EVERYTHING THAT
YOU DO AND THAT YOU HAVE ACHIEVED THAT I CHAIR AND YOU
DO SO MUCH WITH GRACE AND HUMILITY.
YOU BRING PEOPLE IN, YOU BUILD A WIDER TENT.
YOU NEVER DISCOUNT OR DISCOURAGE OTHERS.
YOU ALWAYS TREAT EVERYONE WITH RESPECT.
I HOPE THAT MANY YOUNG PEOPLE OUT THERE WILL SEE YOU AND SEE
THEMSELVES THAT THEY TOO CAN BE AGENTS OF CHANGE IN THEM, BE
LIMITLESS IN ACHIEVING THEIR DREAMS.
I AM SO EXCITED THAT OUR MAYOR HAS SELECTED DIANA TO
LEAD THE DEPARTMENT OF THE STATUS OF WOMEN INTO ITS NEXT
CHAPTER. DIANA YOU ARE TRULY AN
INSPIRATION AND I KNOW THAT YOU WILL CONTINUE DOING THE HARD,
DIFFICULT WORK TO IMPROVE THE LIVES OF WOMEN.
GIRL NONBINARY PEOPLE HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO THANK YOU FOR
EVERYTHING YOU HAVE DONE AND I AM SO PROUD OF YOU.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
IT'S BUT A HOLD UP BECAUSE OTHER SUPERVISORS DON'T WANT TO
PILE ON. >> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR GREAT CHOICE. AND I JUST WANT TO SAY DEANNA
AS A COLLEAGUE OF YOURS ONLY BECAUSE THERE'S SO MANY PEOPLE
TO HONOR TODAY I'M GOING TO BE VERY BRIEF BUT IT HAS MEANT THE
WORLD TO ME TO BE YOUR COLLEAGUE COLLEAGUE OF YOURS
IN THE POLICE DEPARTMENT WHEN WE HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO WORK
ON POLICE REFORM FOR THE COUPLE OF YEARS THAT I WAS THERE
AND THEN BEING HERE HAVING AN OPPORTUNITY TO WORK WITH YOU
AND SEEING WHAT YOU'RE NOT THE NEXT THINGS YOU'RE GOING TO DO
AS A DEPARTMENT HEAD. SO I JUST WANT TO SAY
CONGRATULATIONS TO SUPERVISOR WALTON.
>> THANK YOU PRESIDENT MENEM AND I'M GOING TO BE BRIEF I WAS
NOT GOING TO SAY ANYTHING BUT THEN WHEN SUPERVISOR DORSEY
CHIMED IN I HAD TO MAKE SURE YOU KNEW AND UNDERSTOOD HOW
MUCH I APPRECIATE ALL OF YOUR WORK OVER THE YEARS.
I MEAN WE GO BACK TO OUR DAYS AT THE DEPARTMENT OF CHILDREN,
YOUTH AND FAMILIES BUT IT'S BEEN AMAZING TO WATCH YOUR WORK
AND I'M JUST EXCITED YOU'RE STILL WITH THE CITY FAMILY
AND THIS RECOGNITION IS WELL DESERVED.
>> CONGRATULATIONS. THANK YOU.
AND I WILL ECHO MY COLLEAGUES. >> CONGRATULATIONS, DR. R.J.
AND THE FLOOR IS YOURS. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
WELL, FIRST OF ALL, I JUST WANT TO SAY GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT
MANDOLIN SUPERVISOR MELGAR AND THE MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. OBVIOUSLY I HAVE TO MAKE SURE
THAT I HOLD ON TO, YOU KNOW, THE FORMALITY WELL DONE FOR
YEARS. MORE THAN ANYTHING I WANT TO
JUST SAY THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR SUPPORT.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR WE ALSO HAVE WORKED TOGETHER FOR MANY, MANY
DECADES AND I ABSOLUTELY WANT TO THANK YOU FOR THIS
INCREDIBLE HONOR TO STAND IN FRONT OF YOU AND TO BE
HONORED IN THIS MONTH IN PARTICULAR.
IT MEANS THE WORLD TO ME TO STAND IN FRONT OF THE COMMUNITY
IN FRONT OF MY FAMILY, IN FRONT OF EVERYBODY THAT I'VE WORKED
WITH FOR DECADES. AND SO I JUST WANT TO THANK YOU
AS ANOTHER FELLOW SALVADORIAN AND TO AND TELL YOU THAT I AM
HERE DEDICATED READY TO ROLL UP MY SLEEVES AND WANT TO MAKE
SURE THAT I CONTINUE DOING THE WORK THAT WE DO TO STRIVE FOR
WOMEN, GIRLS AND NON-BINARY COMMUNITIES BUT ALSO FOR THE
COMMUNITY AT LARGE HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
VERY EXCITED OFF OF THE NEW ROLE AND I DO WANT TO THANK THE
MAYOR AND THE MAYOR'S OFFICE FOR ALL THE WORK AND BELIEVING
AND TRUSTING ME TO CONTINUE MOVING FORWARD THE WORK THAT I
SO PASSIONATELY BELIEVE IN. I ALSO WANT TO SINCERELY THANK
MY HUSBAND, MY BEST FRIEND, MY LIFE PARTNER WAS ACTUALLY AN
ARC STARTED RIGHT NOW WITH MY SON IN ANOTHER SON IN THE
NATIONAL BOXING TOURNAMENT. I OBVIOUSLY WANT TO THANK MY
CHILDREN THAT ARE HERE PRESENT JOAQUIN CALI WHO'S IN THE
AUDIENCE GED SALLY AND ALEX WHO COULDN'T JOIN US TODAY.
WE HAVE A BIG FAMILY AND I JUST WANT TO THANK EVERY SINGLE ONE
OF MY CHILDREN FOR ALLOWING ME TO BE A MOM, FOR ALLOWING ME TO
LEARN ABOUT LIFE AND MOST IMPORTANTLY FOR ALLOWING ME TO
BE ABLE TO WORK FOR THIS CITY. >> I ALSO WANT TO HONOR MY
MOTHER AND FATHER. I WOULDN'T BE HERE WITHOUT THEM
AND WITHOUT THE STRONG LINEAGE OF SALVADORIAN ROOTS.
AS SUPERVISOR MELGAR SAID I STAND IN FRONT OF YOU TODAY
WITH A LONG LINEAGE OF SACRIFICE.
MY FAMILY WERE WAR REFUGEES. I CAME AND ASPIRED ONE DAY TO
ACTUALLY BUILD A LIFE OF SAFETY ,A LIFE OF PROSPERITY HERE
IN THE UNITED STATES AND THEY SOUGHT ASYLUM AND THEY HAD FOUR
DAUGHTERS INCLUDING MYSELF. I'M THE ELDEST OF FOUR AND I'M
PROUD TO SAY THAT I AM ONE OF FOUR DAUGHTERS THAT ARE ALL
GRADUATED, HAVE A DOCTORATE AND MY SISTERS ARE PURSUING
THEIR DREAMS AND SO I DO WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THEM AND ALL THE
HARD WORK THAT THEY'VE DONE. >> AND FINALLY I JUST WANT TO
SAY IT WOULD BE REMISS IF I DIDN'T MENTION THAT TODAY IS
THE ACTUAL DAY THE NATIONAL DAY OF REMEMBRANCE FOR THE U.S.
INDIAN BOARDING SCHOOLS AND THE HARSH HISTORY THAT OUR NATION
FACED. AND SO WHILE I AM HONORED,
DEEPLY HONORED TO BE RECOGNIZED TODAY, I HAVE TO ACKNOWLEDGE
THE DAY OF TODAY AND SERVE SOME OF THE HARSH HISTORY FOR US TO
CONTINUE MAKING SURE THAT WE DON'T REPEAT THE SAME HISTORY
THAT THIS NATION HAS SOMETIMES UNFORTUNATELY TRAGICALLY MOVED
FORWARD. >> AND SO FOR THOSE CHILDREN
THAT WERE FORCED INTO BOARDING SCHOOLS, THERE ARE PARALLELS
TODAY WITH CHILDREN IN THE LATINO COMMUNITY THAT ARE ALSO
BEING SEPARATED BY THEIR WITH SEPARATED FROM THEIR MOTHERS,
FROM THEIR FAMILIES, FROM THEIR FATHERS, FROM THEIR CARETAKERS.
>> AND I ASK YOU I WOULDN'T BE ME IF I DIDN'T PLEAD AND SAY AT
THE END OF THIS TO SAY THANK YOU.
BUT I ALSO ASK YOU TO ROLL UP YOUR SLEEVES AND CONTINUE
DEFENDING ALL THE VALUES THAT WE STAND FOR HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO FOR THE LATINO COMMUNITY.
>> SO THANK YOU AND IT'S AN HONOR.
AND I LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING WITH THOSE BIGGER NAMES.
>> CONGRATULATIONS AGAIN, DR. ARCHIE DISTRICT NINE SUPERVISOR
FIELDER THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MAN LEMON YOU DON'T BELIEVE FOR
OF CLASS CLOSELY THAT IS THE FAILED ACTIONS JUVENILE POLIO I
TODAY IN HONOR OF LATINO HERITAGE MONTH I AM DEEPLY
HONORED TODAY TO PRESENT A COMMENDATION FOR THE LEADERS OF
FAITH IN ACTION BAY AREA SAN FRANCISCO WHO ARE BASED IN THE
HEART OF DISTRICT NINE. >> THIS GROUP REPRESENTS
NEWCOMER AND IMMIGRANT FAMILIES ,MANY OF WHOM ARE HOMELESS
AND LIVING IN SHELTERS, SOME OF WHOM HAVE HAD TO SLEEP WITH
THEIR KIDS ON THE STREETS OF SAN FRANCISCO.
THEY'VE HAD TO LEAD THEIR COUNTRY TO PROTECT THEIR
FAMILIES AND BUILD A LIFE HERE IN OUR CITY A SANCTUARY CITY
THAT WELCOMES ALL AND THRIVES PRECISE ONLY BECAUSE OF OUR
IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES WHERE ALL BELONG AND ALL ARE WELCOME.
>> THEY ARE PRIMARILY MOMS WHO HAVE BECOME POWERFUL COMMUNITY
LEADERS WHO ARE ADVOCATING TIRELESSLY FOR HOMELESS
FAMILIES SO THAT NO CHILD IS LEFT TO SLEEP ON THE STREETS.
AS YOU KNOW THIS YEAR ALONE, FAITH AND ACTION LEADERS HAVE
HELPED CHANGE OUR FAMILIES SHELTER LENGTH OF STAY POLICY
TO ONE THAT IS MUCH MORE SENSIBLE AND JUST AND PERHAPS
MORE IMPORTANTLY, THEIR ADVOCACY LED TO PROTECTING
AND INCREASING HOUSING SUBSIDIES FOR FAMILIES IN THIS
YEAR'S BUDGET IN ORDER TO EXPAND VIABLE EXITS FROM
HOMELESSNESS. >> AND WITH THAT I'M GOING TO
ADDRESS THE REST OF MY REMARKS IN SPANISH TO HONOR THIS
INSPIRING GROUP CRISIS AT TODAS LAS ELLOS NEITHER AS VISIONARY
AS THEIR FOR INACTION WAS SAID AS AN DIMOSTRATO
AND UNCOMPROMISING FERALS INTEREST C CON LA COMUNIDAD LA
FAMILIA AS IMMIGRANT THIS CABOOSE CAN LOGRAR IN LA VIDA
ESTABLISHED BARROS WHOSE FAMILIAS AND WESTERN I SEE YOU
THAT CENTURION AND MOSTRADO JUNTOS THOUGH THE WEST DANIEL
U.S. IS NOT UNINFORMED OR RAPIDLY THEM INTO SOVEREIGNS
WHOSE EXPERIENCIAS DOLOROSA ROSA'S EITHER SUBSERVIENT
AND THIS THE BIBLE ALLOWS SYSTEM AS VIDAS DE LA CIUDAD
GANG CRIADO BARRERA'S IN WHO US BUT ON THE MAS BONITO DE SU
MANERA THE ORGANIZER IS GAY NO SOLO ON PRESENT LOCATION IS
SINO GET THEM BEGIN ON OFFER TO SEE THE SOLUTION IS CONCRETE AS
FACADES AND THAT THOSE BEEN INVESTIGATED DOES E ANALYSIS
LOGICAL PERSON THUNDEROUS CON UN PRESS A PUESTO REAL ARE LOOK
IT SO NECESITA BARACK OBAMA CON I FELT THAT EVERY BNF IN THE
YARD BELLA LA FAMILIA SYNAGOGUE IN SAN FRANCISCO EBER GET
TOGETHER SUBMIT THE FINAL AS GRADE CAN NO GO HAMAS ISAIAH
THOMAS GET I NINOS GUYANESE THE WERMAN IN LIKE GUY IN OR THING
ON MIDDLE THE NO SUBURB DONATE TOLD ME THE PAUL A.J.
>> IT UP AND DITO THANK TODOS STATUS IS RECIBIDO FUERTE ASI
IGUANAS BUT I CONTINUE OUT IN LA LUCIA HUNTERS BUT I PUT
PROTO HERE AT TODOS LOS NINOS PRESS YOUR SOURCE AGAINST THE
ANIMALS GET GARANTIZAR UN FEDERAL MY HAIR WHICH SEEMS
GARCIA'S PURSUE DEDICATION BUT SADLY THAT IS IN SPITE OUTDOOR
AS A PATROL DOG LOOK AND BARREN WEST I SEE GUERRILLA
THIS SAN FRANCISCO WAS DEAD AS THE MORE STRAND LOOK AS SAID
UNA VERY LADDU THAT SEE YOU THAT SANTUARIO GRACIOUS PEOPLE
WHEN I STARTED THIS MEAN EMBRACE VERONICA COULD ALSO
LEAD THEIR ACTIVE ORDER FOR AN AXIOM GOOD AFTERNOON MY NAME IS
LAUREN AKOTO VERONICA KYOTO POLICIES FOOD SO THE SISTER
LEADER THE PHENIX SHE IS ONE OF THE LEADERS OF FAITH IN ACTION
AND SHE'S HERE TO WANT TO FIRST AND FOREMOST SHE WANTS TO
APPRECIATE THE RECOMMENDATION TODAY BY SUPERVISOR JACKIE
FIELDER
. ALL RIGHT.
SO I'M GOING TO SUMMARIZE WHAT SHE'S SAYING IS THAT WE KNOW
THAT WE'RE HERE TOGETHER AND I'M SPEAKING FOR HER.
WE KNOW THAT WE'RE HERE TOGETHER AND WE KNOW THAT WE'RE
BEING RECOGNIZED BUT WE WANT TO KNOW I WANT YOU ALL TO KNOW
THAT THE FIGHT DOESN'T STOP HERE.
THE FIGHT CONTINUES BEYOND HERE AND THAT WE FIGHT TO MAKE SURE
THAT THERE ARE NO CHILDREN LEFT OUT IN THE STREET SLEEPING ON
THE STREET AND OUR FIGHT DOESN'T STOP.
WE WANT TO BE ABLE TO REACH THE FACES, THE EAR, THE MINDS OF
THOSE WHO ARE NOT WITH US, WHO DON'T KNOW THE FIGHT AND THE
STRUGGLE THAT WE PURSUE BUT WE REACH OUT TO THEM TO LET THEM
KNOW THAT OUR FIGHT AND OUR GOAL OVERALL TO NOT LET
CHILDREN BE OUT ON THE STREET DOESN'T STOP AND IT'LL CONTINUE
AND WE HOPE WITH THEIR SUPPORT THIS
THEY LET ME SAY GOOD AFTERNOON. >> MY NAME IS MARIA MARTINEZ
AND I'M THE PRESIDENT OF YOUNG PEOPLE OF THE DIRECTIVE TABLE
AND LEADER OF FAITH IN ACTION. AS WE'VE SPOKEN BEFORE, WE WANT
TO BE APPRECIATIVE OF THE COMMON COMMENDATION DONE TODAY
AND WE WANT TO ECHO THE VOICE THAT THE STRUGGLE IS NOT DONE.
WE WANT TO CONTINUE THE FIGHT TO MAKE SURE THERE ARE NO MORE
CHILDREN ON THE STREETS BUT ALSO TO BE CARING FOR THE
ELDERLY. >> THANK YOU FOR
COMING. >> ALL RIGHT, DESTRY ACTS TEN
SUPERVISOR WALTON, THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THANK. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
PRESIDENT, MANAGEMENT AND COLLEAGUES.
FIRST OF ALL I JUST WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR MELGAR
AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR MAKING SURE THAT WE HAD THIS
CELEBRATION TODAY AT THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND ALSO WANT TO
MAKE SURE THAT THANK TRACY BROWN GUAJARDO FROM MY OFFICE
WHO ALSO PLAYED A MAJOR ROLE IN MAKING SURE THIS HAPPENED
TODAY BUT IT IS NOW MY HONOR TODAY TO PRESENT A SPECIAL
COMMENDATION TO SOMEONE WHOSE LIFE WORK HAS BEEN A BLUEPRINT
FOR SERVICE, LEADERSHIP AND COMMUNITY TRANSFORMATION.
MS. RUTH BARAJAS RUTH IS A PROUD SAN FRANCISCO NATIVE
WHOSE JOURNEY AND COMMUNITY WORK BEGAN WHEN SHE WAS JUST 16
YEARS OLD AS ONE OF THE FIRST YOUNG PEOPLE IN THE CHALK
PROGRAM. BY 17 SHE KNEW HER CALLING WAS
TO BECOME THE DIRECTOR OF CHALK.
AND BY 21 SHE HAD ACHIEVED THAT DREAM.
THAT EARLY DETERMINATION IS A THREAD THAT HAS CARRIED THROUGH
EVERY CHAPTER OF HER CAREER FOR NEARLY 25 YEARS.
RUTH SERVES AS THE DIRECTOR OF WORKFORCE AND REENTRY AT THE
BAY AREA COMMUNITY RESOURCES GROWING PROGRAMS ACROSS ALAMEDA
AND CONTRA COSTA COUNTIES WHILE KEEPING STRONG ROOTS IN SAN
FRANCISCO, SHE BUILT REENTRY SERVICES, EXPANDED INTO HOUSING
AND CREATED WORKFORCE PROGRAMS FOR UNDOCUMENTED YOUTH
AND YOUNG PEOPLE LIVING IN HOPE TO SERVE COMMUNITIES
IN DISTRICT TEN. RUTH IS ALSO A VISIONARY
COLLABORATOR. SHE HELPED LAUNCH THE ROADMAP
TO PEACE INITIATIVE AND THE RESET JUSTICE COLLABORATIVE.
SHE CO-FOUNDED THE CITIES MY BROTHER AND SISTERS KEEPER
YOUTH COUNCIL AND LATER THE BAR BARBER PATHWAY PROGRAM AND THE
CITY'S FIRST BARBER EXPO OPENING NEW DOORS FOR
ENTREPRENEURS AND THE FORMERLY INCARCERATED ALIKE.
WHEN COVID 19 PANDEMIC BEGAN, RUTH'S LEADERSHIP WAS
INDISPENSABLE. SHE HELPED LAUNCH THE LATINO
TASK FORCE RESOURCE HUBS FIRST IN THE MISSION THE EXCELSIOR,
THEN BAYVIEW AND VISITATION VALLEY.
THESE HAVE SERVED THE ENTIRE FAMILIES FROM SMALL CHILDREN TO
SENIORS. HER COMMITMENT TO BUILDING
ACROSS THE LIFE COURSE OF INDIVIDUALS HAS STRENGTHENED
OUR CITY IN PROFOUND WAYS IN RECENT YEARS.
RUTH WAS CRITICAL TO SUPPORTING SALT AND THE PACIFIC ISLANDER
COMMUNITY TO LAUNCH THE NATION'S FIRST PACIFIC ISLANDER
CULTURAL DISTRICT A LANDMARK ACHIEVEMENT THAT SPANS ACROSS
DISTRICTS NINE, TEN AND 11. BEYOND SAN FRANCISCO, RUTH HAS
MADE AN IMPACT STATEWIDE AND NATIONALLY SERVING ON THE
BOARD OF NATIONAL YOUTH EMPLOYMENT COALITION,
CONTRIBUTING TO THE CALIFORNIA OPPORTUNITY YOUTH NETWORK
AND SERVING ON THE CITY'S WORKFORCE ALIGNMENT COMMITTEE.
>> HER ACADEMIC PATH REFLECTS THE RESILIENCE
AND DETERMINATION SHE INSTILLS IN OTHERS STARTING AT COMMUNITY
COLLEGE. THEN ADVANCING TO MILLS WHERE
SHE EARNED DEGREES IN SOCIOLOGY AND URBAN EDUCATION.
TODAY SHE CONTINUES HER JOURNEY AS THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF
THE LATINO TASK FORCE AT MISSION LANGUAGE VOCATIONAL
SCHOOL. BUT PERHAPS HER PROUDEST TITLE
IS NOT DIRECTOR OR EXECUTIVE. IT IS MOTHER AND GRANDMOTHER.
SHE IS THE MOTHER OF CALI AND CARLOS AND THE GRANDMOTHER
OF THREE YEAR OLD JUNIOR WHO NO DOUBT WILL INHERIT HER STRENGTH
AND COMPASSION. RUTH IS A TESTAMENT TO WHAT
HAPPENS WHEN PASSION MEETS PURPOSE.
SHE HAS LIFTED UP COUNTLESS YOUNG PEOPLE, FAMILIES
AND COMMUNITIES AND HAS DONE SO WITH GRACE, DETERMINATION
AND LOVE. CONGRATULATIONS RUTH AND THANK
YOU FOR EVERYTHING YOU HAVE GIVEN TO OUR CITY
AND COMMUNITIES. >> YOU.
>> SO RUTH, YOU CAN SPEAK IN A MOMENT BUT SUPERVISOR MELGAR
ALSO WANTS TO SPEAK. >> SO GO AHEAD.
SURPRISE ME FIRST. >> SUPERVISOR WALTON.
EXCELLENT CHOICE. >> RUTH, YOU ARE ONE OF THESE
UNSUNG ANGELS OF OUR WORLD. IN ADDITION TO ALL THE
WONDERFUL THINGS THAT SUPERVISOR WALTON JUST SAID, I
HAVE HAD THE PLEASURE OF WORKING WITH YOU IN THE HONOR
OF WATCHING YOU CHANGE THE LIVES OF COUNTLESS GENERATIONS
OF YOUNG PEOPLE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
YOUR DEDICATION TO THE DEVELOPMENT OF OUR YOUTH TO THE
LOVE THAT YOU BRING IN THESE INTERACTIONS TO SUPPORTING OUR
COMMUNITY AS THEY GROW AND TO KEEP THEM SAFE AND WITH ACCESS
TO OPPORTUNITY. IT'S BEEN BREATHTAKING.
YOU ARE TRULY JUST A ROCK STAR AND I AM SO GLAD THAT WE'RE
HONORING YOU TODAY. JUST YOU ARE A BEACON OF HOPE.
AND I'M SO GLAD THAT YOU HAVE YOU KNOW YOU'RE KEEPING IT
GOING. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK
YOU, PRESIDENT. >> AND I JUST WANT TO ECHO MY
COLLEAGUES AND SAY THAT YOUR IMPACT ON DISTRICT NINE IS
IMMEASURABLE AS EVIDENCED BY THE AMAZING LEVEL OF APPLAUSE
IN THE ROOM TODAY. IT FEELS LIKE ALL THE MISSION
IS HERE. GREAT CHOICE ADVISOR.
>> AND JUST WANTED TO THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMITMENT TO THE
YOUTH FOR YOUR WORK ON VIOLENCE PREVENTION, JOB DEVELOPMENT,
SUPPORTING OUR IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. THANK YOU.
WELL, THANK YOU ALL. NOW IT'S YOUR TURN.
>> YEAH. FIRST I WANT TO SAY THAT I'M
JOINED BY MY SON CALLIE. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON AND THE D-10 OFFICE.
A SPECIAL SHOUT OUT TO TEN LEGISLATIVE AIDE AND COMMUNITY
LEADER TRACY BROWN GALLARDO. >> A TRUE A TRUE COMMUNITY
WARRIOR AND SOMEONE I'M LUCKY ENOUGH TO HAVE AS A MENTOR.
IF YOU KNOW ME, YOU KNOW I HAVE A LOT TO SAY BUT I TEND TO GET
A LITTLE TONGUE TIED WHEN I TALK ABOUT MYSELF OR WHEN I'M
GETTING ACKNOWLEDGMENTS. BUT THIS MEANS A LOT TO ME.
THANK YOU TO THE FULL BOARD. >> I'M A PROUD SAN FRANCISCO
NATIVE. I BEGAN DOING COMMUNITY WORK
WHEN I WAS 16 YEARS OLD AND WHEN I WHEN I JOINED CHALK
AND IT LITERALLY SAVED MY LIFE. I KNEW THEN AT THAT YOUNG AGE
THAT THIS WAS MY PURPOSE, THAT I WAS MEANT TO BE A TOOL FOR
THE CREATOR TO USE TO HELP OTHER PEOPLE TO SUPPORT MY
COMMUNITY. IT'S BEEN ALMOST 30 YEARS BUT I
KNOW THAT I HAVE MORE TO DO. >> BUT I ALSO KNOW THAT I DON'T
DO THIS BY MYSELF. NOT ONLY DO I STAND ON THE
SHOULDERS OF ANCESTORS BUT I STAND ON THE SHOULDERS OF MY
FRIENDS, MY FAMILY AND MY COMMUNITY, MANY OF WHOM ARE
IN THE ROOM. >> I FIRST BECAME PASSIONATE
ABOUT HELPING YOUNG PEOPLE FIND AND USE THEIR VOICE BECAUSE I
KNOW WHAT USING MINE DID FOR ME .
I BECAME PASSIONATE ABOUT CREATING ECONOMIC OPPORTUNITY
FOR YOUNG PEOPLE BECAUSE I KNOW WHAT IT WAS LIKE TO GROW UP
WITH A SINGLE MOM WHO STRUGGLED TO PROVIDE FOR HER CHILDREN.
I'M A PROUD DAUGHTER OF AN IMMIGRANT FATHER.
REST IN PEACE AND I CARRY THE VALUE OF IMMIGRANTS WITH ME
EVERY DAY. I BECAME PASSIONATE ABOUT
REENTRY BECAUSE I SUPPORTED MY BROTHER THROUGH MULTIPLE PRISON
SENTENCES AND TWO STRIKES. HE NOW OWNS HIS OWN MOVING
COMPANY AND IS A HOMEOWNER IN Z TEN.
>> YEAH. GIVE IT UP.
>> THEY ARE ALL THEY ARE ALL PART OF MY PURPOSE AND IT KEEPS
ME GROUNDED AND WHY I HAVE DEDICATED MY LIFE TO SERVICE.
I NEED TO GIVE A SPECIAL THANK YOU TO MY SONS.
THEY SPENT THEIR ENTIRE CHILDHOOD SHARING ME WITH SO
MANY OTHER YOUNG PEOPLE AND I THANK THEM FOR THAT.
I KNOW IT WASN'T ALWAYS EASY AND I NEED TO GIVE A SPECIAL
THANK YOU TO MARTY WEINSTEIN WHO COULDN'T MAKE IT TODAY.
A TWO DECADE MENTOR OF MINE WHO TAUGHT ME SO MANY LESSONS ABOUT
SERVICE, HOW TO TREAT OTHERS AND HOW TO BE A LEADER.
>> AND I NEED TO THANK MY MOTHER WHO'S IN THE ROOM.
SHE'S THE STRONGEST WOMAN I KNOW AND HER STRENGTH LIVES
IN ME. AND LAST BUT NOT LEAST, THERE'S
A HANDFUL OF YOUNG PEOPLE IN THE ROOM AS WELL AS SOME
AMAZING ADULTS WHO ARE YOUNG PEOPLE IN PROGRAMS I MANAGED
OVER THE YEARS WHO I'VE BEEN BLESSED TO SUPPORT IN ONE WAY
OR ANOTHER. I DON'T KNOW THAT YOU
UNDERSTAND HOW MUCH YOU GUYS HAVE GIVEN BACK TO ME.
>> THANK YOU FOR TRUSTING ME. AT CHUCK WE HAVE A FEW CORE
VALUES AT CHUCK WE HAVE A FEW CORE VALUES WE FOLLOW.
>> I'D LIKE TO SHARE TWO WITH YOU AS I CLOSE.
FIRST THAT THIS IS A LIFESTYLE NOT A JOB.
>> AND SECOND, THAT WE UTILIZE OUR LIFE EXPERIENCES TO
POSITIVELY AFFECT THE COMMUNITY.
>> THANK YOU FOR SEEING ME HERE
. >> ALL RIGHTS.
>> DISTRICT 11 SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU PERSONALLY AND ALL MY
TEAM AND I TOO. >> TO BEGIN I ALSO WANT TO
THANK SUPERVISOR FIELDER AND SUPERVISOR MALKA AND ALSO
TRACY BROWN FROM D-10. THIS IS LIKE BEAUTIFUL.
I OWE THIS IMMIGRANT STARS A BEAUTIFUL AND MY HONOR TODAY
IT'S ALSO BEAUTIFUL. I AM SO PROUD TO HONOR ALMA
CASTELLANOS, A SAN FRANCISCO NATIVE.
THANK YOU FOR THOSE CLAPPING. >> SHE'S AMAZING.
SURE. SHE ALSO SPENT HER ENTIRE LIFE
DEEPLY ROOTED IN THE EXCELSIOR NEIGHBORHOOD.
SHE HAS LIVED AND WORKED IN DISTRICT 11 FOR THE PAST 17
YEARS. >> SHE'S JUST A PROUD MOTHER,
GRANDMOTHER AND COMMITTED COMMUNITY LEADERS.
>> UPLIFTING THE NEIGHBORHOOD THAT HER FAMILY CALLS HOME.
>> AS THE DIRECTOR OF OPERATION AT KULTURA AND THE VICE
PRESIDENT AFTER EXACT AFTER EXCELSIOR ACTION GROUP CBD
BOARD SERIOUS TIRELESSLY ADVOCATING FOR SMALL BUSINESS
IN UNDERSERVED COMMUNITIES LIKE DISTRICT 11.
>> SUE IS ALSO TILE'S TIRELESSLY ADVOCATING FOR SMALL
BUSINESS AND ALSO PLANS TO MENTAL ROLE IN HELPING SMALL
BUSINESS THAT THRIVES WITH TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE
AND COMMUNITY CENTER INITIATIVES DURING THE COVID 19
PANDEMIC. >> ALMA SERVE AS THE EXECUTIVE
RESOURCES TOP COORDINATOR FOR THE LATINO TASK FORCE CASA
DIABLO AT A TIME WHEN MOST WEST SHELTER LAYING IN PLACE
AND STEP SHE STEPPED UP SUPPORTING FOOD DISTRIBUTIONS.
>> PERSONALLY DELIVER FOOD BOXES TO FAMILY IN NEED
AND ALSO SUPPORTING TESTING AND VACCINATION AT QUOKKA
AMAZON PARK. >> THANK YOU FOR THAT.
>> ALMA'S COMMITMENT EXTENDS FAR BEYOND EMERGENCY RESPONSE.
SHE HAS SUPPORTED CRITICAL PROJECTS AIMED AT ECONOMIC
EMPOWERMENT INCLUDING HER WHAT MISSION STREET VENDORS DURING
THE TEMPORARY VENDING BAN. SHE ASSISTED MULTIPLE VENDORS
TO SECURE A STORE FOR AND SPACE SPACES TO CONTINUE THEIR SMALL
BUSINESS OPERATION AND PRESERVING THEN LIKELIHOOD
AND HONORING THE CULTURAL VIBRANCY OF THE CORRIDOR.
THROUGH HER DEDICATION, COMPASSION AND STRATEGIC
LEADERSHIP, ALMA CASTANEDA'S CONTINUE TO SHAPE A MORE
RESILIENT, INCLUSIVE AND THRIVING FUTURE FOR SAN
FRANCISCO AND THE EXCELSIOR. THANK YOU FOR EVERYTHING THAT
YOU HAVE DONE AND THAT YOU WILL DO.
>> THANK YOU ALMA. SO HONOR TO HONOR YOU TODAY
AND AND BEFORE YOU SPEAK. >> SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK
YOU, PRESIDENT. >> GREAT CHOICE.
DIRECTOR CHEN ONCE AGAIN, ALMA IT'S BEEN GREAT TO GET TO KNOW
YOU IN THIS NEW JOB AND YOUR LOVE FOR THE COMMUNITY IS SO
CLEAR. EVERY TIME YOU'RE OUT TALKING
TO SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS, TALKING TO VENDORS, TALKING
WITH CITY ADMINISTRATION IT'S JUST SO CLEAR YOUR DEDICATION
GOES ABOVE AND BEYOND WHAT WHAT ANYONE COULD REALLY HAVE FOR
THIS PARTICULAR ROLE THAT YOU HOLD IN SAN FRANCISCO AND FOR
ESPECIALLY FOR OUR LATINO IMMIGRANT COMMUNITY YOUR YOUR
COMPASSION IS IS JUST REALLY BEAUTIFUL AND IT'S WE'RE REALLY
LUCKY TO HAVE YOU SERVING DISTRICT 11 AND DISTRICT NINE
AND REALLY THE WHOLE CITY. SO THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU TO TWO MORE SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU
ALMA THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR EVERYTHING YOU'VE DONE.
IT HAS BEEN REALLY BREATHTAKING TO WATCH YOU STEP UP
IN LEADERSHIP THROUGH YOUR WORK AT BCR AND TAKING ON THIS ROLE
LIKE LED TO SUPPORTING OUR SMALL BUSINESSES ARE FOLKS WHO
ARE THEN DOING ALL OF THIS JUST SHOWS WHAT A WONDERFUL GENEROUS
PERSON YOU ARE BUT ALSO THAT YOU'RE PUTTING YOUR SKILLS, YOU
KNOW TO THE USE OF THE COMMUNITY THAT NEEDS YOU.
NOT EVERYONE PUTS THEMSELVES OUT THERE WHEN THEY'RE NEEDED
AND SO THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR EVERYTHING YOU DO AN EXCELLENT
CHOICE. >> SUPERVISOR CHEN SUPERVISOR
WALTON OBVIOUSLY THERE ARE A LOT OF PEOPLE BEING HONORED
TODAY THAT I WOULD LOVE OF COURSE TO JUST SAY SOME SOME
WORDS ABOUT BUT I REALLY JUST WANT TO APPRECIATE YOU FOR
BEING SOMEONE WHO NOT JUST FOCUSES ON EMPOWERMENT BUT YOU
ALSO UNDERSTAND THE IMPORTANCE OF WORKING CROSS-CULTURALLY
AND PROVIDING OPPORTUNITIES FOR EVERYONE.
>> SO I JUST WANT YOU TO KNOW WE SEE YOU APPRECIATE YOU
AND THIS IS WELL DESERVED. >> THANK YOU.
CONGRATULATIONS. >> THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
THANK YOU, SUPERVISORS. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK
YOU TO THE WHOLE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FIRST AND FOREMOST
I'D LIKE TO START BY SAYING I STAND BEFORE YOU AS A PROUD
MEXICAN SALVADORAN DAUGHTER OF IMMIGRANTS.
>> I SAY THAT WITH PRIDE BECAUSE AS THE FIRST
GRANDDAUGHTER FIRST BORN DAUGHTER I HAVE BEEN A
COMMUNITY MEMBER SINCE I COULD SPEAK FOR THE SIMPLE FACT THAT
I HAVE BEEN A TRANSLATOR FOR MY GRANDPARENTS TRANSLATOR FOR THE
FAMILY, TRANSLATOR FOR THE COMMUNITY ADVOCATING FOR FOR MY
FAMILY COMMUNITY MY FRIENDS, MY COLLEAGUES.
>> THIS WORK NEVER STOPS. I SAY WE PRAY BECAUSE I
REPRESENT MAYA WELL. IT'S MY MOTHER WHO IS HERE WITH
ME MY UNCLE JOE, MY CHILDREN, MY GRANDCHILD, MY ENTIRE
FAMILY, MY FRIENDS AND MY COLLEAGUES.
I COULDN'T HAVE DONE THIS AND I WOULDN'T BE HERE WITHOUT THEM
AND WITHOUT YOU GUYS. I AM HONORED TO BE HERE AS A
SAN FRANCISCO NATIVE TO BE RECOGNIZED BY THE VERY CITY
THAT RAISED ME IS A BIG ACCOMPLISHMENT.
I AM SO THANKFUL TO HAVE BEEN A PART OF HISTORY IN SAN
FRANCISCO FROM STARTING WITH THE LATINO TASK FORCE TO
HELPING START THE HEART OF THE EXCELSIOR CASA BOYLE TO NOW
DIRECTOR OF OPERATIONS AT CULTURE.
>> I THANK YOU AND I HUMBLY ACCEPT THIS OPPORTUNITY
AND WONDERFUL ACKNOWLEDGMENT. >> I REALLY WANT TO THANK RUTH
BARAJAS WHO ACTUALLY GAVE ME MY OPPORTUNITY AT LATINO TASK
FORCE MBA SENIOR TO BE RECOGNIZED TODAY ALONGSIDE HER
OMAR THE GREAT AS WELL FROM LATINO TASK FORCE.
>> IT IS TRULY, TRULY EVERYTHING.
I ALSO WANT TO SAY A SPECIAL THANK YOU TO WILLIAM ORTIZ
CARTAGENA FOR ALSO SEEING ME AND GIVING ME THE OPPORTUNITY
TO TAKE ON THIS ROLE OF DIRECTOR OF OPERATIONS AT
GRACIAS. >> WELL I WANT TO THANK MY
PARTNER AGAIN. COMMUNITY WORK IS 24 HOURS A
DAY SEVEN DAYS A WEEK. MY CHILDREN, MY FAMILY THANK
YOU FOR GIVING ME PATIENCE AND GIVING ME GRACE
AND ALLOWING ME TO BE FOR THE COMMUNITY LIKE I AM FOR THEM AT
HOME. >> EVERYTHING I DO I DO WITH
THE LOVE THAT I HAVE FOR THEM AND FOR THE LOVE I HAVE FOR THE
COMMUNITY. >> I ALSO STAND BEFORE YOU GUYS
TO REALLY ASKS YOU GUYS WHEN IT'S BUDGET SEASON AGAIN
REMEMBER US THAT ARE BEING HONORED WHEN YOU STAND HERE YOU
SAY YOU APPRECIATE THE WORK WE DO AND YOU LOVE WHAT WE DO.
REMEMBER THESE FACES WERE THE ONES THAT ARE STANDING HERE DAY
AND NIGHT ADVOCATING FOR NOT JUST OURSELVES BUT FOR
EVERYBODY IN OUR COMMUNITIES. >> SO AGAIN, I THANK YOU ALL
VERY MUCH. GRACIAS TO ALL THE COMMUNITY.
THANK YOU TO EVERYBODY YOU CAN A LA LUCHA DEL
DISTRICT ONE SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT MAN DOMAIN
COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE THE HONOR TO RECOGNIZE JOSE AGUAYO
WHO IS THE OWNER OF BABO. I PRODUCE IN THE OUTER BUBBLE
BUBBLE I PRODUCE WAS ESTABLISHED APPROXIMATELY 45
YEARS AGO ON A UNIQUE BLOCK OF THE OUTER RICHMOND.
JOSE AND HIS WIFE MARIA BEGAN OPERATING THE GROCERY STORE
IN 2014 AND THEY'VE BEEN ESTABLISH THEIR BUSINESS THERE
. NOT ONLY THAT, THEY ARE TRULY A
UNIQUE IMMIGRANT STORY IN THE RICHMOND AND IN SAN FRANCISCO
YOU SHOULD MEET THIS AMAZING FAMILY.
I WANT YOUR ENTIRE FAMILY TO COME UP AND BECAUSE I THINK
ONCE I INTRODUCE THEM AND SAY TELL THEIR STORY YOU WILL KNOW
WHY THAT THIS IS A FAMILY THAT WHITE LATINO HERITAGE MONTH IS
REALLY WHY WE DO WHAT WE DO. THIS IS A FAMILY THAT PARENTS
WHO WORK REALLY HARD DEDICATED ARE LIVE RAISING THREE AMAZING
CHILDREN AND I THINK THAT AS THEY CONTINUE TO GROW THEY WILL
BE ONE OF THESE LEADERS THAT COMING BACK IN THIS CHAMBER
AND THAT WE WILL HONOR THEM AGAIN AND THAT THEY WILL BE THE
NEXT GENERATION OF LEADERS IN SAN FRANCISCO.
BUT I'M GOING TO HAVE JOSE TO REALLY TELL HIS STORY AND WHAT
AN AMAZING MAN BUT I KNOW HE CAN'T DO IT ALONE IF IT WEREN'T
FOR HIS WIFE MARIA BUT HIS KIDS ARE HERE.
OTIS ALSO JOSE WHO IS A STUDENT IS NOW A FRESHMAN UNIVERSITY OF
SANTA CLARA AND A DAUGHTER. GISELLE IS A PEDIATRIC
ONCOLOGIST ON TWO COLLEGES AND IT'S JUST AMAZING.
AND THEN ALSO DAVID WHO IS A HIGH SCHOOL STUDENTS SENIOR AT
SACRED HEART HIGH SCHOOL JUST AMAZING FAMILY.
WE'RE SO GRATEFUL TO HAVE THEM IN THE RICHMOND IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> WE VISIT THEM OFTEN BUT HOW
EASY AS A DAD AND AS A NEIGHBOR AND A SMALL BUSINESS OWNER
REALLY BEEN A PILLAR OF OUR COMMUNITY AND REALLY CONTRIBUTE
A LOT ON THAT BLOCK AND IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD.
BUT HE TRULY BRINGS THE CULTURE AND THE HERITAGE NOT JUST TO
OUR COMMUNITY BUT ALSO THROUGH HIS FAMILY.
>> SO HOW SAY THE FLOOR IS YOURS?
WHEN I STARTED THIS I TOLD OTHER SUPERVISORS GOOD EVENING
OUR SUPERVISORS HE THOUGHT CELEBRATE THE LATINO HERITAGE
MONTH WILL SAY SOMETHING ABOUT ME AND MY BUSINESS AND SPANISH
AND MY SON WILL TRANSLATE AN ENGLISH
SO I'M HOSAM IS SO I'LL BE REITERATING WHAT HE SAID
IN ENGLISH IT'S LIKE I BEGAN MY CAREER IN THE POST MARKET
BUSINESS AT THE AGE OF 19 RIGHT WHEN I ARRIVED IN AMERICA I
WORKED IN SEVERAL DIFFERENT GROCERY STORES WHERE I HAD THE
OPPORTUNITY TO LEARN ESSENTIAL SKILLS WHICH HELPED ME TO
SUCCESSFULLY RUN BALBO PRODUCE TODAY PRIOR PRIOR TO BALBO
PRODUCE I ESTABLISHED A SMALLER GROCERY STORE ON GENEVA STREET
IN SAN FRANCISCO. SIMULTANEOUSLY I WAS DELIVERING
PRODUCE TO VARIOUS MARKETS AND RESTAURANTS INCLUDING ONE
OF THOSE BEING VOLVO PRODUCE. THE OWNER OF THE BELOW PRODUCE
MARKET AT THE TIME WAS CONSIDERING SON THE STORE AND I
SAW AN OPPORTUNITY FOR MYSELF AND MY FAMILY.
I WAS ABLE TO ACQUIRE THE STORE BUT NOT WITHOUT ITS FAULTS.
THE LOCATION AND COMMUNITY WERE THE PRIMARY REASONS FOR
CONSIDERING THE ESTABLISHMENT THERE BEING MY CHILDREN'S
SCHOOL ST THOMAS THE APOSTLE. HOWEVER, THE CONDITION OF THE
STORE WAS NOT IDEAL. IT TOOK SEVERAL YEARS TO
RENOVATE THE STORE BUT WE WERE ABLE TO GET IT TO ITS CURRENT
STATE. NOT EASY BUT WORTH IT.
BOB OPUS ALLOWED ME TO BE CLOSE TO MY CHILDREN'S SCHOOL ST
THOMAS APOSTLE CREATE LIFELONG RELATIONSHIPS WITH SURROUNDING
BUSINESSES OWNERS AND FAMILIES. BOB OUR PRODUCE WAS NOT THE
ONLY SOURCE OF INCOME BUT OUR LIVELIHOOD LIVELIHOOD WE HAVE
TAKEN PRIDE IN HAVING THE PRIVILEGE OF WITNESSING THE
GROWTH AND TRANSFORMATION OF OUR NEIGHBORHOOD AS WELL AS THE
DEVELOPMENT, THE CONTINUED DEVELOPMENT OF OUR BUSINESS
WITHIN IT. MY FAMILY AND I JUST WANT TO
TAKE A MOMENT TO THANK THE SUPPORT OF SAN FRANCISCO
COMMUNITY, ESPECIALLY THE OUTER RICHMOND DISTRICT AND CONNIE
CHAN FOR THE RECOGNITION AND APPRECIATION OUR FAMILY
BUSINESS FOR ALL OF OUR PRODUCE.
>> BEFORE I CLOSE I ACTUALLY WROTE A NOTE FOR MY PARENTS.
I WANT TO HEAR WHAT I'M SAYING. MY MOM AND DAD FOR EVERYTHING
THAT YOU HAVE DONE FOR OUR FAMILY GATHERING MOMENTS BUT
HELLO SIR. >> I'M ON MY
. >> EVERYTHING YOU HAVE DONE FOR
OUR FAMILY AND FORGIVE MY BROTHER AND MY SISTER AND ME
THE BEST LIFE WE COULD HAVE ASKED FOR.
YOU HAVE PROVIDED US WITH EVERYTHING WE NEEDED TO TO
SUCCEED IN THIS WORLD AND HAVE TAUGHT US THE TRUE MEANING OF
SACRIFICE PUTTING THE NEEDS OF THOSE YOU LOVE ABOVE YOUR OWN
LEAVING ONE LIFE BEHIND AND BUILDING A NEW ONE FROM THE
GROUND UP WAS THE GREATEST GIFT YOU COULD HAVE GIVEN US FOR
THAT AND SO MUCH MORE. WE LOVE YOU AND WE'RE FOREVER
GRATEFUL. >> THANK YOU MOM AND DAD YOU
OKAY? >> WELL YOUR
OKAY OKAY. >> DISTRICT TWO SUPERVISOR
CHERYL THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDEL MIN IS BALAAM HERE ALL
RIGHT, COME ON UP. >> WELL, COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
HONORED TO COMMEND JAVIER REVIEW ARAGON, OWNER OF
LEONARDO'S DELI AND TAQUERIA AS PART OF OUR CELEBRATION OF
LATINO HERITAGE MONTH HERE IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO LOCATED IN OPERA PLAZA AND CATHEDRAL HILL HONORS
IS MORE THAN JUST A RESTAURANT. IT'S REALLY A TRIBUTE TO
JAVIER'S LATE MOTHER LENORE, WHO FIRST INSPIRED HIS LOVE FOR
FOOD AND HIS PASSION FOR HOSPITALITY.
>> JAVIER WAS BORN IN MEXICO CITY IN 1974 AND RAISED BY
HARDWORKING PARENTS WHO INSTILLED IN HIM THE VALUES OF
DISCIPLINE FAMILY AND COMMUNITY.
AND IN THE MID 1990S HE CAME TO THE UNITED STATES IN PURSUIT OF
THE AMERICAN DREAM. >> AND IN SAN FRANCISCO HE
AND HIS FAMILY BUILT A LIFE ROOTED IN PERSEVERANCE
AND SERVICE. OPENING THE DOORS WAS JAVIER'S
WAY OF HONORING HIS MOTHER'S MEMORY WHILE ALSO CREATING A
PLACE THAT CELEBRATES MEXICAN CULINARY TRADITIONS
AND WELCOMES NEIGHBORS FROM ACROSS THE CITY.
THROUGH EVERY MEAL THE NORA'S SHARES THE VISUAL ORGANS,
FAMILY VALUES OF COMMUNITY PRIDE AND RESILIENCE WHILE
ADDING THE VIBRANT FLAVORS OF LATINO CULTURE TO DISTRICT TWO.
>> NOW MY OFFICE HOLDS THE FIRM BELIEF THAT THEIR BREAKFAST
BURRITO WITH SALSA WITH VERDE SALSA IS THE BEST IN THE WHOLE
DISTRICT AND I KNOW THAT MIGHT GET ME IN TROUBLE BUT I'M
WILLING TO GO ON THE RECORD SAYING THAT LOUD AND PROUD.
BUT TODAY ALSO IT'S IMPORTANT TO RECOGNIZE THAT RUNNING A
SMALL BUSINESS TAKES LONG HOURS AND CONSISTENT COMMITMENT.
>> YOU MAY NOTICE THAT THE PERSON STANDING BEFORE US
PROBABLY WAS NOT BORN IN 1974 AVIATOR HIMSELF COULD NOT BE
HERE BECAUSE HE IS AT LINARES KEEPING THE RESTAURANT GOING.
SO ACCEPTING THE COMMENDATION ON HIS BEHALF IS HIS CHILD
BALAAM JAVIER VIGIL IN HONORING JAVIER IN THE NEWS TODAY WE
CELEBRATE BELLA. I'M NOT ONLY YOUR FATHER'S
ENTREPRENEURIAL SPIRIT BUT ALSO YOUR FAMILY'S LEGACY.
ONE THAT YOU CONTINUE ON YOURSELF AND THE RICH CULTURAL
TRADITIONS OF SAN FRANCISCO'S LATINO COMMUNITY.
>> WELL, CONGRATULATIONS TO YOU AND TO YOUR ENTIRE FAMILY AND I
INVITE YOU UP TO ACCEPT THIS COMMENDATION ON BEHALF OF YOUR
FATHER AND SAY A FEW WORDS. >> THANK YOU.
BUT FIRST SUPERVISOR WELL, I JUST WANT TO SAY HOW WE ARE
CONGRATULATIONS TO YOU AND YOUR FAMILY.
AND I JUST WANT PEOPLE TO KNOW HOW INCREDIBLE OF A LEADER YOU
ARE GOING FROM SOMEBODY WHO WAS IN LEADERSHIP AT A YOUNG AGE.
>> WE FOUGHT SO MANY BATTLES TOGETHER.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. AND I JUST AM PROUD TO SEE YOU
AND YOUR FAMILY GET THIS AWARD TODAY.
>> THANK YOU. >> AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR, THANK
YOU. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR FOR
HONORING THIS WONDERFUL FAMILY. >> GREAT CHOICE BUT I WANTED TO
SAY A FEW WORDS SPECIFICALLY TO BALAAM BECAUSE YOU ARE SOMEONE
THAT I'VE KNOWN FOR MANY YEARS AND YOU KNOW I WILL TAKE CREDIT
FOR MENTORING YOU A LITTLE BIT BECAUSE I DO THINK THAT YOU
HAVE DEVOTED SO MUCH TIME AND ENERGY AND ALSO FED THE
COMMUNITY THROUGH YOUR FAMILY'S BUSINESS FOR SO MANY YEARS
AND FED US VERY WELL BECAUSE I AGREE WITH SUPERVISOR CHERYL IT
IS ONE OF THE BEST BURRITOS IN TOWN.
BUT YOU IN PARTICULAR HAVE SHOWN LEADERSHIP ABOVE
AND BEYOND SOMEONE OF YOUR YOUNG AGE AND TAKEN ON A
RESPONSIBILITY FOR YOUR GENERATION AND JUST DONE
INCREDIBLE THINGS AND I LOOK FORWARD TO WHAT YOU WILL
ACCOMPLISH. I'M SO PROUD OF YOU.
I'M SO PROUD OF YOUR FAMILY AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHERYL
FOR THIS HONOR. >> THANK YOU.
AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER YES. THANK YOU OF CHERYL FOR THIS
GREAT SELECTION AND CONGRATULATIONS TO YOU
AND YOUR FAMILY. BALAM I'VE ENJOYED OUR
CONVERSATION AND YOUR FAMILY SHOULD BE VERY PROUD OF YOU FOR
ALL THE WORK THAT YOU'VE DONE AND YOUTH LEADERSHIP IN THE
CITY AND I SHOULD ALSO BE PROUD OF YOU FOR GOING BACK TO
SCHOOL. >> I'VE ENJOYED OUR
CONVERSATIONS ABOUT THAT BUT BUT CONGRATULATIONS.
>> THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU.
OKAY. BLOOM I TRY NOT TO CRY.
>> I'M SORRY. WELL, THANK YOU, EVERYONE.
THANK YOU, SIR. ANSWER CHERYL THANK YOU.
BOARD PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT AND JUST EVERYONE FOR YOUR KIND
WORDS. I WAS SO NERVOUS COMING HERE.
AS YOU ALL KNOW, I'VE BEEN VERY HANDS OFF TRYING TO FOCUS ON
FAMILY AND SUCH BUT TO START ON BEHALF OF MY FAMILY I JUST WANT
TO THANK YOU ALL FOR THIS TRULY HONORABLE AWARD RECOGNIZING NOT
ONLY MY FATHER'S RESTAURANT BUT THE VALUES HE CARRIES INTO
EVERY MEAL HE SERVES AND EVERY LIFE HE TOUCHES INCLUDING HIS
CHILDREN. MY DAD CAME TO THIS COUNTRY
WITH A SIMPLE BUT POWERFUL DREAM TO BUILD A FAMILY AND TO
EMBODY WHAT A MODEL SAN FRANCISCAN CAN BE SOMEONE WHO
GIVES BACK LIFTS UP THOSE IN NEED AND NEVER LETS A
NEIGHBOR GO HUNGRY. >> ALTHOUGH MY ROLE IN THE
RESTAURANT WAS SMALL, OUR FARM FAMILY WORKED SIDE BY SIDE TO
MAKE LEONA'S DELI IN KOREA A SPACE THAT NOURISHES MORE THAN
APPETITES. DURING THE PANDEMIC WE PROVIDED
QUALITY MEALS FOR SHELTER IN PLACE.
HOTELS SERVED FIRST RESPONDERS AND PUBLIC SERVANTS AND DID OUR
BEST TO SHARE FOOD WITH COMMUNITY MEMBERS EXPERIENCING
HOMELESSNESS OR HARD TIMES. >> BIG SHOUT OUT TO MY MOM FOR
THAT TO TO AS THE RESTAURANT IS FOR MORE IS FAR MORE THAN A
BUSINESS IT REPRESENTS THE SPIRIT OF LATINO VALUES HARD
WORK SERVICE, COLLECTIVE EFFORT AND THE BELIEF THAT FOOD CAN
BRING PEOPLE TOGETHER AND MAKE NEIGHBORHOODS STRONGER.
FOR ME PERSONALLY, LEONORA IS A LIVING MANIFESTATION OF MY
FATHER'S VALUES THE SAME VALUES I STRIVE TO CARRY FORWARD IN MY
OWN SERVICE TO THE HOMELESS COMMUNITY AND HERE AT CITY
HALL. THIS AWARD AFFIRMS THAT THESE
EFFORTS RESONATE NOT ONLY WITHIN THE LATINO COMMUNITY BUT
ACROSS THE DIVERSE FABRIC OF SAN FRANCISCO SHOWING WHAT WE
CAN ACCOMPLISH WHEN WE WORK TOGETHER.
MY FATHER'S STORY AND HIS AMERICAN DREAM REMIND ME THAT
AT OUR CORE WE ARE ALL PEOPLE STRIVING FOR A BETTER SAN
FRANCISCO. EVEN WHEN WE DISAGREE WE CAN
COME TOGETHER AS NEIGHBORS. RESTAURANT OWNERS, PUBLIC
SERVANTS, ADVOCATES AND COMMUNITY MEMBERS UNITED BY
OUR SHARED DESIRE TO SEE THE CITY THRIVE.
I LOOK FORWARD TO CONTINUING TO SUPPORT YOU ALL IN FINDING
SOLUTIONS FOR THE CHALLENGES AHEAD AND TO HELPING MY FATHER
KEEP SERVING FOOD THAT IS BOTH MEANINGFUL AND DELICIOUS.
THANK YOU FOR HONORING OUR FAMILY'S JOURNEY AND FOR
ALLOWING US TO CONTINUE SERVING SAN FRANCISCO IN WAYS THAT
CELEBRATE ITS SPIRIT OF RESILIENCY, DIVERSITY
AND UNITY. >> THANK YOU.
>> DISTRICT THREE SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU PRESIDENT
BENJAMIN TOO. TODAY I AM HONORED TO CELEBRATE
DISTRICT THREE SMALL BUSINESS OWNER HILDA MENDEZ.
HILDA WOULD YOU COME ON UP AND JOIN US PLEASE?
>> HILDA IMMIGRATED FROM MEXICO CITY IN 2001 TO SAN FRANCISCO
AND OPENED CAFE ISABELA IN HILL IN 2006.
NAMING IT AFTER HER DAUGHTER ISABELLA WHO IS OF COURSE ALSO
HERE WITH US TODAY. >> NEARLY 20 YEARS LATER WITH
THE SUPPORT ALSO OF HER SISTER AND MOTHER, HILDA HAS BUILT A
BELOVED NEIGHBORHOOD CAFE KNOWN FOR MORNING GATHERINGS,
AUTHENTIC MEXICAN CUISINE WITH AN AMERICAN TOUCH.
AND HILDA HAS ALWAYS LOVED SAN FRANCISCO.
HER STORY REFLECTS THAT LOVE AS SHE'S MADE A LIFE, BUSINESS
AND FAMILY HERE. WE ARE TRULY FORTUNATE TO HAVE
HILDA IN OUR COMMUNITY. I THINK SHE'S A GEM.
I THINK SHE'S A FIXTURE. COLLEAGUES, I WOULD ENCOURAGE
YOU IF YOU ARE IN HILL TO GO BUY CAFE ISABELLA IT'S A
DELIGHTFUL SPOT ON TAYLOR STREET AND YOU'LL SEE THE
NEIGHBORS OUT THERE ON THE STREETS WITH THEIR BEAUTIFUL.
IT'S THE TINIEST LITTLE CAFE BUT IT'S A BEAUTIFUL SETTING.
YOU TAKE SUCH GOOD CARE OF THAT BLOCK.
YOU LOOK OUT FOR YOUR NEIGHBORS, YOU LOOK OUT FOR ALL
OF YOUR CUSTOMERS. YOU SERVE DELICIOUS FOOD.
ANOTHER GREAT BREAKFAST BURRITO THE CAFE MOCHA AZTECA
AND AGAIN, I THINK YOU JUST TAKE CARE OF EVERYONE
AND THAT'S WHY EVERYONE LOVES YOUR FOOD BUT EVERYONE FEELS
THE WARMTH OF OF YOUR FAMILY OF THE COMMUNITY YOU'VE BUILT
THERE. AND WE ARE SO LUCKY TO HAVE
YOU. I'M SO LUCKY TO HAVE YOU
IN DISTRICT THREE SO THANK YOU. AND THE FLOOR IS YOURS IF YOU'D
LIKE TO MAKE SOME REMARKS. >> THANK YOU.
I'M. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THIS IS MY FIRST TIME HERE AND I'M SO HAPPY TO BE PART OF
THE LATINO POWER. >> SO GOOD AFTERNOON,
SUPERVISORS. OUR BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
>> I WANT TO START OFF BY SAYING I'M GRATEFUL FOR THIS
INVITATION. IT MEANS SO MUCH TO ME BECAUSE
I SHOWED THEM MY EFFORT AND MY LOVE FOR THIS COMMUNITY.
>> SO IT HAS BEEN RECOGNIZED HERE.
MY COFFEE SHOP IS NOT JUST A BUSINESS FOR ME IT'S ABOUT
CREATING AND WELCOMING A SPACE TO MY NEIGHBORS.
>> I CAN FEEL HOME. >> I WILL CONTINUE TO GIVE MY
VERY BEST EFFORT BECAUSE I REALLY LOVE WHAT I DO
AND NOTHING MAKES ME HAPPY THAN SEEING MY CUSTOMERS SMILE.
MY GREATEST MOTIVATION MY CHILDREN'S AND MALIA
AND ISABELLA. >> I WANT TO TEACH THEM HOW
IMPORTANT IT IS TO LOVE IN HARMONY.
>> WITH YOUR COMMUNITY TO WORK HARD AND NEVER EVER GIVE UP.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR SUPPORT. I WILL KEEP MOVING FORWARD NO
MATTER WHAT CHALLENGES I HAVE. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
>> LATINOS DON'T LIKE THE BITTER FIGHTS AND WE DON'T WANT
DAIRY. NO, NO, NO.
AND NEXT UP DISTRICT FOR SUPERVISOR AND GARCIA.
THANK YOU. IS DANIEL HERE?
ALL RIGHT, COME ON UP. >> OH, ALL RIGHT, COLLEAGUES,
IT'S MY GREAT HONOR TO RECOGNIZE DANIEL RAMIREZ, THE
FOUNDER OF SMOKING IN BARBECUE ON IRVING STREET IN THE SUNSET
. >> DANIEL IS AN IMMIGRANT OF
MEXICAN DESCENT FROM HOUSTON. HE MARRIED LORENA CHIU WHO IS
CHINESE-AMERICAN AND BORN AND RAISED IN THE SUNSET.
>> THEIR MARRIAGE NOT ONLY BROUGHT DANIEL INTO OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD BUT ALSO CREATED SOMETHING TRULY UNIQUE A FUSION
OF TEXAS BARBECUE WHICH DANIEL GREW UP WITH AND CHINESE BAO A
TRADITIONAL LORRAINE HIS FAMILY AND THIS FUSION BECAME THE NOW
FAMOUS BISCUIT BAO A SENSATION AT FARMERS MARKETS, NIGHT
MARKETS AND AT THEIR RESTAURANT ON IRVING STREET.
NOW THE STORY OF BISCUIT BAO BEGINS WITH THE COMMUNITY AS
THAT PANDEMIC ENDED. DANIEL IN-ARENA BEGAN COOKING
IN THEIR GARAGE WITH NEIGHBORS AS THEIR FIRST CUSTOMERS.
THEN THEY OPENED A BOOTH AT THE SUNSET'S POPULAR SUNDAY
FARMER'S MARKET. THEY ALSO HAD A BOOTH AT THE
FIRST SUNSET NIGHT MARKET WHERE THEY SOLD OUT IN JUST TWO
HOURS. AND AS THE NIGHT MARKET SCENE
SPREAD ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO, THEY BROUGHT THEIR FOOD TO
EVERY EVENT THEY COULD. AND THIS YEAR DANIEL AND LORENA
OPENED A BRICK AND MORTAR STORE ON IRVING STREET.
>> IT IS THE DREAM OF THE SMALL BUSINESS OWNER FROM FARMER'S
MARKET TO BRICK AND MORTAR AND SMOKE IN THESE HAS QUICKLY
BECOME MORE THAN A PLACE TO EAT.
IT'S A NEIGHBORHOOD HUB WHERE FEW FOOD AND COMMUNITY COME
TOGETHER. NOW WHEN THE SUNSET NIGHT
MARKET THAT HELPED PUT SMOKIN D'S ON THE MAP WAS POSTPONED
THIS YEAR. DANIEL STEPPED FORWARD TO MAKE
SURE WE HAD A NIGHT MARKET ON IRVING STREET.
>> ALL RIGHT. YES.
HE ORGANIZED A COMMUNITY LED EVENT CALLED SUNSET AFTER DARK
AND IT KEPT THE JOY AND ECONOMIC VITALITY GOING.
WITH LESS THAN TWO MONTHS TO PREPARE, DANIEL RAISED FUNDS
FROM THE CIVIC JOY FUND. >> HE PARTNERED WITH DEAR
COMMUNITY P YES, DEAR COMMUNITY .
HE COORDINATED MERCHANT OUTREACH WITH MY OFFICE AND HE
MANAGED ALL OF THIS WHILE RUNNING HIS BUSINESS LAST
FRIDAY THOUSAND OF PEOPLE FILLED THREE BLOCKS OF IRVING
STREET. 50 VENDORS OFFERED LOCAL
FLAVORS BOBA DRINKS, DESSERTS, HANDCRAFTED GOODS, FAMILIES
PLAYED GAMES AND WON PRIZES. THE EVENT NOT ONLY LIFTED LOCAL
BUSINESSES BUT ALSO REMINDED US THAT THE SUNSET IS VIBRANT,
WELCOMING AND FULL OF OPPORTUNITY.
DANIEL YOUR JOURNEY INSPIRES OTHER ENTREPRENEURS TO TAKE
RISKS, CHASE THEIR DREAMS AND INVEST IN OUR COMMUNITY.
YOU'VE SHOWN THAT SMALL BUSINESSES ARE NOT JUST ENGINES
OF ECONOMIC GROWTH THEY ARE ANCHORS OF CULTURE, PRIDE
AND CONNECTION. YOUR LEADERSHIP HELPS CREATE
THE ATMOSPHERE IN WHICH INNOVATION, CREATIVITY
AND OPPORTUNITY CAN THRIVE. SO ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS, THANK YOU FOR YOUR VISION, YOUR HARD WORK AND YOUR
DEDICATION TO THE SUNSET DISTRICT.
>> BUT WAIT SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO FOR THIS
RECOGNITION AND COLLEAGUES IF YOU HAVEN'T TRIED THIS MAN'S
BARBECUE YOU MUST BECAUSE IT IS THE BOMB ALSO I JUST FOUND OUT
TODAY THAT THESE FOLKS ACTUALLY LIVE IN DISTRICT SEVEN SO I'M
TAKING GREAT PRIDE IN THIS BUT REALLY YOU ARE WHAT MAKES SAN
FRANCISCO SPECIAL AND WONDERFUL AND THE JOY THAT YOU BRING
IN FEEDING THAT COMMUNITY BUT ALSO CELEBRATING IS REALLY
QUITE SPECIAL. SO THANK YOU SUPERVISOR GARCIA
AGAIN FOR THE RECOGNITION OF THIS WONDERFUL ENDEAVOR
AND THIS WONDERFUL MAN AND I'M SO GLAD THAT WE'RE DOING THIS
FOR YOU. THANK YOU, JOHN AND GAUDIO,
THANK YOU. BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
IT'S AN HONOR TO BE HERE AS A SON OF IMMIGRANT PARENTS IT IS
I CAN'T BELIEVE MY LITTLE BARBECUE HAS BROUGHT ME TO
IN FRONT OF ALL YOU GUYS SO THIS IS AWESOME.
ALL RIGHT. SO THIS NICE MARKET WAS A WAY
OF BRINGING A MORE SUSTAINABLE AND BALANCED EVENT TO OUR
COMMUNITY THAT WAS ENVISIONED BY THE COMMUNITY FOR OUR
COMMUNITY. OUR RESIDENTS HAVE BEEN DIVIDED
OVER THE LAST YEAR AND THIS ALLOWED US TO HEAL AND COME
TOGETHER AS ONE. THIS LITTLE MARKET ALLOWED US
TO ALLOWED US TO CREATE A SPACE FOR OUR SCHOOLS AND PTA TO
ACTIVATE FUNDRAISING SEASON. WE HAD MORE THAN 60 HIGH SCHOOL
VOLUNTEERS. WE HAD A KIDS CARNIVAL, WE HAD
A GAMING TENT WHERE USERS COULD GIVE LIVE FEEDBACK TO THEIR
ENGINEERS OVER 50 FOOD TENTS AND SO MUCH MORE.
THIS IS A POWER OF COMMUNITY. WHEN WE COME TOGETHER AND WE
PUT KIDS FIRST WE ALL WIN. SO THANK YOU EVERYBODY FOR THE
HONORS GIFT
NOW DISTRICT FIVE SUPERVISOR MAHMUD IS A JUAN LUIS GOMEZ
PENA HERE. I WANT TO COME UP TO THE PODIUM
COLLEAGUES IN RECOGNITION OF LATINO HERITAGE MONTH
AND NATIONAL FIREFIGHTER APPRECIATION MONTH IT IS MY
DISTINCT HONOR TO RECOGNIZE AS JUAN LUIS GOMEZ PENA A PROUD
SON OF THE TENDERLOIN DEDICATED PUBLIC SERVANT AND AN INSPIRING
EXAMPLE OF RESILIENCE, REPRESENTATION AND RELENTLESS
DETERMINATION. >> AS A YOUNG BOY GROWING UP
IN THE TENDERLOIN, JUAN WITNESSED FIRSTHAND WHAT
SACRIFICE AND PERSEVERANCE TRULY MEANT.
HIS MOTHER CARED FOR NEIGHBORHOOD CHILDREN WHILE HIS
FATHER WORKED TWO JOBS TO PROVIDE FOR THEIR FAMILY OF
FIVE THESE EARLY EXPERIENCES INSTILLED IN HIM A DEEP RESPECT
FOR COMMUNITY AND A STRONG WORK ETHIC THAT WOULD GUIDE HIM
THROUGH THE MANY OBSTACLES AHEAD.
>> GROWING UP NEAR A FIRE STATION, JUAN TOOK INSPIRATION
FROM THE FIRE TRUCKS PASSING, TELLING HIS MOTHER HE'D GROW UP
ONE DAY TO BE A FIREFIGHTER AND HE ACTUALLY DID.
>> JUAN'S PATH TO BECOMING A SAN FRANCISCO FIREFIGHTER WAS
ANYTHING BUT EASY. HE STRUGGLED ACADEMICALLY
AND LIKE SO MANY YOUNG PEOPLE IN THE TENDERLOIN FACED
CHALLENGES THAT COULD HAVE EASILY DERAILED HIS FUTURE.
>> BUT ALSO JUST LIKE SO MANY IN THE TENDERLOIN, JUAN NEVER
GAVE UP. >> DURING THIS TIME HE REMAINED
CLOSE TO THE FIRE SERVICE VOLUNTEERING HIS TIME WORKING
BEHIND THE SCENES ON PHOTOGRAPHY FOR THE FIRE
DEPARTMENT AND CONTINUING TO GROW AND EXPERIENCE KNOWLEDGE
AND HUMILITY. >> HE REMAINED FOCUSED ON ONE
THING GIVING BACK TO THE COMMUNITY THAT RAISED HIM.
>> HE WAS DETERMINED TO PASS THE EMT COURSE AND AFTER SEVEN
LONG YEARS HE FINALLY GOT HIS DREAM JOB WITH THE SAN
FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT IN 2023.
TODAY JUAN STANDS NOT ONLY AS A MEMBER OF THE SAN FRANCISCO
FIRE DEPARTMENT BUT ALSO AS A SYMBOL OF HOPE FOR OTHER YOUNG
LATINOS GROWING UP IN THE TENDERLOIN AND BEYOND.
>> AS HIS FELLOW FIREFIGHTER ANTONIO AT STATION 21 PUT IT,
JUAN IS ONE OF THE HARDEST WORKING AND MOST GENUINE PEOPLE
YOU COULD HOPE TO MEET. >> HIS ROOTS IN THE CITY RUN
DEEP AND HE TRULY EMBODIES WHAT IT MEANS TO BE A PUBLIC SERVANT
. >> I CAN GENUINELY SAY THE CITY
IS BLESSED TO HAVE PEOPLE LIKE JUAN LOOKING OUT FOR IT.
>> AS WE CELEBRATE LATINO HERITAGE MONTH AND FIREFIGHTER
APPRECIATION MONTH, JUAN REMINDS US OF THE POWER OF
INTERGENERATIONAL DREAMS BREAKING CYCLES, THE VALUE OF
REPRESENTATION AND THE POWER OF GIVING BACK TO OUR COMMUNITY.
>> HE DID NOT CHOOSE THIS PATH FOR PRESTIGE OR PRAISE.
HE CHOSE IT, AS I UNDERSTAND FOR HIS FAMILY, FOR HIS
COMMUNITY AND TO SHOW HIS NEPHEW AND THE NEXT GENERATION
THAT NO MATTER YOUR PAST OR HOW MANY TRIES IT TAKES YOU CAN
ACHIEVE ANYTHING YOU SET YOUR SIGHTS ON.
>> JUAN THANK YOU FOR YOUR COURAGE, YOUR COMMITMENT TO
SERVICE AND KEEPING OUR CITIES SAFE AND YOUR UNWAVERING BELIEF
IN YOURSELF AND OUR COMMUNITY. YOU HAVE NOT ONLY MADE YOUR
FAMILY PROUD, YOU HAVE MADE THIS ENTIRE CITY PROUD AS WELL.
>> WE ARE CLOSE BY SAYING GRACIAS FOR FELICIDAD ES
BAMBARA. >> GOMEZ GARCIA YES.
>> YEAH. THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
FIRST I WANT TO SAY THANK YOU TO THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR
NOT ONLY WHAT YOU DO BUT EVERYTHING YOU DO AS WELL AS
FOR THIS RECOGNITION NOT JUST FROM MY FAMILY BUT FROM MYSELF
AS WELL. I'M A PROUD SON, PROUD SON OF
IMMIGRANT PARENTS. AS A NATIVE BORN AND RAISED
IN THE TENDERLOIN WHERE MY FAMILY STILL LIVES.
BEFORE ANYTHING ELSE I WANT TO SAY THAT NO MATTER WHERE YOU
COME FROM THAT IF A KID FROM THE TENDERLOIN CAN ACHIEVE HIS
GOAL AND HIS DREAM OF BECOMING A FIREFIGHTER THAT ANYBODY CAN
DO ANYTHING THEY SET THEIR MINDS TO.
>> I WANT TO THANK MY FRIENDS MENTORS THAT I'VE HAD SO MANY
MY LADY AND MOST IMPORTANTLY THE PEOPLE THAT HAVE BEEN THERE
SINCE DAY ONE WITH FAMILIA. THEY ARE THE REASON I AM THE
PERSON I AM TODAY THROUGH SEEING THEIR STRENGTH
RESILIENCE, BRAVERY AND MOST IMPORTANTLY THEIR LOVE NOT JUST
FOR MY BROTHER, SISTER AND MYSELF BUT THE LOVE
AND KINDNESS THEY SHOW TO EVERYONE THEY COME ACROSS.
THIS IS WHAT BEING A PROUD MEXICAN IS ALL ABOUT BEING
THERE FOR ONE ANOTHER AND NEVER GIVING UP.
NO MATTER HOW HARD HOW HARD TIMES GET.
>> MA BUT I STILL SUPPORT OTHER
ALL RIGHT, COLLEAGUES, BEFORE I CALL ON SUPERVISOR DORSEY, I DO
WANT TO REITERATE A NORM THAT WE HAVE WHICH IS THAT WE TRY TO
HAVE ONE HONOREE FOR OUR 230 SPECIAL COMMENDATIONS.
NOW SOMETIMES LIFE INTERVENES AND FOR SOME SET OF REASONS WE
HAVE TO DO MORE THAN ONE AND I HAVE GIVEN MYSELF THAT
ACCOMMODATION I RECOGNIZED IN THE PAST AND IF ANY OF YOU
ASK FOR THAT ACCOMMODATION UNLESS THE BOARD DECIDES THAT
THEY DON'T WANT ME TO, I AM GOING TO ALLOW IT.
BUT I KNOW SOME PEOPLE DID PULL BACK LOOKING AT YOU SUPERVISOR
CHAN A DOUBLING UP AND SO SUPERVISOR DORSEY FROM DISTRICT
SIX THIS IS YEAR TWO FOR OKAY THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN.
>> COLLEAGUES ACTUALLY IS FORMER SUPERVISOR MAHER YEAH
OKAY OKAY. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY IT'S MY
PRIVILEGE TO RECOGNIZE SOMEONE I HAD INTENDED TO HONOR TWO
WEEKS AGO UNTIL A SUPERIOR COURT SUMMONS FOR JURY DUTY
PREVENTED ME FROM BEING HERE TO DO THAT.
SO AS WE ALSO CLOSE RECOVERY MONTH TWO, I WANTED TO HONOR
THE FORMER SUPERVISOR BILL MAHER, A RECOVERY COMMUNITY
TRAILBLAZER, AN ACCOMPLISHED PUBLIC SERVANT AND A PERSONAL
INSPIRATION TO ME AND COUNTLESS OTHERS.
BILL MAHER STORY IS A TESTAMENT TO THE TRANSFORMATIVE POWER OF
RECOVERY AND TO WHAT'S POSSIBLE WHEN WE MEET ADDICTION WITH
HUMANITY AND ACCOUNTABILITY. A SAN FRANCISCO'S FIRST
SUPERVISOR TO OPENLY ACKNOWLEDGE HIS JOURNEY
IN RECOVERY FROM DRUG ADDICTION.
BILL OPENED A DOOR THAT MADE IT POSSIBLE FOR PEOPLE LIKE ME.
SAN FRANCISCO'S SECOND SUCH SUPERVISOR TO FOLLOW IN HIS
FOOTSTEPS. IN MY OWN POLITICAL WORK AS
IN MY OWN RECOVERY JOURNEY I'VE OFTEN LOOKED TO BILL'S EXAMPLE
HIS PERSEVERANCE, HIS PRAGMATISM, HIS POLITICAL
SOPHISTICATION AND HIS BELIEF THAT THE ABIDING LESSONS OF
RECOVERY ARE NOT JUST PERSONAL BUT CIVIC VALUES WORTH
CELEBRATING. BILL'S PATH WAS ANYTHING BUT
EASY. BY AGE 14 HE WAS STRUGGLING
WITH A HEROIN ADDICTION AND HAD BEEN ARRESTED MANY TIMES.
EVENTUALLY A BOSTON JUDGE GAVE HIM AN OPPORTUNITY A SUSPENDED
PRISON SENTENCE IF SENTENCE IF HE ENTERED DRUG TREATMENT
IN SAN FRANCISCO. THAT DECISION TOGETHER WITH HIS
BROTHER JOHN SUPPORT THROUGH THE DELANCEY STREET FOUNDATION
HE CO-FOUNDED SET HIM ON A NEW COURSE.
>> AT DELANCEY STREET, BILL WORKED TO BUILD PROGRAMS THAT
GAVE PEOPLE IN RECOVERY NOT JUST A SAFE PLACE TO LIVE BUT
JOB SKILLS, EDUCATION AND A PATH BACK TO DIGNITY.
BILL'S COMMITMENT TO RECOVERY DIDN'T END WITH HIS OWN
SOBRIETY. HE CARRIED IT INTO PUBLIC
SERVICE AS A MEMBER AND LATER PRESIDENT OF SAN FRANCISCO'S
BOARD OF EDUCATION. HE WORKED TO EXPAND THE
OPPORTUNITIES AFFORDED BY PUBLIC SCHOOLS RECOGNIZING THE
HARMS CAUSED WHEN THOSE OPPORTUNITIES ARE LACKING.
ELECTED TO THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR THREE TERMS
BILL WAS AN ACCOMPLISHED AND SOLUTIONS ORIENTED
PRAGMATIST. AMONG HIS MANY CONTRIBUTIONS
ARE THE MAJOR ORDINANCE WHICH STILL PROTECTS SAN FRANCISCANS
BY REQUIRING THE CLEAN UP OF TOXIC INDUSTRIAL SITES BEFORE
DEVELOPMENT. A VOTER APPROVED MEASURE TO
PRESERVE SUNLIGHT IN OUR CITY PARKS.
AND HIS GROUNDBREAKING SUPPORT AS AN EARLY STRAIGHT ALLY TO
THE LGBTQ PLUS COMMUNITY AS A CO-FOUNDING MEMBER OF THE
LGBTQ+ DEMOCRATIC CLUB AND CREATING A GAY SPEAKER'S
BUREAU THAT YEARS AGO BROUGHT LGBT Q PLUS VOICES TO CITY
CLASSROOMS TO REDUCE STIGMA AND HATE CRIMES.
BILL MAHER'S STORY UNDERSCORES THE MESSAGE THAT RECOVERY IS
POSSIBLE AND THAT THE POWER THAT MESSAGE HOLDS NOT JUST FOR
INDIVIDUALS BUT FOR ENTIRE COMMUNITIES.
HIS STORY REMINDS US THAT INVESTING IN TREATMENT AND IN
SECOND CHANCES CAN CHANGE LIVES AND CAN CHANGE A CITY.
AS WE GRAPPLE WITH TODAY'S ADDICTION AND OVERDOSE CRISES,
WE SHOULD REMEMBER THAT THE MANY ENDURING SOLUTIONS LIKE
THOSE OFFERED BY DELANCEY STREET AND OTHERS COME FROM
THOSE WHO'VE BEEN THERE. BILL'S JOURNEY WHICH LIKE MY
OWN INCLUDES BEING A YOUTHFUL TROUBLEMAKER IN BOSTON TO AN
ELECTED LEADER IN SAN FRANCISCO EMBODIES THE SPIRIT OF RECOVERY
MONTH. ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS AND THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO, I WANT TO THANK
BILL MAHER FOR HIS SERVICE, COURAGE AND ONGOING EXAMPLE.
BILL, THANK YOU FOR YOUR SERVICE TO OUR CITY AND TO THE
RECOVERY MOVEMENT FOR SERIOUS. WELCOME BACK TO THE CHAMBER
SUPERVISOR. >> THEN WHILE I HAVE THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND THANKS TO MY WIFE WHO SHARES THE
EXPERIENCE OF OTHERS HERE OF HAVING BEEN GIVEN FROM HER HOME
ONE WHY THE WAR IN UKRAINE SEE BROTHER DORSEY AND I ARE
STRUGGLING TOGETHER TO REFORM SAN FRANCISCO'S ADDICTION
POLICIES. WE'VE BECOME A CITY OF ENABLERS
AND CO-DEPENDENCE. OUR EXPECTATIONS FOR ADDICTED
PEOPLE ARE ABYSMALLY LOW. WE NEED TO DEMAND MORE.
WE NEED TO LOVE THOSE PEOPLE. AND WHEN YOU LOVE PEOPLE YOU
DEMAND FROM THEM AND YOU HELP THEM MEET THOSE DEMANDS.
>> I GREW UP IN THE SOUTH BRONX AND HARLEM DROPPED OUT OF
SCHOOL, SPENT A DOZEN YEARS SHOOTING DOPE, GOT 20 YEARS
IN WALPOLE PENITENTIARY LAST TIME AND FORTUNATELY THE JUDGE
DECIDED TO TAKE A CHANCE ON ME AND SEND ME TO SAN FRANCISCO.
I'VE ALWAYS APPRECIATED THAT I STOPPED SHOOTING SMACK.
>> I CHANGED MY LIFE BECAUSE I WAS REQUIRED TO.
>> AND INSTEAD I HEADED THE AMERICAN DELEGATION TO CHINA
IN 84 FOR THE WHITE HOUSE SCHOOL BOARD AND SAT ON THIS
BOARD FOR 12 YEARS. OUR POLICY IS DON'T SEEM TO
THINK WE CAN RISE ABOVE LIVING IN A GUTTER JUST BECAUSE WE DID
ONCE. >> WE CAN RISE ABOVE IT.
TENS OF THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE OVER THE LAST 50 YEARS FROM
DELANCEY STREET AND MILLIONS OF PEOPLE AROUND THIS COUNTRY HAVE
MADE A CHOICE TO GET OUT OF THE GUTTER AND BUILD NEW LIVES
AND THEY BUILD THEM WITH SUPPORT FROM US.
BUT WE CAN'T LEAD. THEY HAVE TO LEAD AND WHEN THEY
DO WE NEED TO HELP THEM. OUR POLICIES SHOULD PRESS
PEOPLE TO DO BETTER, NOT TO ENTRAP THEM.
YOU GIVE CHRIST IF I'D GOTTEN FREE FOOD FREE PLACE TO LIVE
AND EVERYTHING ELSE I MIGHT STILL BE SHOOTING UP ON A
STREET CORNER SOMEWHERE. >> WE NEED TO DO BETTER.
I HOPE THAT YOU WILL THINK ABOUT THOSE CHANGES AND DEMAND
MORE OF YOURSELVES AND DEMAND MORE OF US.
OUR PRESENT POLICY IGNORES THE TENDERLOIN.
I WAS A VOLUNTEER THERE SEVERAL TIMES AT DIFFERENT
ORGANIZATIONS AND WHY SHOULD SCHOOLCHILDREN HAVE TO WALK
OVER BODIES EVERY MORNING GOING TO SCHOOL AND WONDER IF THEY'RE
DEAD, DRUGGED OR JUST DRUNK? >> GREAT CHOICES.
IT MAKES IT MORE DIFFICULT FOR THE PEOPLE YOU'RE HONORING HERE
WHO ARE TRYING TO RUN SMALL BUSINESSES.
WE'RE TRYING TO BUILD LIVES. WE'RE TRYING TO BUILD COMMUNITY
. I HOPE YOU'LL CONSIDER CHANGING
YOUR POLICIES TO EXPECT MORE TO DEMAND MORE AND TO HELP US WHEN
WE DO THAT NOT TO HAVE SOMEONE TRYING TO BE SOBER LIVING
IN PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING WHERE EVERYONE ELSE IS DRINKING
OR SHOOTING DOPE. >> THAT'S NOT THE WAY WE HELP
PEOPLE OUT. ENOUGH LECTURING.
IT'S NICE TO BE BACK. >> I HAVEN'T BEEN HERE IN A
WHILE. I ACTUALLY AVOID THE PLACE
GENERALLY BUT THANKS AND SUPERVISE YOUR DORSEY.
>> AND SERIOUSLY WE CAN DO BETTER AND LET'S TRY.
AND AGAIN THANKS TO MY WIFE WHO TOUCHED WE WERE LISTENING TO
IMMIGRANTS AND REFUGEES TODAY SHE'S REFUGEES FROM A WAR TO
AND WE UNDERSTAND HOW HARD IT IS AND IT'S HARD FOR OUR KIDS
IT'S HARD FOR PEOPLE TO BUILD NEW LIVES BUT IT'S WHAT WE NEED
TO DEMAND. AND WHEN THEY RISE TO THE
OCCASION WE NEED TO HELP THEM. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
IT'S ABOUT PROTOCOL NOW BUT AND NEXT I'M DOUBLE DIPPING TO
JOIN MY BOARD COLLEAGUES AND ALSO CELEBRATING LATINO
HERITAGE MONTH HERE AT THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND IT IS
MY PRIVILEGE AND HONOR TO RECOGNIZE A TRUE DISTRICT SIX
HERO AND COMMUNITY LEADER OMAR DEL RIO FOR OMAR, OMAR SERVES
AS THE GENERAL MANAGER OF MISSION HIRING HALL A
CORNERSTONE OF WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT IN OUR CITY SINCE
1971. FROM THEIR OFFICES AT FOLSOM
AND RUSSELL STREETS IN THE HEART OF SOUTH OF MARKET
MISSION HIRING HALL HAS BEEN CONNECTING SAN FRANCISCANS
ESPECIALLY LOW INCOME RESIDENTS AND PEOPLE EXPERIENCING
HOMELESSNESS WITH THE TRAINING, SUPPORT AND OPPORTUNITIES THEY
NEED TO BUILD STABLE AND MEANINGFUL CAREERS.
OMAR'S LEADERSHIP AND DEDICATION EMBODY THAT
MISSION EVERY DAY. HE IS RELENTLESS IN MATCHING
JOBSEEKERS TO THE RIGHT OPPORTUNITY AND IF SOMEONE
ISN'T QUITE READY YET HE MAKES SURE THAT THEY FIND THE
TRAINING PROGRAM THAT WILL HELP THEM TO GET THERE.
OMAR ALSO BRINGS HIS PASSION FOR WORKFORCE EQUITY TO THE
LATINO TASK FORCE WHERE HE CO-CHAIRS THE EMPLOYMENT
COMMITTEE. DURING THE PANDEMIC HE HELPED
TO ORGANIZE SOME OF THE LARGEST JOB FAIRS IN SAN FRANCISCO
LINKING EMPLOYERS WITH READY WORKERS WHEN IT MATTERED MOST.
AND AS I OFTEN SAY WHENEVER I'M AT A WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT
EVENT HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO AND I THINK IT'S ESPECIALLY
TRUE REPRESENTING DISTRICT SIX WHICH HAS A LOT OF I
AND BIOTECH COMPANIES THIS WORK IS IMPORTANT NOT JUST FOR THE
PROSPECTIVE WORKERS YOU'RE SERVING.
IT'S ALSO IMPORTANT TO SAN FRANCISCO'S ECONOMIC VIBRANCY
AND ITS GLOBAL COMPETITIVENESS. AND WHENEVER I TALK TO LARGE
EMPLOYERS THEY WILL BE THE FIRST TO SAY THAT THE
COMPETITIVE ADVANTAGE OF SAN FRANCISCO IS ITS PEOPLE.
SO THANK YOU FOR THE WORK THAT YOU'RE DOING TO SUPPORT THAT.
OMAR ON BEHALF OF DISTRICT SIX AND THE ENTIRE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS, I THANK YOU FOR YOUR SERVICE AND ON THE
OCCASION OF LATINO HERITAGE MONTH WE ARE PROUD TO CELEBRATE
YOUR CONTRIBUTIONS TO ALL OUR COMMUNITIES.
CONGRATULATIONS ON THE RAFAEL. DO I HAVE THE MIKE?
OH CIGARET SMOKE NO WE HAVE TO SAY NICE THINGS ABOUT HIM.
OH MY GOSH IT'S LIKE A WHO'S WHO OF THE LATINO COMMUNITY
HERE TODAY. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR DAWSEY
EXCELLENT CHOICE. AND I JUST WANT TO SAY OH MY
THANK YOU FOR EVERYTHING THAT YOU DO DAY TO DAY FOR FOLKS
CONNECTING THEM TO OPPORTUNITY BUT ALSO FOR YOUR GREAT CARE
AND THOUGHTFULNESS FOR EVERY INDIVIDUAL AND TO MEET THEM
WHERE THEY'RE AT BECAUSE THAT'S YOUR SUPERPOWER.
THAT'S YOUR GIFT. I AM SO GRATEFUL THAT WE HAVE
YOU IN OUR CITY IN THAT WE HAVE AT YOUR LEADERSHIP I NOT JUST
AT MISSION HIRING HALL BUT YOU KNOW AT THE LATINO TASKFORCE
EVERYTHING THAT YOU HAVE DONE TO SUPPORT THE COMMUNITY, I'M
REALLY PROUD THAT YOU ARE GETTING THIS RECOGNITION
AND THANK YOU FOR EVERYTHING YOU DO.
AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU ROGER DORSEY FOR THIS HONOR
TO AN INCREDIBLE YOUNG LEADER AND I JUST WANTED TO SAY OMAR,
CONGRATULATIONS. THANK YOU FOR ALL YOU DO WITH
ALL THE STUFF IN MISSION HIRING HALL YOU ALSO HAVE A GREAT
ANNOUNCER VOICE AND ARE JUST VERY PERSONABLE AND I THINK
THAT IS REALLY A HUGE ASSET TO THE COMMUNITY.
>> SO THANK YOU FOR YOUR SERVICE AND NOW THE FLOOR IS
YOURS WHICH IS GOOD ACCESS BUT DON'T WE ARE GOING TO SEE THEM.
>> BUT I RECEIVED A CERTIFICATE ON THIS RECOGNITION PREMIUM
AND THEY LOOK AT ALL THE SCENE WHICH IS GOOD SEE SOME SPIDERS
ANTONIO DEL REAL VERONICA DEL REAL THEY SHOWED UP TO THIS
COUNTRY ABOUT 17 AND 19 YEARS OLD RESPECTIVELY.
>> MY OLDER BROTHER MEXICAN SAID SERGIO DEL REAL AND I'M
THE FIRST AMERICAN BORN IN THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.
>> MY YOUNGER SISTER DR. EVELYN DEL REAL THANK YOU ALL FIVE I
COULDN'T HAVE DONE IT WITHOUT YOU.
>> AND YOU KNOW WHEN I FIRST GOT HERE TO SAN FRANCISCO I WAS
ABOUT 18 YEARS OLD, HAD A BACKPACK.
>> I CAME FROM EAST SIDE SAN JOSE AND IF YOU'RE FROM
EASTSIDE SAN JOSE YOU KNOW YOUR STATE YOU'RE GOING TO STAY
IN EAST SIDE SAN JOSE. >> SO I GOT ON THE CALTRAIN
BACKPACK. I DIDN'T KNOW ANYBODY.
I WAS IN MUSIC. >> I WAS A LEAD SINGER OF A
BAND CHUCK NORRIS AND VIET CONG SHOUT OUT HEY HIP AND I GOT
STARTED HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO BY NOT KNOWING ANYONE BUT JUST
BY CHARISMA CONNECTING WITH INDIVIDUALS BUT GOT MY FIRST
JOB WITHIN A MONTH HERE AT MACY'S SAN FRANCISCO UNION
SQUARE STARTED SELLING FRAGRANCES AND COSMETICS WAS
THERE FOR ABOUT NINE YEARS AND I WORKED OVER AT MAC
COSMETICS IN EMERYVILLE. I WAS A HOT SHOT AND I'M LIKE
OH MAN, I WAS A KID. I WAS LIKE 20 YEARS OLD WORKING
IN CORPORATE MAC COSMETICS. THEN 2008 HAPPENED GET LAID OFF
WORK AT PEDRO'S COFFEE AND I STARTED MAKING CAPPUCCINOS FOR
EVERYBODY. NOT MY FAVORITE THING TO DO
EVENTUALLY BECAUSE OF THE PEOPLE THAT I MET AT MACY'S,
SAN FRANCISCO AND UNION SQUARE I GOT CONNECTED TO MISSION
HIRING HALL WHERE I'VE BEEN THERE FOR THE LAST NINE YEARS.
>> EARLIER THANK YOU FOR THINKING NOW I'LL KEEP IT SHORT
BUT YOU KNOW I STARTED THERE WORKING AT CITY BULL ACADEMY
GETTING FOLKS ALL THE SAN FRANCISCO UNIFIED DISTRICTS TO
GET A CAREER IN CONSTRUCT AND WHEN THEY WEREN'T GOING TO
GO TO COLLEGE THEY CALLED ME AND SAID WHAT CAN I DO TO GET
THIS KID? >> YOU BETTER HURRY UP.
GET THEM OVER HERE IF THEY'RE AT THE SAN BRUNO JAILS EVEN
WHEN WOODSIDE WAS STILL AVAILABLE I WAS THERE OFFERING
THESE SERVICES THEN FORWARD ON WE STARTED WITH THE CITY DRIVE
AND THEN OF COURSE YOU KNOW WHEN THE ALL THOSE FOLKS WHO
GOT LAID OFF BECAUSE OF FORD MOTOR COMPANY BUT THAT WEIRD
TECHIE 2016 TRANSIT APP AND THEN UNFORTUNATELY 300
INDIVIDUALS GOT LAID OFF WE WE WERE THERE FOR MISSION HIRING
AND WE SAID WE CAN GET THOSE INDIVIDUALS TO START WORKING
FOR MUNI SO WE WERE THERE FOR CITY DRIVE AND THANK YOU SO
MUCH. AND THEN OF COURSE THE PANDEMIC
HAPPENED AND WHEN THAT PANDEMIC HAPPENED WE DIDN'T WALK BUT WE
RAN. WE RAN AND WE SAID WE WANTED TO
BE A PART OF THIS AND WE DIDN'T CARE FOR OUR OWN WELL-BEING.
BUT WE WANT WE CARE FOR THE WELL-BEING OF THE COMMUNITY SAN
FRANCISCO AND BEYOND AND BECAUSE OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO LATINO TASK FORCE WE WERE RECOGNIZED NATIONALLY AS
THE MODEL OF WHAT TO DO IN A PANDEMIC SITUATION.
SO I THANK YOU ALL AT THE SAN FRANCISCO LATINO TASK FORCE.
>> OUR WORK ISN'T DONE. EARLIER TODAY OF COURSE, YOU
KNOW, 2025 BROUGHT A NEW ADMINISTRATION IN AND THIS YEAR
IT'S BEEN TOUGH. >> IT'S BEEN DIFFICULT.
I'VE BEEN CONNECTING INDIVIDUALS WITH EMPLOYMENT
OPPORTUNITIES. BUT I'M PROUD TO SAY THAT THIS
AFTERNOON I'M NOT GOING TO TELL YOU WHERE THIS INDIVIDUAL GOT
EMPLOYED BUT THIS PERSON DOES NOT HAVE LEGAL DOCUMENT RIGHT
TO WORK DOCUMENTS BUT WE GOT HIM WORK TODAY.
>> OKAY. HE'S GOING TO WORK TONIGHT
AND TODAY WE'RE ALREADY LATE. IT'S ABOUT THIS MEETING STARTED
AT 4:00. >> WE HAVE AN EMERGENCY MEETING
DOWN AT JIM'S RESTAURANT IN THE MISSION FOR A LATINO TASK FORCE
IMMIGRATION COMMITTEE EMERGENCY MEETING TO SEE WHAT WE CAN DO
TO ENSURE THAT WE ARE STILL SUPPORTING THE COMMUNITY.
SO WITH THAT, THANK YOU EVERYBODY.
I REALLY APPRECIATE THIS BUT I'M GOING TO CONTINUE TO WORK
AND MR. MATT DORSEY, THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR ALWAYS SUPPORTING
MISSION HIRING. >> WE LOOK FORWARD TO SEEING
YOU AT OUR NEXT FUND RAISER. YOU ALL RIGHT?
GABRIELLE AND JUDD, YOU HAVE WAITED A VERY LONG TIME.
>> DISTRICT EIGHT HONOR GABRIELLA JUDD COME ON UP WITH
YOUR FAMILY AND IT'S NICE TO SEE YOU.
>> NICE TO SEE YOU TOO. COLLEAGUES, TODAY I AM OFFERING
A SPECIAL COMMENDATION TO GABRIELLA JUDD.
>> GABRIELLA IS THE CO-FOUNDER OF PRIMEROS PASSOS, A SPANISH
IMMERSION DAYCARE IN PRESCHOOL THAT SHE AND HER HUSBAND FRANCO
STARTED IN GLEN PARK IN 2013. GABRIELLE IS A NATIVE SPANISH
SPEAKER WITH FAMILY ROOTS IN EL SALVADOR, A TRAINED SINGER WITH
A BACHELOR'S IN OUR HISTORY AND A BACKGROUND
IN ARCHITECTURE AND DESIGN, GABRIELLE HAS WORK IN EARLY
CHILDHOOD EDUCATION, WAS INSPIRED BY HER MOTHER WHO WAS
FOR MANY YEARS A BILINGUAL TEACHER'S AIDE AFTER SENDING
HER OWN DAUGHTER TO A CORPORATE PRESCHOOL, GABRIELA WAS
INSPIRED TO START A PRESCHOOL THAT WOULD KUPPER COUPLE HER
MOTHER'S TEACHINGS WITH HER OWN TRAINING IN DESIGN TO CREATE
MORE NURTURING AND INSPIRING LEARNING SPACES.
>> AFTER 12 VERY SUCCESSFUL YEARS IN GLEN PARK, PRIMEROS
PASSOS MOVED AND EXPANDED TO TWO NEW LOCATIONS SILVER PARK
IN 2019 AND NOVI VALLEY IN 2023.
>> UNLIKE MANY EARLY CHILDHOOD EDUCATION CENTERS, PRIMEROS
PASSOS HAS AN EXCEPTIONALLY LOW TURNOVER RATE AMONG STAFF.
FAMILIES TRUST AND VALUE THE PROGRAM AND CONSEQUENTLY
REFERRALS AND SIBLING ENROLLMENTS ARE A HALLMARK YEAR
AFTER YEAR. GABRIEL AND FRANCO'S CHILDREN
ARE THEMSELVES GRADUATES WHO REMAIN FULLY BILINGUAL.
GABRIELA HAS ALSO PURSUED EXTENSIVE ACADEMIC TRAINING
IN EARLY CHILDHOOD EDUCATION IN ADDITION TO HER STUDIES
IN ART HISTORY AND ARCHITECTURE.
SHE COMPLETED A MASTER'S IN EARLY CHILDHOOD EDUCATION AT
SAN FRANCISCO STATE UNIVERSITY WHERE HER THESIS FOCUSED ON
LEARNING ENVIRONMENTS FOR CHILDREN.
SHE HOLDS MULTIPLE CERTIFICATES AND ADMINISTRATION ADVOCACY,
INFANT TODDLER CARE AND EARLY CHILDHOOD PRACTICE AND SHE'S
PARTICIPATED IN PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT AT STANFORD
UNIVERSITY'S BEING SUMMER EDUCATOR SESSIONS.
THROUGH IT ALL, GABRIELLE HAS GABRIELA HAS REMAINED A JOYFUL
EDUCATOR BRINGING MUSIC INTO THE CLASSROOM, SINGING WITH THE
CHILDREN AND CARRYING FORWARD THE LEGACY OF HER MOTHER'S
WORK. SHE AND HER HUSBAND OFTEN SAY
IT IS THEIR PRIVILEGE TO PROVIDE CARE AND ENRICHMENT FOR
SAN FRANCISCO FAMILIES AND THE SUCCESS OF PRIMEROS PASSOS IS A
TESTAMENT TO THAT SPIRIT OF SERVICE.
>> GABRIELA, THANK YOU FOR YOUR SERVICE TO THE CHILDREN
AND FAMILIES OF DISTRICT EIGHT AND THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO. >> AND THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
THANK YOU. >> WELL, THANK YOU, MR. BOARD
PRESIDENT SUPERVISORS AND COMMUNITY MEMBERS WHO ARE
STILL HERE. THANK YOU FOR YOUR STAMINA.
WE NOTE THAT YOU'RE ALL THE SUPERVISORS ARE STILL HERE
AND THAT MEANS A LOT TO US. WHEN I HEARD ABOUT THIS PROGRAM
FOR A MR. STELLA EDDINGS YEAH. >> ESPINA I THOUGHT THAT WAS
JUST AMAZING THAT YOU ALL ARE TAKING THE TIME TO ADD A BOARD
OF SUPERVISORS FULL MEETING TO RECOGNIZE MEMBERS OF THE
COMMUNITY. WE REALLY APPRECIATE THAT.
THANK YOU. WE FEEL VERY, VERY SEEN.
>> I SHARE THIS AWARD WITH MY HUSBAND FRANCO WHO IS A
CO-FOUNDER OF PRE MEADOWS PARCELS WITH ME.
I AM THE FIRST BORN HERE IN THE U.S. MY FAMILY IS FROM EL
SALVADOR. MY TWO SISTERS WERE BORN THERE.
FRANCO WAS ACTUALLY NOT BORN IN THE U.S. BORN IN ITALY SO HE
HAS THE FULL IMMIGRANT EXPERIENCE STARTING IN S.F.
USDA KINDERGARTEN WITHOUT SPEAKING ENGLISH.
>> BUT WE CURRENTLY ARE EXTREMELY PROUD OF PRIMODOS
PARCELS WHICH AS YOU MENTIONED IS BORN FROM OUR OWN CHILDREN.
DONATELLA MY DAUGHTER GOES TO REARDON HIGH SCHOOL SALVATORE
MY SON AT SAINT THOMAS MORE BUT THAT GREW UP THROUGH OUR
PROGRAM AND THEY ARE FULLY BILINGUAL AND SPANISH LANGUAGE
IS A GIFT THAT WE GIVE TO CHILDREN QUANDO A COMPARATIVE
MS. MAESTRO AT NCA AND THEY CAN SPEAK THE LANGUAGE.
WOW WHAT A GIFT. SO WE CURRENTLY EMPLOYED 20 A
STAFF OF 20 AND ALL OF OUR TEACHERS.
>> WOW JUST AN AMAZING AMAZING LOYALTY RATE AND HOW DO WE
ACHIEVE THAT? FIRST OF ALL, THROUGH BASE
VALUES THAT WE TRY TO TEACH OUR CHILDREN AND SHARE WITH OUR
COMMUNITY VALUES OF RESPECT VALUES A VERY HIGH MORALE
THROUGH PROFESSIONALISM AND COURTESY AND CARE
AND SOCIAL EMOTIONAL FACTORS ALL THAT COMMUNITY BUILDING
REALLY MAKES A DIFFERENCE. >> OUR TEACHERS WHAT THEY START
WITH US TEND TO NEVER LEAVE WHICH IS WONDERFUL.
>> WE LOVE THAT YOU MAY KNOW AS SUPERVISORS THAT UNIVERSITY
PROFESSORS ARE QUITE EXALTED HIGH SCHOOL TEACHERS, MIDDLE
SCHOOL TEACHERS AS WELL. >> THEY SHOULD BE ELEMENTARY
TEACHERS YOUR PRESCHOOL TEACHERS.
I'M HERE TO TELL YOU HOW ARE DOING ANYBODY GOING TO SNAP
WITH ME ARE HERE TO DOING AMAZING WORK FOR THOSE YEARS 0
TO 5 THOSE ARE KEY KEY YEARS IN CHILDREN'S BRAIN DEVELOPMENT
AND CHILDREN SUPERVISOR SOUDER, I KNOW YOU HAVE A YOUNG ONE.
CHOOSE WISELY. THOSE ARE VERY, VERY KEY HERE
SO LET'S SUPPORT THEM. >> I'M GOING TO ASK YOU AS A
BOARD TO TAKE A LOOK AT BABY PROP C AND ALL OTHER FUNDS THAT
ARE THERE. MAKE SURE THAT THEY ARE THERE
FOR ALL SCHOOLS AND NOT JUST FOR A SUBSET OF SCHOOLS IN SAN
FRANCISCO WE NEED ALL KINDS OF SCHOOLS IN SAN FRANCISCO
AND THAT'S VERY, VERY IMPORTANT .
OUR STAFF THANK YOU. OUR STAFF HAS BEEN THROUGH A
LOT THERE AS WE KNOW VARIOUS IMMIGRATION ISSUES, VARIOUS
CULTURAL, SOCIAL EMOTIONAL ATTITUDES TOWARDS LATINOS AMONG
CERTAIN SUBSETS OF OUR POPULATION.
SADLY THESE DAYS AND OUR TEACHERS ARE EXTREMELY PROUD.
>> SO I WANT TO SHARE WITH YOU SOME WORDS FROM ONE OF OUR
TEACHERS A ME AS IS INDEED REGULAR.
SO THEY USE THEIR COMMON VISIONARY FOR A CAREER IN THE
COMMUNITY SPANISH EITHER ZAPATA DE LA FAMILIA THAT MEANS IS
THAT THIS AWARD MAKES ME AS A TEACHER FEEL VERY PROUD OF YOU
MEANING ME AS A VISIONARY AND IT HELPS ME BELIEVE IN THE
HISPANIC COMMUNITY AND TO BE PART OF THE FAMILY WHICH IS
PRIMITIVE SPONSORS YOU HAVE ALWAYS TOLD US WHY NOT US?
WE CAN MAKE A DIFFERENCE. SEE SUBWAY WHICH I THINK
EVERYONE KNOWS FROM VERY FAMOUS PEOPLE CESAR CHAVEZ AND DOLORES
HUERTA. >> SO THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR
YOUR SUPPORT. THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR
SUPPORT OF SMALL BUSINESS. WE HAVE NEGOTIATED COVID AND A
LOT OF OTHER THINGS AND THAT'S MY OTHER ASSET TO YOU AS A
BOARD. A LOT OF BUSINESSES ARE RUN BY
IMMIGRANTS TO THIS COUNTRY OR PEOPLE OF MANY CULTURES ACROSS
THE WORLD AND SO PLEASE WE VALUE YOUR SUPPORT.
>> PLEASE LOOK FOR HOW YOU CAN HELP SMALL BUSINESSES IN YOUR
COMMUNITY. >> WE DO FEEL YOUR WERE A GOOD
LIFEBLOOD FOR YOU ALL. >> SO THANK YOU SO MUCH AND WE
APPRECIATE YOU WHICH I GET I SENSE ONE MORE NOTE IF I MAY
WHILE THE BOARD PRESIDENT IS COMING DOWN, WE ORGANIZE WHAT'S
CALLED THE SAN FRANCISCO PRESCHOOL NIGHT WHICH WILL BE
HELD THIS YEAR AT OCT OCTOBER NINTH AT RIORDAN HIGH SCHOOL
FROM 6 TO 730 ALL OF YOUR DISTRICTS WILL BE REPRESENTED
AS THERE ARE 61 PRESCHOOLS REGISTERED AND WE'LL BE THERE
TALKING WITH FAMILIES FOR FREE. SO PLEASE COME AND SUPPORT US
THERE. SEE YOUR PRESCHOOLS REPRESENTED
THERE. >> THANK YOU AND THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. I APPRECIATE EVERYBODY.
I WANT TO THANK YOU. OKAY.
SO BACK TO ITEMS 25 AND 26. >> MADAM CLERK.
COULD YOU CALL THEM? >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
ITEMS 25 AND 26 ARE TWO RESOLUTIONS THAT DETERMINE THE
TWO LIQUOR LICENSES WILL SERVE THE PUBLIC CONVENIENCE OR
NECESSITY OF THE CITY. ITEM 25 IS A PERSON TO PERSON
PREMISE TO PREMISE TRANSFER OF A TYPE 21 OFF SALE GENERAL BEER
WINE AND DISTILLED SPIRITS LIQUOR LICENSE TO GROCERY
OUTLET INC LOCATED AT 350 BAY STREET AND FOR ITEM 26 THIS IS
THE TYPE 90 ON SALE GENERAL MUSIC VENUE LIQUOR LICENSE TO
THE ENDGAME'S IMPROV LLC DOING BUSINESS AS END GAMES IMPROV
LOCATED AT 2989 MISSION STREET AND TO REQUEST THAT THE
CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF ALCOHOLIC BEVERAGE CONTROL
IMPOSE A CONDITION ON THE ISSUANCE OF EACH LICENSE.
>> MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU CALL THE CALL THE ROLL ON THESE
ITEMS AND ITEMS 25 AND 26 SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR EYES
SUPERVISOR SUTTER SUTTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN HI CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND GAUDIO EYES SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
AND SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANAGEMENT I THERE ARE 11 EYES
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 27 ITEM 27 ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO CREATE THE UNION STREET ENTERTAINMENT
ZONE ON UNION STREET BETWEEN GOUGH AND STEINER STREETS
AND ON FILLMORE STREET BETWEEN UNION AND GREENWICH STREETS
AND TO AFFIRM THE SEQUEL DETERMINATION SUPERVISOR CHERYL
THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDEL MIN AND I'LL IGNORE YOUR LOOKS YOU
JUST GAVE ME SORRY COLLEAGUES I'M PROPOSING AMENDMENTS TODAY
TO THIS ITEM THAT WILL ALLOW EVENTS IN THE UNION STREET
ENTERTAINMENT ZONE THAT DO NOT CLOSE THE STREET.
THESE AMENDMENTS WHICH WE CIRCULATED TO YOUR OFFICES
EARLIER TODAY WILL EMPOWER MERCHANTS ALONG THE STREET TO
HOST SMALLER GATHERINGS ON THE SIDEWALKS AHEAD OF THE HOLIDAY
SEASON. IT'S PIVOTAL THAT UNION STREET
MERCHANTS AS I'M SURE MANY MERCHANTS IN YOUR DISTRICTS AS
WELL ARE ABLE TO TAKE ADVANTAGE OF HOLIDAY SHOPPING
AND INCREASE THEIR REVENUES BY HOSTING THESE TYPES OF SMALLER
EVENTS. AND WE'RE GOING TO CONTINUE TO
WORK WITH THE UNION STREET MERCHANTS ASSOCIATIONS AND THE
NEARBY NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATIONS TO ENSURE THE BEST
IMPLEMENTATION OF THIS ENTERTAINMENT ZONE FOR
EVERYONE. SPECIFICALLY, I'M PROPOSING THE
FOLLOWING LANGUAGE STARTING ON PAGE THREE LINE TEN B
NOTWITHSTANDING SUBSECTION C IF AN ENTERTAINMENT ZONE EVENT
WITHIN THE UNION STREET ENTERTAINMENT ZONE DOES NOT
INVOLVE THE CLOSURE OF A PUBLIC STREET, IT NEED NOT RECEIVE A
PERMIT FOR THE USE OF A PUBLIC STREET UNDER TRANSPORTATION
CODE DIVISION ONE, SECTION 6.6 OR 6.16 OR TRANSPORTATION CODE
DIVISION TWO, SECTION 2 OR 6 OR ANY OTHER OR OTHER APPLICABLE
AUTHORITY OF THE MTA GIVEN THIS AMENDMENT IS SUBSTANTIVE, THIS
ITEM WILL NEED TO BE RETURNED TO THE RULES COMMITTEE FOR
ANOTHER OPPORTUNITY FOR PUBLIC COMMENT.
THUS I MOVE TO ACCEPT THESE AMENDMENTS AND SEND THE AMENDED
VERSION BACK TO COMMITTEE AND THAT WORKS, SAYS MY CITY
ATTORNEY. OKAY, SO THERE'S A MOTION FROM
SUPERVISOR CHERYL IS THERE A SECOND SECONDED BY MELGAR
COLLEAGUES I THINK WE CAN PROBABLY TAKE THAT WITHOUT
OBJECTION. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION.
THE MOTION PASSES. AND MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 28. AND SO MR. PRESIDENT, JUST TO
BE SURE BECAUSE WE WILL DIVIDE THE MOTIONS UP IN OUR MINUTES.
THE AMENDMENTS WERE TAKEN WITHOUT OBJECTION AND IT IS IT
HAS BEEN SENT TO THE RULES COMMITTEE.
OKAY. OKAY, GREAT.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
ITEM 28. >> ITEM 27 A OH WE'RE
DELIBERATING. RIGHT?
SO ITEM 20 IS EIGHT. ITEM 28 IS AN ORDINANCE TO
APPROVE AMENDMENTS TO THE RULES AND REGULATIONS FOR THE
NEIGHBORHOOD BEAUTIFICATION AND GRAFFITI CLEANUP FUND.
>> AND MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU CALL THE ROLL ON THAT ITEM ON
ITEM 28 SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUTER
SAUTER EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR FOR
WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN
CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR
AND ENGARDIO AND GUARDIAN EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES
SUPERVISOR OF MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I AND SUPERVISOR MENDELSON I
MANDELL MEANT EITHER ARI LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEM 29 ITEM 29 MOTION TO APPOINT CRYSTAL HAWKINGS TO THE
CHILD CARE PLANNING AND ADVISORY COUNCIL TERM
ENDING MARCH 19TH 2028 AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT ITEM
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS
APPROVED. >> MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE
CALL OUR NEXT ITEM ITEM 30 THIS IS A MOTION TO REAPPOINT
SUPERVISOR RAFAEL MEN TO THE CALIFORNIA STATE ASSOCIATION OF
COUNTIES TERM ENDING DECEMBER 1ST, 2026.
>> THANK YOU COLLEAGUES. I ENTERTAIN A MOTION TO EXCUSE
PRESIDENT AMENDMENT FROM THIS ITEM MADE BY SUPERVISOR FIELD
OR SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR CHEN MADAM CLERK.
ON THAT MOTION ON THE MOTION AND MR..
MR. PRESIDENT THIS IS ON THE MOTION TO EXCUSED OR WAS THAT
WITHOUT OBJECTION TO WHAT WE CAN LET'S DO IT WITHOUT
OBJECTION. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION.
WITHOUT OBJECTION. >> PRESIDENT AMENDMENT IS
EXCUSED. AND NOW LET'S DO THE ROLL CALL
ON ITEM ITEM 30. >> SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SUTTER SUTTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON I WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND GAUDIO I SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER I AND SUPERVISOR MY MIND MAHMOOD I THERE ARE
CHENNAI'S THANK YOU MOTION CARRIES PLEASE CALL ITEM 31
ITEM 31 THIS IS A MOTION TO APPOINT SUPERVISOR SHERMAN
WALTON TO THE COMMITTEE ON CITY WORKFORCE ALIGNMENT FOR AN
INDEFINITE TERM. >> CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO
EXCUSE SUPERVISOR WALTON FROM VOTING ON THIS MATTER?
MOVED BY SOLDER SECONDED BY FIELDER WE CAN TAKE THAT MOTION
WITHOUT OBJECTION. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION.
THE MOTION PASSES. AND THEN MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE ITEM ON ITEM 31 SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR EYES SUPERVISOR SARDAR SUTTER EYES SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN
EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR AND AUDIO AND GAUDIO
EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
AND SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANAGEMENT I THERE ARE EYES
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO
TO OUR COMMITTEE REPORTS YES ITEM 32 WAS CONSIDERED BY THE
LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING
ON MONDAY, SEPTEMBER 29TH AND WAS RECOMMENDED AS A
COMMITTEE REPORT ITEM 32 IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PLANNING
CODE TO DESIGNATE THE MINT MALL AND HALL AT 951 THROUGH 957
MISSION STREET IN THE SOUTH SIDE MISSION STREET BETWEEN
FIFTH AND SIXTH STREETS AS A LANDMARK AND TO AFFIRM THE
SECRET DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS
SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDELA
AND COLLEAGUES I'M PROUD TO BE SPONSORING THIS COMMUNITY
INITIATED LANDMARKING OF THE MINT MALL.
THIS IS BOTH A SIGNIFICANT CULTURAL INSTITUTION FOR SAN
FRANCISCO'S FILIPINO COMMUNITY AND A CHERISHED NEIGHBORHOOD
GEM. THE MINT MALL HAS A LONG
AND STORIED HISTORY WHICH GIVEN THE HOUR I WILL REFRAIN FROM
SHARING AT THIS TIME. BUT I DO WANT TO EXPRESS KUDOS
TO THE FILIPINO COMMUNITY LEADERS MANY OF WHOM WERE
INSTRUMENTAL IN SAVING THE MINT MALL BACK IN THE 1990S WHO
CHAMPIONED THIS HISTORIC LANDMARKING.
THIS WAS SENT AS A COMMITTEE REPORT TO ENSURE ENACTMENT
WITHIN FILIPINO AMERICAN HERITAGE HISTORY MONTH WHICH
STARTS TOMORROW. SO I WANT TO THANK EVERYBODY
FROM THE FILIPINO COMMUNITY WHO SPEARHEADED THIS PROCESS.
THANKS AS WELL TO MADISON TAM FROM MY OFFICE WHO WORKED
TIRELESSLY ON THIS. AND FINALLY THANKS TO MY CO
SPONSORS PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN AND SUPERVISORS CHAN SARDAR
CHERYL CHEN AND MELGAR FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP AND SUPPORT.
IT MEANS A LOT TO THE COMMUNITY, TO THE NEIGHBORHOOD
AND TO ME. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON ITEM 32. SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SAUTER SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR AND GAUDIO AND GAUDIO I SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I AND SUPERVISOR
RANDLEMAN HI MANAGEMENT EITHER ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION
THE ORDINANCES PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO
ROLL CALL FOR INTRODUCTIONS FIRST MEMBER UP TO INTRODUCE
NEW BUSINESS IS SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES HAPPY GOOD NEIGHBOR
WEEK AT LATER WE WILL BE VOTING TO DECLARE THE FIRST OFFICIAL
GOOD NEIGHBOR WEEKEND SAN FRANCISCO AND WILL CELEBRATE
WITH EVENTS ACROSS THE CITY. AND SO WE'RE GOING TO KEEP THAT
NEIGHBORLY SPIRIT GOING STRONG .
TODAY I AM INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION TO SUPPORT THE SIX
NEIGHBORS CAMPAIGN LED BY THE CALIFORNIA VOLUNTEERS OF THE
OFFICE OF THE GOVERNOR PARTNERING WITH THE DEPARTMENT
OF DISABILITY AND AGING SERVICES AND THE HUMAN SERVICES
AGENCY. WE ARE ENCOURAGING SAN
FRANCISCANS TO TAKE A PLEDGE TO MEET SIX NEIGHBORS AND TO SHARE
YOUR EXPERIENCES AS PART OF SOCIAL CONNECTIONS.
THIS WEEK THERE ARE OVER 21,000 CALIFORNIA WHO HAVE SIGNED UP
AND ONLY ABOUT 400 IN SAN FRANCISCO.
SO LET'S HELP RAISE THOSE NUMBERS AND PERHAPS SEE WHICH
DISTRICT SUPERVISOR COULD GET THE MOST PLEDGES.
RESEARCH SHOWS THAT KNOWING AT LEAST SIX NEIGHBORS IMPROVES
HEALTH AND WELL-BEING. >> IT MAKES OUR COMMUNITIES
BETTER PREPARED DURING DISASTERS AS WELL.
SO TO LEARN MORE VISIT W W W DOT S.F. HSA DOT ORG.
FORWARD SLASH NEIGHBOR NEIGHBOR PROGRAM.
>> NEXT I WILL BE INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION TO DECLARE OCTOBER
17TH 2025 BROKE AS STUART DAY IN SAN FRANCISCO.
STUART CHAPMAN MY FRIEND AT BETTER KNOWN AS BROKE GUEST
STUART IS A SAN FRANCISCO CULTURAL ICON A ONCE MAYORAL
CANDIDATE SELF-PROCLAIMED RABBLE ROUSER, AVID WORLD
TRAVELER AND ONE OF THE FUNNIEST PEOPLE I'VE EVER MET.
>> AFTER TWO DECADES OF SHARING HIS PROLIFIC WRITING WITH OVER
15,000 ARTICLES PUBLISHED ON HIS WEBSITE BROKE AS STUART.COM
HE HAS NOW PUBLISHED A BOOK THE WORST OF BROKEN STUART 20 YEARS
OF LOVE DEATH AND DIVE BARS IN AN ERA WHERE PUBLICATIONS
KEEP VANISHING FASTER THAN AFFORDABLE APARTMENT WORK.
STUART HAS STUBBORNLY CONTINUED TO PUBLISH INDEPENDENT LOCAL
JOURNALISM JOURNALISM TELLING THE STORIES OF ARTISTS,
WORKERS, WEIRDOS, ACTIVISTS AND ALL THE PEOPLE THAT MAKE
SAN FRANCISCO WONDERFUL. >> CONGRATULATIONS, BROOKE
STUART ON YOUR NEW BOOK AND WE KNOW YOUR LOFT ON OCTOBER 17TH
AT KILOWATT WILL BE EPIC IN ONE NIGHT TO BE REMEMBER THANK YOU
AND THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR SUPERVISOR SADR.
>> YES, COLLEAGUES LAST WEEK I JOINED MAYOR LURIE AND OUR LAW
ENFORCEMENT LEADERS TO ANNOUNCE A MAJOR ENFORCEMENT OPERATION
IN WHICH SIX DIRT BIKES AND ONE ATV WERE SEIZED.
THAT OPERATION ALSO INCLUDED FOUR ARRESTS FOR POSSESSION OF
STOLEN VEHICLES. THIS WAS WELCOME NEWS TO MY
CONSTITUENTS AND I IMAGINE MANY OF YOURS WHO ARE FED UP AND ON
EDGE BECAUSE OF DANGEROUS DIRT BIKE RIDING AND SIDESHOW
ACTIVITY. THIS BEHAVIOR HAS BECOME MORE
AGGRESSIVE AND CONSTANT RIPPING THROUGH CROWDED RESIDENTIAL
AREAS AND EVEN ROUTINELY SPILLING ON TO SIDEWALKS
AND PARKS. SO BUILDING ON THAT PROGRESS
WITH THOSE ENFORCEMENT ACTIONS TODAY I AM INTRODUCING
LEGISLATION THAT WILL INCREASE THE FINE FOR MISDEMEANOR
CONVICTIONS OF OFFENSES RELATED TO SIDESHOWS AND ILLEGAL STUNT
DRIVING. WE ARE BRINGING THIS FINE UP TO
THE STANDARDS OF SIMILAR MUNICIPALITY USED TO SHOW THAT
SAN FRANCISCO IS PAYING ATTENTION AND TAKING THIS
SERIOUSLY. CURRENTLY OUR FINE IS LOWER
THAN SAN JOSE. FRESNO, OAKLAND AND MANY OTHERS
WHICH MAKES US AN ATTRACTIVE TARGET FOR THIS DANGEROUS
BEHAVIOR. OUR LEGISLATION WILL FIX THIS
AND BE ANOTHER TOOL AT OUR DISPOSAL TO END THIS RECKLESS
DRIVING AND KEEP OUR COMMUNITY SAFE.
>> I WANT TO THANK TITA BELL IN MY OFFICE FOR HER WORK ON
THIS AS WELL AS JEN HUBER IN THE CITY'S ATTORNEY CITY
ATTORNEY'S OFFICE. THANK YOU AS WELL TO MY EARLY
CO SPONSORS SUPERVISOR MAN WOMAN CHERYL AND DORSEY.
>> TODAY I ALSO HAVE A HEARING REQUEST TO INTRODUCE FOR
7-ELEVEN POST WHICH IS A LARGE HOMELESS SHELTER AND LOCATED
IN THE LOWER HILL NEIGHBORHOOD.
7-ELEVEN POST IS OPERATED BY URBAN ALCHEMY AND WHILE I
UNDERSTAND THERE ARE CONCERNS ABOUT THE ORGANIZATION'S
PRACTICES CITYWIDE, OUR HEARING WILL PRIMARILY BE FOCUSED ON
THEIR WORK AT 7-ELEVEN POST. >> AT THIS SITE WE KNOW FOR
EXAMPLE, THERE HAS BEEN UNAUTHORIZED OVERSPENDING TO
THE TUNE OF $800,000 IN WHICH URBAN ALCHEMY KNOWINGLY
INCREASED STAFF COMPENSATION BEYOND THE CITY'S AGREED UPON
GRANT DESPITE GUIDANCE FROM SAGE OF COURSE TO NOT DO THIS.
THAT IS DEEPLY CONCERNING. AND AS WE SIT ON THE CUSP OF A
MULTIYEAR AGREEMENT WITH A PROVIDER FOR 7-ELEVEN POST, I
WANT TO ENSURE THAT WE ARE NOT RUSHING INTO ANYTHING AND THAT
WE MONITOR FINANCIAL RED FLAGS ADEQUATELY.
SO OUR HEARING TO BE HELD IN 60 DAYS WILL ALLOW US TO DO JUST
THAT. >> AND WITH THOSE TWO ITEMS THE
REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL COLLEAGUES. TODAY I'M INTRODUCING A
RESOLUTION THAT SPEAKS TO ONE OF THE MOST URGENT
RESPONSIBILITIES WE HAVE WHICH IS PROTECTING OUR CHILDREN
AND FAMILIES. SAN FRANCISCO IS IN THE MIDST
OF A PUBLIC SAFETY AND PUBLIC HEALTH CRISIS.
WE ALL SEE IT. OPEN DRUG USE, TRAFFICKING
OVERDOSES HAPPENING ON IN THE SHADOWS WHICH WE DON'T WANT IT
TO HAPPEN THERE EITHER BUT ALSO IN BROAD DAYLIGHT IN THE VERY
SPACES MEANT FOR KIDS TO PLAY, STUDENTS TO LEARN AND FAMILIES
TOGETHER. IN RECENT MONTHS I'VE HEARD
FROM PARENTS AND EDUCATORS AND NEIGHBORS WE'RE DEEPLY
CONCERNED ABOUT WHAT'S HAPPENING NEAR OUR PARKS, OUR
SCHOOLS AND OUR PLAYGROUNDS. THEY'RE NOT JUST WORRIED.
THEY'RE ANGRY, CONFUSED AND SCARED.
THEY ASK WHO DO WE CALL WHEN SOMEONE IS USING OR DEALING
DRUGS RIGHT NEXT TO A JUNGLE GYM OR A SCHOOL ENTRANCE?
THEY ASKED WHY ISN'T THERE A FASTER, CLEARER RESPONSE?
>> AND THEY ASK WHEN OFFICERS ARRIVE WHY IS BAD BEHAVIOR
ALLOWED TO REMAIN ON THE SCENE? AND QUITE FRANKLY THEY DESERVE
ANSWERS AND ACTION. >> THIS RESOLUTION CALLS ON THE
SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT TO DEVELOP AND IMPLEMENT A
COMPREHENSIVE PLAN FOR ENFORCEMENT AND INTERVENTION
FOCUSED SPECIFICALLY WITHIN 250FT OF PARKS, PLAYGROUNDS
AND SCHOOLS. THAT PLAN COULD INCLUDE
CITATIONS FOR ILLEGAL ACTIVITY ON SITE ASSESSMENTS FOR HEALTH
NEEDS AND REMOVAL AND REFERRAL TO DETOX OR TREATMENT SERVICES
WHEN APPROPRIATE. >> THIS ISN'T ABOUT MASS
ARRESTS. >> IT'S ABOUT SETTING CLEAR
STANDARDS AND ENSURING COORDINATED COMPASSIONATE
ENFORCEMENT IN SPACES WHERE OUR MOST VULNERABLE ARE AT WORK.
>> IT'S ALSO ABOUT IMPROVING HOW WE WORK USING TECHNOLOGY TO
STREAMLINE REPORTING AND MAKING IT EASIER FOR OFFICERS TO DO
THEIR JOBS EFFECTIVELY. BUT WE ALSO NEED TO ACKNOWLEDGE
THAT ENFORCEMENT PLAYS A ROLE. THIS RESOLUTION DOES NOT CREATE
NEW LAWS. IT DOES NOT CRIMINALIZE
ADDICTION. WHAT IT DOES IS REAFFIRM OUR
DUTY TO KEEP PUBLIC SPACES SAFE WHILE OFFERING A PATH TO
RECOVERY AND SUPPORT FOR THOSE STRUGGLING WITH SUBSTANCE USE.
MOST IMPORTANTLY, IT HOLDS US ACCOUNTABLE.
IT ASKS THE POLICE DEPARTMENT TO RETURN TO THIS BOARD WITHIN
60 DAYS WITH A DETAILED IMPLEMENTATION PLAN TIMELINES,
RESOURCES, COORDINATION STRATEGIES AND CHALLENGES.
>> COLLEAGUES, IF WE CAN'T SAY THAT OUR CHILDREN ARE SAFE
WALKING TO SCHOOL OR THAT A PARENT CAN TAKE THEIR TODDLER
TO A PARK WITHOUT WORRY THEN WE ARE NOT DOING OUR JOBS.
SO LET'S TAKE THIS STEP TOGETHER TO MAKE OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS SAFER, OUR PUBLIC SPACES CLEANER AND OUR RESPONSE
SMARTER AND MORE COMPASSIONATE. >> AND THE REST I SUBMIT THANK
YOU. SUPERVISOR SHERYL SUPERVISOR
WALTON. SUBMIT.
THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR CHAN. SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE A
RESOLUTION TO INTRODUCE AND ALSO IN MEMORIAM.
>> I AM INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION TODAY TO SUPPORT
IMMIGRANTS TO HAVE THEIR RIGHT TO SEEK HEALTH CARE WITHOUT
FEAR. >> ALL IMMIGRANTS HAVE A RIGHT
TO SEE HEALTH CARE AND SHOULD NOT BE SUBJECT TO FEAR
AND ANXIETY DUE TO THEIR IMMIGRATION STATUS.
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT RECENTLY RECEIVED PREVIOUS POLICY
GUIDANCE THAT PROHIBITED IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT
IN SENSITIVE AREAS SUCH AS HOSPITALS, SCHOOLS
AND CHURCHES. THIS MEANS THAT HOSPITALS
AND CLINICS COULD BE THE TARGET OF IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT.
>> THERE HAVE ALREADY BEEN HORRIFYING SAMPLES SUCH AS THE
TEN YEAR OLD GIRL WOULD BRING CANCER BEING DETAINED
AND DEPORTED WHILE ON HER WAY TO THE HOSPITAL FOR EMERGENCY
MEDICAL TREATMENT IN HOUSTON, TEXAS.
THIS HAS HAD A CHILLING EFFECT ON IMMIGRANTS SEEKING CARE.
>> WE ARE ASKING THAT SAN FRANCISCO COSTS ON HOSPITALS,
CLINICS AND HEALTH PROVIDERS TO PROTECT THE IMMIGRANT
COMMUNITIES THEY SERVE AND TO HONOR ETHICAL GUIDELINES OF
MEDICAL PROFESSIONALS TO AVOID HARM AND PROVIDE CARE TO ALL
WHO NEED IT. >> THANK YOU TO SEIU, UAW FOR
YOUR LEADERSHIP AND ALSO THANK YOU TO SUPERVISORS CHEN, MALKA,
FEODOR MOORE, SALTER AND DORSEY FOR YOUR EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP.
>> TODAY I WOULD ALSO LIKE TO JOIN OUR MEETING IN HONOR OF
NANCY WILSON. NANCY WAS A REMARKABLE WOMAN
WHO STOOD AS A RADIANT BEACON OF HOPE.
THROUGH HER TIRELESSLY DEDICATION TO HEART WALKED HER
UNWAVERING COMMITMENT TO UPLIFTING OTHERS AND FOSTERING
POSITIVE CHANGE HAS BECOME A SOURCE OF INSPIRATION FOR
EVERYONE FORTUNATE ENOUGH TO KNOW HER.
>> AS A TEENAGER GROWING UP IN THE CROCKER, AMAZON
AND EXCELSIOR NEIGHBORHOODS, NANCY WAS ACTIVELY INVOLVED
IN HER COMMUNITY THROUGH SERVES AS THE PRESIDENT OF THE
EXCELSIOR YOUTH CLUB WHERE SHE HAS FACILITATED PROGRAMING
AND MOBILIZED IT YOUTH TO ENGAGE IN THE CREATION OF
EXCELSIOR MURALS THAT ADORN DEPARTS AS WELL AS A 52 BUS
STOP ON EXCELSIOR AND MISSION. >> IN EVERY ROLE THEREAFTER SHE
BOUGHT HER WISDOM, HUMOR AND STEADY LEADERSHIP FROM THE
PRISCILLA CENTER CHOOSING ANTONY'S WOMAN FOUNDATION TO
FAMILY OASIS NORTH COUNTY OUTREACH COLLABORATIVE AND KOP
IMPACT AND TO THE ESSENCE OF NOT NANA MANNER PARENT PROJECTS
CHARLOTTE WITH PURPOSE AND WOOD HOT.
>> SHE BECAME A STRONG ADVOCATE TO ENSURE THE PACIFIC ISLANDER
COMMUNITY WAS PROPERLY REPRESENTED WITHIN ASIAN
PACIFIC ISLANDER SPACES. IN HER WORK OF DOING
PREVENTION, EARLY INTERVENTION AND OUTREACH TO YOUTH ON
SEPTEMBER 9TH HER HARD WORK ON EARTH WHICH ITS FINAL CHAPTER A
LIFE SPAN WEAVING OF STRING AND KINDNESS IN INTO EVERY
CORNER SHOULD TOUCH. YET THIS WAS NOT AN ENDING BUT
A CORNER A NATION OF HER SPIRIT .
THE QUEEN ROSE FROM HER EARTHLY THORN CARING HER HEART OR INTO
RAMSAY BEYOND. WE WEAR HER RING CONTINUES
SILENT YET POWERFUL GUIDING US ,INSPIRING US AND RULING WITH
THE SAME UNWAVERING LOVE DOES SHAPE OUR LIVES.
THOUGH WE NO LONGER SEE HER CROWN IN THIS WORLD ITS LIGHT
SHINES ETERNALLY. >> A REMINDER THAT TO HEART
WHERE IT NEVER DIES NANCY'S SURVIVED IT BY HER MARTYRDOM.
CHRISTINA SALOMON ZENA NAHA WILSON.
HER CHILDREN DANU DANNY BOY NAHA VAI VAI ÉVOLUE JASMINE
IMMORTAL AND GRANDDAUGHTERS JEANETTE AND CHIKA TOLEDANO
BINA AND MELANIE HONEY. >> SHE LOVED HER NIECES
AND NEPHEWS AS HER OWN AND EVEN THEIR CHILDREN AS HER BABIES.
>> THROUGHOUT HER LIFE NANCY NURTURED HER RELATIONSHIP WITH
COUNTLESS FAMILY FRIENDS LEAVING AN UNFORGETTABLE
IMPRINT ON THEIR LIVES AND AND HER INFAMOUS RAT SMOOCH ON
THEIR CHEEK. >> NANCY'S PRESENCE WAS A
TESTAMENT TO THE TRANSFORMATIVE TRANSFORMING POWER OF KINDNESS
ILLUMINATING THE PATH TOWARD A MORE COMPASSIONATE
AND INTERCONNECTED COMMUNITY. IN HER WE FIND HER NOT ONLY A
LEADER BUT A GENUINE SOURCE OF LIGHT THAT ENCOURAGES US ALL TO
ACTIVELY CONTRIBUTE TO THE WELL-BEING OF THOSE AROUND US.
>> THANK YOU. AND THE RIVERSIDE SUMMIT.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHEN SUPERVISOR DORSEY.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. FIRST COLLEAGUES AS YOUR
REPRESENTATIVE TO THE CITY'S HEALTH SERVICE SYSTEMS.
IT IS AMONG MY DUTIES THERE TO EVANGELIZE OPEN ENROLLMENT SO I
WANT TO LET EVERYONE KNOW THAT THE 2026 PLAN YEAR OPEN
ENROLLMENT BEGINS TOMORROW MORNING AT 8 A.M. WEDNESDAY,
OCTOBER FIRST. PERHAPS MORE IMPORTANT IT WILL
CONCLUDE ON FRIDAY OCTOBER 24TH 2025 AT 5 P.M..
SO MARK YOUR CALENDARS. WE WILL NOT GET THE FULL MONTH
OF OCTOBER. THIS IS ONE OPPORTUNITY EACH
YEAR FOR MEMBERS TO MAKE CHANGES TO THEIR HEALTH
BENEFITS INCLUDING MEDICAL, DENTAL AND VISION COVERAGE
AND TO ADD AND REMOVE DEPENDENTS OR TO ENROLL IN A
FLEXIBLE SPENDING ACCOUNT OR TO MAKE ADJUSTMENTS TO IT.
I STRONGLY ENCOURAGE ALL MEMBERS TO REVIEW THE AVAILABLE
OPTIONS CAREFULLY, COMPLETE ANY NECESSARY CHANGES AND SUBMIT
THEIR ENROLLMENT BEFORE THE OCTOBER 24TH DEADLINE.
SECOND, I'M HONORED TO INTRODUCE TODAY THE WEST SUMMIT
ENTERTAINMENT ZONE A HIGHLY ANTICIPATED INITIATIVE THAT
WILL STRENGTHEN OUR CITY'S NIGHTLIFE, SUPPORT OUR CULTURAL
COMMUNITIES AND BRING RENEWED VIBRANCE VIBRANCY TO OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS, STREETS AND SMALL BUSINESSES.
THIS ENTERTAINMENT ZONE WILL ALLOW PATRONS TO ENJOY TO-GO
BEVERAGES IN SOME OF SAN FRANCISCO'S MOST CELEBRATED
NIGHTLIFE CORRIDORS INCLUDING FOLSOM STREET AND 11TH STREET.
IT WILL ALSO ELEVATE SIGNATURE EVENTS LIKE THE FOLSOM STREET
FAIR WHICH WE JUST CELEBRATED THIS PAST WEEKEND AND GARRISON
STREET FAIR WHICH WE WILL BE CELEBRATING ON OCTOBER 18TH.
THIS WILL FURTHER SHOWCASE THE CULTURAL RICHNESS, ECONOMIC
VITALITY AND DOUBTLESS TO THE ERA PRINCIPLE STREAK OF OUR
SOUTH OF MARKET COMMUNITY. I'D LIKE TO THANK ALL THE
PARTNERS WHO HELPED TO MAKE THIS POSSIBLE ESPECIALLY BEN
VAN OUTEN, KELLY VARIAN FROM THE OFFICE OF ECONOMIC
WORKFORCE AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT.
VICKIE WONG FROM THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE THE SOMA WEST
COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT AND THE LEATHER AND LGBTQ PLUS
CULTURAL DISTRICT. WE ALSO WORK CLOSELY WITH
SEVERAL COMMUNITY STAKEHOLDERS AND SMALL BUSINESSES TO ENSURE
THIS PROPOSAL HAD BROAD SUPPORT AND MET THE NEEDS OF THE
NEIGHBORHOOD. FINALLY COLLEAGUES I AM TODAY
INTRODUCING LEGISLATION TO REPEAL A MUNICIPAL CODE
PROVISION THAT AUTHORIZES COURTS TO AWARD ATTORNEY'S FEES
AND COSTS TO ANY PLAINTIFF WHO PREVAILS IN CIVIL LITIGATION
AGAINST THE CITY AND ITS TAXPAYERS FOR VIOLATING OUR
SURVEILLANCE ORDINANCE. IN MY VIEW, PREVAILING
PLAINTIFF FEE AND COST PROVISIONS WRITTEN INTO OUR
SURVEILLANCE ORDINANCE BACK IN 2019 WERE IRRESPONSIBLE.
IT HAS INCENTIVIZED BASELESS AND COSTLY LITIGATION WHICH HAS
ALREADY SQUANDERED HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF TAXPAYER DOLLARS
OVER BOGUS ALLEGED VIOLATIONS OF A FLAWED LAW THAT HAS BEEN
ONEROUS TO ADMINISTER SINCE IT WAS FIRST ENACTED.
FOR CONTEXT ATTORNEY'S FEES PROVISIONS FOR PREVAILING
PLAINTIFFS IN CIVIL LITIGATION ARE RARE IN THE UNITED STATES.
AS I SAW DURING MY OWN 14 YEARS IN THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE,
THEY ARE GENERALLY LIMITED ONLY TO THE MOST SERIOUS FEDERAL
CIVIL RIGHTS AND CONSTITUTIONAL VIOLATIONS BY THE GOVERNMENT.
THERE THEY PLAY AN IMPORTANT ROLE TO ASSURE ACCESS TO
JUSTICE FOR THOSE WHO MAY NOT HAVE IT.
THESE KINDS OF FEE AND COST PROVISIONS SHOULD NOT BE
EXPLOITED FOR PLAINTIFFS FINANCIAL GAIN OVER PAPERWORK
DEFICIENCIES. HOWEVER, AS THEY HAVE BEEN FOR
THE FOR THE SAN FRANCISCO SURVEILLANCE TECHNOLOGY
ORDINANCE. MORE RECENTLY A LAWSUIT BY
SECURE JUSTICE EXPOSED JUST HOW CYNICALLY SELF-DEALING THIS
LEGISLATE AND LITIGATE SHAKEDOWN IS WITH CLAIMS THAT
STAND TO REAP SIGNIFICANT FINANCIAL REWARDS FOR THE VERY
SAME ADVOCATES WHO DEVISE THE LAW'S MANDATES AND ATTORNEYS
FEES PROVISIONS IN THE FIRST PLACE.
IT IS A SELF-DEALING PRACTICE THAT I DON'T THINK PASSES
MUSTER WITH TAXPAYERS AND SO I'M INTRODUCING LEGISLATION TO
END IT. I WANT TO EXPRESS MY
APPRECIATION TO SUPERVISOR CHERYL AND PRESIDENT MANDOLIN
FOR THEIR EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP. AND I LOOK FORWARD TO REACHING
OUT FOR FURTHER CONVERSATIONS TO EARN MORE SUPPORT FOR THIS
NEEDED CHANGE AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FOR DORSEY
SUPERVISOR AND GAUDIO THANK YOU COLLEAGUES.
WHEN I GAVE THE COMMENCEMENT SPEECH FOR POLITICAL SCIENCE
GRADUATES AT SAN FRANCISCO STATE LAST YEAR, I TOLD THE
CLASS YOU ARE CHARGED WITH ANALYZING AND NAVIGATING SOME
OF THE WORLD'S MOST INTRACTABLE ISSUES.
BUT IF YOU WANT TO PRACTICE YOUR SKILLS FOR THE STATE
DEPARTMENT OR THE UNITED NATIONS, GO TO ANY NEIGHBORHOOD
ASSOCIATION MEETING IN SAN FRANCISCO AND ASK THE FOLLOWING
QUESTIONS. SHOULD THE GREAT HIGHWAY BE A
HIGHWAY FOR CARS OR A PARK FOR PEOPLE?
WHERE SHOULD WE BUILD HOUSING? AND HOW TALL SHOULD THE
BUILDINGS BE? I REMEMBER THAT LINE DREW SOME
KNOWING LAUGHTER FROM THE AUDIENCE.
THEN I SAID DARE TO ANSWER THOSE QUESTIONS AND YOU RISK
BEING KICKED OUT OF OFFICE AS A ONE TERM SUPERVISOR.
ANOTHER LAUGH LINE BECAUSE COMEDY IS FOUND IN THE PAINFUL
TRUTH. MY TIME AS SUPERVISOR WILL BE
SHORTER THAN EXPECTED. BUT TODAY I WANT TO SHARE WITH
YOU MY HOPES FOR THE FUTURE OF OUR CITY.
>> THERE'S A PLAQUE ABOVE MY DESK THAT SAYS WHAT WOULD JIMMY
CARTER DO A ONE TERM PRESIDENT. BUT HISTORY HAS SHOWN THE
WISDOM OF HIS VIEWS ON HUMAN RIGHTS, THE ECONOMY AND THE
ENVIRONMENT. HE PUT SOLAR PANELS ON THE ROOF
OF THE WHITE HOUSE NEARLY 50 YEARS AGO.
AND WHEN JIMMY CARTER LOST HIS REELECTION CAMPAIGN, THE NEW
PRESIDENT RONALD REAGAN TORE OUT THOSE SOLAR PANELS.
AMERICA DOUBLED DOWN ON THE GAS AND OIL INDUSTRY.
IMAGINE HOW MUCH BETTER THE WORLD WOULD BE IF WE HAD
FOLLOWED JIMMY CARTER'S VISION AND SPENT THE PAST HALF CENTURY
FOCUSED ON ADVANCING RENEWABLE ENERGY.
I WISH MORE ELECTED OFFICIALS HAD THE COURAGE OF JIMMY CARTER
. >> IMAGINE IF THE BAY AREA
LEADERS IN THE 1960S HAD MORE COURAGE WHEN PLANNING BART WE
WOULD HAVE TRAIN TUNNELS FROM DOWNTOWN TO THE WEST SIDE
AND UNDER 19TH AVENUE. BART WOULD GO TO MARIN IN THE
NORTH SAN JOSE IN THE SOUTH WITH MULTIPLE CROSSINGS TO THE
EAST BAY. BUT IT WAS NOT POLITICALLY
POPULAR AND POLITICAL SURVIVAL USUALLY COMES FIRST FOR
POLITICIANS. >> DOES ANYONE REMEMBER THE
NAMES OF CITY SUPERVISORS FROM THE 1960S?
EVEN MAYORS AND GOVERNORS ARE EVENTUALLY FORGOTTEN.
WE MAY NOT KNOW THEIR NAMES BUT WE WOULD BE GRATEFUL IF THEY
HAD CREATED THE PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION SYSTEM WE SO
DESPERATELY NEED TODAY AND THAT'S WHY WE MUST ASK
OURSELVES WHAT DECISIONS ARE WE MAKING TODAY THAT PEOPLE WILL
APPRECIATE IN 50 YEARS? EVEN IF WE ARE NOT REMEMBERED.
THAT'S WHY I ASK MYSELF WHAT WOULD JIMMY CARTER DO?
THIS QUESTION WAS ON MY MIND FOR A NUMBER OF ISSUES THAT
DIVIDED OUR BOARD AND THE PUBLIC.
I VOTED FOR THE CEASE FIRE RESOLUTION.
I DEFENDED OUR SANCTUARY CITY POLICY.
I CALLED FOR THE RELEASE OF THE BANK O'BRIEN VIDEO.
AND I STOOD WITH LABOR STOOD WITH LABOR WHEN THE VOTE WAS
NOT UNANIMOUS. I FACED A LOT OF PRESSURE TO
VOTE DIFFERENTLY. BUT I VOTED MY CONSCIENCE.
I'M PROUD OF THAT AND I'M PROUD OF WHAT MY OFFICE HAS DONE FOR
THE SUNSET DISTRICT IN MY NEARLY THREE YEARS AS
SUPERVISOR. >> WHILE WE DIDN'T SOLVE WORLD
PEACE, I MADE SURE WE PRIORITIZE THE TANGIBLE THINGS
WE COULD DO TO IMPROVE THE DAILY LIVES OF RESIDENTS.
THAT'S WHY I CREATED AN ONLINE FIX IT FORM TO UPLOAD A PHOTO
OF A PROBLEM THAT NEEDS FIXING OUR FIX IT FILE ADDRESSED
THOUSANDS OF CONSTITUENT ISSUES FROM POTHOLE PATCHING TO
PLAYGROUND REPAIRS. WE LAUNCHED THE SUNSET NIGHT
MARKET WITH COMMUNITY PARTNERS. IT ATTRACTED TENS OF THOUSANDS
OF PEOPLE TO THE SUNSET TO SUPPORT LOCAL BUSINESSES.
WE PROVED WHAT'S POSSIBLE FOR NIGHT MARKETS ON COMMERCIAL
CORRIDORS CITYWIDE. NOW THEY'RE EVERYWHERE
AND THAT'S WONDERFUL. WE LEGISLATED OPPORTUNITIES FOR
HOMEOWNERS TO BUILD AND SELL BACKYARD IN-LAW UNITS GIVING
LONGTIME RESIDENTS OPTIONS TO DOWNSIZE AND CREATE FAMILY
WEALTH. WE LEGISLATED TALLER APARTMENT
BUILDINGS ON CORNER LOTS SO FAMILIES CAN STAY IN SAN
FRANCISCO. IT ALLOWS FOR A GROUND FLOOR
AMENITY LIKE A GROCERY OR A CAFE THAT AN ENTIRE
NEIGHBORHOOD CAN BENEFIT FROM. WE WORKED WITH PARENT ADVOCATES
AND SPONSORED PROP G WHICH PROVIDED THE PUBLIC PRESSURE
THE SCHOOL DISTRICT NEEDED TO BRING BACK EIGHTH GRADE
ALGEBRA. AFTER A DECADE OF DELAY WHEN
MERCHANTS WERE STRUGGLING DURING THE TERRIBLE TRAIN
CONSTRUCTION WE SECURED THEM $1 MILLION IN RELIEF FUNDING.
WE HELPED RESTORE FUNDING FOR CIVIL LEGAL SERVICES AND FOOD
SECURITY FOR SENIORS IN THE CITY BUDGET.
WE MET WITH EVERY OFFICER AT TERRYVILLE POLICE STATION
AND VISITED THE FIREHOUSES TO HEAR DIRECTLY WHAT OUR FIRST
RESPONDERS NEED. I ALSO CREATED A CIVILIAN
PUBLIC SAFETY LIAISON TO ASSIST CRIME VICTIMS.
THEY RUN CRIME PREVENTION PROGRAMS IN ENGLISH, CANTONESE
AND MANDARIN. THE SUNSET CHINESE CULTURAL
DISTRICT ADOPTED ITS STRATEGIC REPORT FOR CULTURAL HISTORY,
HOUSING AND ECONOMIC SUSTAINABILITY IN THE SUNSET.
AND WHEN THE GREENWAY ALONG SUNSET BOULEVARD HAD FADED
AND FALLEN INTO DISREPAIR OVER THE YEARS WE DELIVERED CITY
AND STATE INVESTMENTS TO MAKE IT GREEN AGAIN.
RESIDENTS HAD LONG ASKED FOR REC AND PARK GARDENERS.
AND THEY'RE FINALLY COMING. NOW THE TWO MILES OF PARKLAND
ALONG SUNSET BOULEVARD CAN CONNECT TO LAKE SAID AND GOLDEN
GATE PARK TO CREATE AN EMERALD NECKLACE OF SAN FRANCISCO THAT
EXTENDS TO THE COAST. THIS INCLUDES SUNSET DUNES.
OUR NEW PARK CREATED FROM A SECTION OF THE GREAT HIGHWAY
SUNSET DUNES. WHAT WOULD JIMMY CARTER DO?
I BELIEVE HE WOULD HAVE SUPPORTED THE PARK BECAUSE IT
WAS THE COURAGEOUS THING TO DO. THERE WAS A CONTENTIOUS DEBATE
ABOUT THE FUTURE OF THE GREAT HIGHWAY.
I MET WITH ADVOCATES ON BOTH SIDES.
I SUPPORTED DEMOCRACY BY GIVING PEOPLE A CHOICE ABOUT WHAT TO
DO WITH THEIR COAST. I JOINED FOUR OTHER SUPERVISORS
TO PUT PROP K ON THE BALLOT. IT ALLOWED FOR MORE PUBLIC
DEBATE IN THE MOST OPEN DEMOCRATIC AND TRANSPARENT
PROCESS POSSIBLE. EVERY VOTER HAD AN EQUAL SAY
BECAUSE THE COAST BELONGS TO EVERYONE.
THE GREAT HIGHWAY WAS A CLIMATE CHANGE ISSUE.
THE SOUTHERN SECTION OF THE ROAD IS FALLING INTO THE OCEAN
FROM SEVERE COASTAL EROSION. THE CONVENIENT CONNECTION TO
DALY CITY WAS GOING TO CLOSE BY STATE MANDATE NO MATTER WHAT.
CARS HAD TO DIVERT INLAND NO MATTER WHAT.
THIS IS THE LEMON MOTHER NATURE GAVE US.
NOW WE ARE MAKING LEMONADE BY CREATING A NEW COASTAL PARK.
AND THE SKY DID NOT FALL. THE TRAFFIC CARMAGEDDON PEOPLE
FEARED DID NOT HAPPEN. TRAFFIC STUDIES SHOW THAT CARS
ARE GETTING WHERE THEY NEED TO GO WITH A MINIMAL IMPACT.
WE'RE ALSO PUTTING A LOT OF ATTENTION ON TRAFFIC CALMING
IN THE AVENUES TO KEEP PEDESTRIANS SAFE.
THE BENEFITS OF THE PARK FAR OUTWEIGH THE FEARS.
SUNSET DUNES IS GOOD FOR THE ENVIRONMENT, GOOD FOR OUR LOCAL
ECONOMY AND IT'S BRINGING JOY AND HEALTH TO PEOPLE OF ALL
AGES AND ABILITIES. YET THERE IS A LOT OF UGLY
RHETORIC ABOUT THE PARK THAT IS DISAPPOINTING TO HEAR.
PARK ADVOCATES ARE LABELED AS QUOTE DANGEROUS NOT BECAUSE
THEY SUPPORT SOMETHING THAT WILL ATTRACT QUOTE NEW PEOPLE
AND A DIFFERENT TYPE OF PEOPLE WITH A WHOLE DIFFERENT SET OF
VALUES AND VISIONS ON THE WEST SIDE UNQUOTE.
THIS RHETORIC DOES NOT REPRESENT OUR CITY'S VALUES.
>> SAN FRANCISCO HAS ALWAYS BEEN A PLACE FOR NEWCOMERS FROM
THE GOLD RUSH TO THE SUMMER OF LOVE.
EVERY NEW IMMIGRANT ARTIST, LGBTQ PERSON AND INNOVATOR
MAKES OUR CITY BETTER. >> OPPOSITION TO SUNSET DUNES
HAS BECOME SYNONYMOUS WITH OPPOSITION TO NEW HOUSING
AND THE HOUSING PLAN THAT THIS BOARD WILL CONSIDER THE CATCH
PHRASE. DON'T LET OCEAN BEACH BECOME
MIAMI BEACH HAS STOKED FEARS THAT ARE SIMPLY NOT TRUE.
OUR CITY CHARTER FORBIDS DEVELOPMENT IN PARK LAND.
THE STREETS ALONG SUNSET DUNES ARE NOT BEING UP ZONED IN THE
HOUSING PLAN. OUR COAST WILL NOT BECOME MIAMI
BEACH. YET WE NEED TO BUILD MORE
HOUSING IN SAN FRANCISCO AND THE WEST SIDE ESPECIALLY
NEAR PUBLIC TRANSIT. ALL CITIES IN CALIFORNIA NEED
TO DO THIS BECAUSE SUBURBAN SPRAWL IS TERRIBLE FOR THE
ENVIRONMENT AND IT'S TERRIBLE FOR PUBLIC HEALTH.
BUT ABOVE ALL, SUBURBAN SPRAWL IS TERRIBLE BECAUSE IT LIMITS
ACCESS TO ECONOMIC OPPORTUNITY. >> THE REFUSAL TO BUILD ENOUGH
AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN SAN FRANCISCO HAS FORCED MORE
PEOPLE TO THE SUBURBS AND THIS INCLUDES SOME VERY IMPORTANT
PEOPLE. A CITY NEEDS TO FUNCTION.
OUR FIRST RESPONDERS TEACHERS AND ESSENTIAL WORKERS.
WE'RE FORCING THEM TO LIVE FAR AWAY AND COMMUTE BACK INTO THE
CITY. EVEN OUR ADULT KIDS
AND GRANDKIDS HAVE TO MOVE AWAY BUT THEY CAN STAY IN SAN
FRANCISCO. IF WE EMBRACE SOME APARTMENT
BUILDINGS IN EVERY NEIGHBORHOOD I KNOCKED ON THOUSANDS OF DOORS
THE PAST FEW MONTHS AND HAD AN IMPORTANT CONVERSATION WITH
SUNSET RESIDENTS OF EVERY BACKGROUND ONE WOMAN STANDS OUT
IN HOW SHE SUMMED EVERYTHING UP .
>> SUNSET DUNES IS POPULAR AND THE TRAFFIC IS FINE, SHE
SAID. WHY ARE WE ARGUING ABOUT A PARK
AND A ROAD WHEN THE WORLD IS ON FIRE?
WE NEED TO FOCUS ON MORE IMPORTANT THINGS LIKE SAVING
OUR DEMOCRACY, SHE SAID. >> I AGREE OUR IMMIGRANT
COMMUNITY IS UNDER ATTACK. LGBTQ PEOPLE ARE BEING
TARGETED. SCIENCE BASED INSTITUTIONS ARE
BEING DISMANTLED OLD. A GENERATION HAS GROWN UP IN A
CULTURE OF MASS SHOOTINGS. WE HAVE A MENTAL HEALTH CRISIS.
THE COST OF HOUSING AND HEALTH CARE MAKES IT IMPOSSIBLE FOR
MANY TO SURVIVE AS CITY SUPERVISORS.
>> WE DON'T HAVE THE POWERS OF GOVERNORS AND SENATORS BUT
THERE IS A LOT WE CAN DO LOCALLY TO FIGHT WHAT'S ON FIRE
IN THE WORLD. >> OUR SANCTUARY CITY POLICY
MATTERS OUR HOUSING HOUSING AND ZONING POLICIES MATTER HOW
WE RUN OUR DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH MATTERS.
AND WHEN IT COMES TO THE LITERAL FIRES ALL OVER
CALIFORNIA, IT MATTERS HOW WE APPROACH THE EXISTENTIAL THREAT
OF CLIMATE CHANGE. THIS IS ABOUT OUR FUTURE.
>> IF WE WANT TO KEEP OUR FAMILIES AND WORKERS HERE THEN
WE HAVE TO BE GOOD STEWARDS OF THE ENVIRONMENT.
WE WILL HAVE TO ACCEPT SOME TALLER APARTMENT BUILDINGS NEAR
PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION AND WE WILL HAVE TO ACCEPT CREATING
SOME SAFE SPACES FOR WALKERS AND CYCLISTS.
THAT'S NOT ASKING A LOT. NO ONE IS BANNING SINGLE FAMILY
HOMES. WE'RE ONLY TALKING ABOUT SOME
SIX STORY APARTMENT BUILDINGS. NO ONE IS BANNING CARS.
FAR FROM IT. WE'RE ONLY TALKING ABOUT SOME
CARS TAKING A SLIGHTLY DIFFERENT ROUTE.
>> HOW ARE WE EVER GOING TO COME TOGETHER AND ADDRESS OUR
BIGGEST ISSUES LIKE CLIMATE CHANGE?
IF WE CANNOT BUILD IN APARTMENT BUILDING OR CHANGE OUR DRIVING
HABITS WITHOUT IT BECOMING AN UGLY BATTLE OVER WHO DESERVES
TO LIVE IN A NEIGHBORHOOD AND DEFINE ITS CHARACTER.
THIS RAISES SOME IMPORTANT QUESTIONS ABOUT THE FUTURE OF
SAN FRANCISCO. DO WE WANT TO BE A CITY THAT
ONLY LOOKS TO PRESERVE THE PAST?
>> OR DO WE WANT TO BE A FORWARD LOOKING AND INNOVATIVE
CITY THAT KEEPS OUR FAMILIES AND WORKERS HERE WHILE
WELCOMING NEW PEOPLE, IMMIGRANTS AND IDEAS?
>> SAN FRANCISCO WILL ONLY REALIZE ITS FULL POTENTIAL IF
WE LET OURSELVES DO BOLD THINGS .
WE CANNOT BE THE MOST PROGRESSIVE CITY THAT FEARS
CHANGE. WE MUST BE THE MOST PROGRESSIVE
CITY THAT EMBRACES THE FUTURE. >> IF WE NEVER CHANGED ANYTHING
IN SAN FRANCISCO THE SUNSET WOULD STILL BE SAND DUNES
AND WE WOULD NOT HAVE RESIDENTS LIKE DOROTHY LAYTON.
DOROTHY WAS ONE OF THE FIRST BLACK RESIDENTS ALLOWED TO BUY
A HOME IN THE SUNSET A FEW YEARS AFTER BASEBALL STAR
WILLIE MAYS WAS DENIED ON THE WEST SIDE.
DOROTHY HAS LIVED ACROSS FROM THE GREAT HIGHWAY FOR MORE THAN
SIX DECADES. >> SHE CONTRIBUTED TO OUR CITY
AS AN EDUCATOR AND COMMUNITY LEADER.
DOROTHY'S PRESENCE IS THE BENEFIT OF CHANGE AND SHE
EMBRACES CHANGE. SHE LOVES SUNSET DUNES.
>> MY FAVORITE IMAGE OF DOROTHY IS SEEING HER AT A SUNSET NIGHT
MARKET CANE IN ONE HAND AND A MARGUERITA IN THE OTHER BOP
INTO THE MUSIC AT 93. SHE IS THE ANTITHESIS OF THE
ANGRY OLD MAN WHO YELLS AT CLOUDS.
DOROTHY IS MORE FUN TO BE AROUND.
LET'S BE LIKE DOROTHY AND CREATE OUR BEST SAN
FRANCISCO. >> OUR CITY IS DEFINED BY
MOVEMENTS AND LANDMARKS THAT REQUIRE DIFFICULT
AND COURAGEOUS CHOICES. THE GOLDEN GATE BRIDGE WAS
BUILT IN SPITE OF ITS MANY DETRACTORS.
IT WAS CALLED AN UPSIDE DOWN RAT TRAP AND NOW IT'S THE ICON
OF OUR CITY. THIS IS THE STORY OF SUNSET
DUNES A TRANSFORMATIONAL SPACE THAT CONNECTS PEOPLE TO
SOMETHING BIGGER THAN THEMSELVES.
THE POWER OF THE OCEAN. THE BEAUTY OF THE SUNSET.
WHERE CHILDREN CAN LEARN TO RIDE A BIKE AND DREAM.
WHERE A SENIOR CAN ROLL IN A WHEELCHAIR AND REMEMBER A SPACE
FOR EVERY FACET OF LIFE. TO CELEBRATE FATE, MOURN, HEAL
AND REFLECT BEFORE LONG. WE WILL WONDER WHY THERE WAS A
CONTROVERSY AT ALL AND WE WON'T BE ABLE TO IMAGINE SAN
FRANCISCO WITHOUT A COASTAL PARK AND THE BENEFITS IT
OFFERS. LIKE THE WOMAN I MET AT THE
DOOR SAID SUNSET DUNES IS POPULAR IN THE TRAFFIC IS FINE.
WHY ARE WE ARGUING ABOUT A PARK AND A ROAD WHEN THE WORLD IS ON
FIRE? >> WE NEED TO FOCUS ON MORE
IMPORTANT THINGS LIKE SAVING OUR DEMOCRACY.
I AM CERTAIN JIMMY CARTER WOULD HAVE SAID AMEN TO THAT AND THE
REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR
AND ENGARDIO SUPERVISOR FIELDER .
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE TWO
INTRODUCTIONS. THE FIRST I'M INTRODUCING A
RESOLUTION AFFIRMING THE HISTORICAL LEGACY AND FUTURE OF
THE MICHIGAN CULTURAL CENTER FOR LATINO ARTS A PARTICULARLY
FITTING ACTION TO TAKE DURING LATINO HERITAGE MONTH.
THIS RESOLUTION NOT ONLY AFFIRMS THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS RECOGNITION OF THE HISTORICAL LEGACY OF THE
MISSION CULTURAL CENTER FOR LATINO ARTS IT ALSO LIPS THE
IMPORTANCE OF ITS FUTURE THROUGHOUT AND AFTER THE
PENDING RETROFIT OF THE BUILDING AT 2868 MISSION
STREET. >> THE RESOLUTION ULTIMATELY
URGES THE S.F. ARTS COMMISSION TO PROVIDE CECILIA THE RIGHT TO
RETURN UPON THE COMPLETION OF CONSTRUCTION AS MANY OF YOU
KNOW, CECILIA HAS BEEN A BELOVED SAN FRANCISCO
INSTITUTION SINCE 1977 CELEBRATING AND REPRESENTING
THE VITAL CONTRIBUTIONS OF THE LATINO COMMUNITY TO CULTURE,
ART, MUSIC, DANCE, POETRY, PRINTMAKING, GRAPHIC ARTS,
MURAL ARTS, THEATER AND SO MUCH MORE.
IT HAS BEEN CENTRAL TO DISTRICT NINE COMMUNITY AND HAS BEEN AT
THE CUTTING EDGE OF ARTISTIC EXPRESSION IN SAN FRANCISCO
SINCE ITS INCEPTION. IT IS THE PLACE WHERE SOME OF
SAN FRANCISCO'S MOST ICONIC AND WORLD RENOWNED ANNUAL
CELEBRATIONS HAVE TAKEN PLACE FOR DECADES, INCLUDING THE
LATINO HERITAGE COMMUNITY'S CELEBRATION OF THE LOS MUERTOS
AND POWERFUL ALTAR EXHIBIT IN THE FALL.
SOLOMON HARRIS AND OF COURSE CARNIVAL IN THE SPRING.
WITH THIS RESOLUTION WE RECOGNIZE AND CELEBRATE M.C.
CELIA AND COMMIT TO THE ORGANIZATION OUR INTENT TO
CONTINUE SUPPORTING THEIR FUTURE AND RIGHT TO RESIDE AT
2868 MISSION STREET. >> I WANT TO THANK DIRECTOR
MARTINA AYALA AND CECILIA BOARD FOR THEIR WORK MY EARLY CO
SPONSORS SUPERVISORS MELGAR WALTON, CHEN CHAN AND MAHMOOD.
>> AND I HOPE THAT ALL OF YOU WILL SIGN ON TO SHOW OUR FULL
SUPPORT AND APPRECIATION FOR THE LEGACY AND FUTURE OF THE
MISSION CULTURAL CENTER. >> SECONDLY, I AM INTRODUCING A
RESOLUTION TO FIRMLY SUPPORT UDC 89119 CLINICAL SOCIAL
WORKERS RECOGNIZING THEIR INVALUABLE CONTRIBUTIONS
IN LEADING HARM REDUCTION AND DIVERSION EFFORTS IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND URGING UCSF TO END THE TWO TIERED SYSTEM
WITHIN THEIR MENTAL HEALTH WORKFORCE.
>> CLINICAL SOCIAL WORKERS AND CLINICIANS PROVIDE CRITICAL
SERVICES TO ALL BAY AREA RESIDENTS FROM THOSE WHO ARE
WELL INSURED TO THOSE WHO ARE UNINSURED OR UNDERINSURED.
UCSF HAS A TWO TIER SYSTEM THAT CLASSIFIES WORKERS IN EQUITABLY
AND MAKES IT SUCH THAT CLINICAL SOCIAL WORKERS WORKING ON
CAMPUS CLINICS GET PAID DIFFERENTLY THAN THEIR
COUNTERPARTS WORKING IN THE STREETS.
>> CANNABIS CLINICAL SOCIAL WORKERS OFTEN SERVE OUR CITY'S
MOST VULNERABLE POPULATIONS PEOPLE LIVING WITH SERIOUS
MENTAL ILLNESS, SURVIVORS OF SEVERE TRAUMA, PEOPLE
STRUGGLING WITH SUBSTANCE USE DISORDERS AND FAR TOO MANY WHO
ARE ALSO NAVIGATING DISPLACEMENT, HOUSING
INSECURITY OR HOMELESSNESS. >> DESPITE THIS BECAUSE OF
THEIR WORKER CLASSIFICATION UNDER THE TWO TIERED SYSTEM
CAMPUS CLINICAL SOCIAL WORKERS MAKE ON AVERAGE 31% LESS THAN
THEIR COUNTERPARTS AT MEDICAL CENTERS.
>> THESE ARE HIGHLY TRAINED PROFESSIONALS WITH THE SAME
ADVANCED DEGREES AND LICENSES AS THEIR MEDICAL CENTER
COUNTERPARTS. BUT FACED WITH PAY INEQUITY
THAT BLOCKS THEM FROM EQUITABLE CAREER PROGRESSION
AND ADVANCEMENT, UCSF IS EFFECTIVELY ASKING THOSE ON THE
FRONT LINES OF OUR CITY'S MENTAL HEALTH CRISIS TO NOT
JUST DO MORE WORK BUT MORE DANGEROUS, MORE COMPLEX WORK
FOR SIGNIFICANTLY LESS PAY. >> SO TODAY I CALL UPON UCSF
WITH THIS RESOLUTION TO RECLASSIFY THESE WORKERS
IN LINE WITH THEIR QUALIFICATIONS LINES TO ADOPT
UNIFORM HIRING AND CLASSIFICATION STANDARDS
AND TO ENSURE THAT PAY EQUITY IS ACHIEVED ACROSS THESE
CLINICAL SOCIAL WORK POSITIONS. >> I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISORS
WALTON CHAN, MELGAR MAHMOOD AND DORSEY FOR YOUR EARLY
CO-SPONSORSHIP AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD SUBMIT THANK YOU
AND SUPERVISOR GENTLEMAN. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
I WILL SUBMIT MY LEGISLATION BUT I AM ASKING THAT WE CLOSE
IN MEMORY OF RAVEN SKEETER SORRELL.
HE DIED ON AUGUST 11TH, 2025 AT THE AGE OF 31.
RAVEN WAS BORN IN NEWPORT BEACH, NICOLE SEWELL AND WAS
RAISED IN REDDING WITH HIS THREE BROTHERS AND THREE
SISTERS. >> DIAGNOSED WITH AUTISM AT THE
AGE OF FIVE, RAVEN ENDURED A TRAUMATIC CHILDHOOD AND FELL
INTO HOMELESSNESS AT JUST 16 YEARS OLD AT AGE 20.
HE MOVED TO SAN FRANCISCO WHERE HE QUICKLY FELL IN LOVE WITH
THE CASTRO AND BECAME A WELL-LIKED MEMBER OF THE STREET
COMMUNITY. THOSE WHO KNEW HIM REMEMBER A
SOFT SPOKEN PERSON WITH A BIG HEART OFTEN FOUND ON CASTRO
BETWEEN 17TH AND 18TH. HE LOOKED OUT FOR NEW ARRIVALS
TO THE CITY MAKING SURE THEY HAD FOOD AND SUPPLIES TO GET
BY. >> HE WAS ALSO AN ARTIST WHO
CREATED HIS ARTWORKS FROM SCRAPS OF WOOD, METAL PAINT
AND A BUTANE TORCH OFTEN PURCHASED FROM CLIFF'S VARIETY.
BUT RAVEN'S LIFE REFLECTS A FAR TOO FAMILIAR PATTERN ON SAN
FRANCISCO'S STREETS. >> OVER THE YEARS HE ENTERED
COURT, ORDERED RESIDENTIAL DRUG TREATMENT SEVERAL TIMES BUT
NEVER COMPLETED A PROGRAM. HE WAS PERMANENTLY HOUSED AT
ONE POINT BUT LOST HIS UNIT AFTER AN ARSON INCIDENT.
HE CYCLED THROUGH ARRESTS, SHORT STAYS IN JAIL, BRIEF
PERIODS OF SOBRIETY AND INEVITABLY FOUND HIMSELF
BACK ON THE STREETS. THIS EXPENSIVE RINSE AND REPEAT
CYCLE NEVER DELIVERED THE SUSTAINED CARE THAT RAVEN
NEEDED. AFTER HIS MOST RECENT RELEASE
FROM JAIL, HE RELAPSED INTO FENTANYL USE AND NEVER
RECOVERED. HE DIED IN A TINY CABIN NEAR
16TH AND MISSION. RAVEN STORY IS A PERSONAL
TRAGEDY BUT IT IS ALSO EMBLEMATIC OF A BROADER TRAGIC
POLICY FAILURE. HE WAS CREATIVE AND KIND
AND VERY YOUNG AND VERY BROKEN. HE DID HAVE A COMMUNITY THAT
LOVED HIM BUT SAN FRANCISCO AND CALIFORNIA FAILED HIM AS WE
HAVE FAILED SO MANY THOUSANDS LIKE HIM.
A MEMORIAL FOR RAVEN WILL BE HELD ON OCTOBER 12TH FROM 1 TO
2 P.M. AT MOST HOLY REDEEMER CHURCH IN THE CASTRO.
WE SEND OUR CONDOLENCES TO RAVEN'S FAMILY AND COMMUNITY.
REST IN PEACE, RAVENS TERRELL. MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A BLESSING.
THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
AND SEEING NO OTHER NAMES ON THE ROSTER THAT CONCLUDES THE
INTRODUCTION OF NEW BUSINESS. MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO PUBLIC
COMMENT. >> AT THIS TIME THE BOARD
WELCOMES YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT AND IF YOU LINE UP YOUR RIGHT
HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER YOU'LL BE ABLE TO SPEAK TO GENERAL
MATTERS THAT ARE NOT ON THE PUBLISHED AGENDA BUT ARE WITHIN
THE BOARD SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION.
ADDITIONALLY ITEMS 35 THROUGH 39 THESE ARE THE ITEMS THAT DID
NOT GO TO COMMITTEE THAT ARE ON THE ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE CALENDAR. >> ALL RIGHT, LET'S HEAR FROM
OUR FIRST SPEAKER. WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR
TWO MINUTES. KEEP AN EYE ON THE CLOCK THAT
IS ON THE ROSTER. >> WELL YEAH, WE SAID LUNCH ANY
TIME. OKAY SO YOU ARE PEDOPHILE
ZONES. >> THAT'S ABSOLUTELY CLEAR AT
LEAST WORKING FOR PEDOPHILES WHICH COMES THROUGH THE SAME.
>> SO YOU ARE IN TROUBLE. WE'RE GOING TO REOPEN THE GREAT
OUR WAY. >> BY THE WAY, I ABSOLUTELY NO
WAY ARE YOU TALKING IT WAS ENTIRELY RIGGED.
NO ONE VOTED FOR CLOSETS. YOU KNOW IT DON'T PUT ON YOU'RE
IN TROUBLE. >> I WILL LEAVE SAN FRANCISCO
IF I WERE YOU BECAUSE THE WAR AGAINST THE PEDOPHILES IS NOT
SOON TO END. >> WE'RE GOING TO FIGHT WITH
EVERYONE HERE AGAINST THESE UGLY HUMAN BEINGS.
>> THAT'S RIGHT. TO CONTROL ALL OF US.
SO NO MATTER HOW OLD YOU TRY, IT'S NOT GOING TO WORK.
>> BY THE WAY, LATINOS DON'T LIKE PEDOPHILES, HUH?
>> SO IT'S AREA THE BLACK COMMUNITY THOUGH.
DON'T WORRY. I SPEAK TO ALL OF THEM.
THE SHERIFF IS JUST WAITING HERE TO KEEP THEM NFL NOW BUT
GET READY. OKAY.
SO YOU ARE IN TROUBLE. I DON'T KNOW WHAT YOU CAN DO,
GUYS. >> OKAY?
IT'S ALL ABOUT SELF CONTROL. >> YOU UNDERSTAND?
EXISTENCE IS ABOUT PAIN AND PLEASURE WHICH IS WHY YOU
NEED TO HAVE SELF-CONTROL TO GO NEITHER TOO FAR ON THIS SIDE IF
YOU GO FOR TOO MUCH PLEASURE SEX CRAZINESS LIKE WITH KIDS
YOU'RE GOING TO HAVE AN EXTRA AMP AND IT'S COMING YOU SEE?
>> ARE YOU GUYS READY TO WAKE UP?
OH, PEDOPHILES HERE YOU HAVE DONE THERE IS NOTHING YOU CAN
DO AGAINST WHAT'S COMING TO YOU NO MATTER HOW HARD YOU TRY.
WE HAVE FAKE ASSASSINATE SESSIONS WITH THE GUY NOT EVEN
OPENING HIS EYES AFTER BEING SHOT BY BULLET BUT ACTING TOO
BAD FOR YOU. YOUR COMMENTS ARE ACKNOWLEDGED
BUT NOT ENDORSED. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD.
MY NAME IS DR. MARTINA AYALA, EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE
MISSION CULTURAL CENTER FOR LATINO ARTS.
THANK YOU FOR BRINGING FORWARD A RESOLUTION THAT RECOGNIZES
M.C. CLAY'S HISTORIC LEGACY AND AFFIRMS OUR FUTURE.
BEFORE, DURING AND AFTER THE SEISMIC RETROFIT AT 2868
MISSION STREET. FOR 49 YEARS M.C. CLAY HAS BEEN
A CITY LANDMARK IN PRACTICE AND IN LAW HOME TO A THEATER
GALLERY EXHIBITIONS, DANCE MUSIC STUDIOS, PODCASTS, LAB
MISSION GRAPHIC PRINTMAKING AND AN ARCHIVE THAT PRESERVES
OUR CULTURAL MEMORY. >> WE FULLY SUPPORT THE
RETROFIT SAFETY MATTERS. SO DOES CONTINUITY DURING
CONSTRUCTION WE MUST RELOCATE PROGRAMS, EQUIPMENT ARCHIVES
SUPPORT OVER 30 TEACHING ARTISTS AND STAFF AND KEEP
COMMUNITY ACCESS ALIVE. THAT'S DIFFICULT IN AN
UNDERFUNDED ARTS ECOSYSTEM STILL RECOVERING FROM THE
PANDEMIC. THIS RESOLUTION IS ESSENTIAL
BECAUSE IT PAIRS HISTORY WITH A PATH FORWARD.
>> M.C. CLAY IS NOT MERELY A BUILDING IT IS A PUBLIC GOOD A
PLACE WHERE NEWCOMERS AND LONG TIME RESIDENTS MEET, WHERE
CULTURE HEALS, TEACHES AND INSPIRES BELONGING.
DURING LATINO HERITAGE MONTH THIS BOARD CAN AFFIRM THAT SAN
FRANCISCO HONORS ITS PAST AND INVEST IN ITS FUTURE.
>> ON BEHALF OF OUR ARTISTS, STUDENTS AND FAMILIES, I URGE
YOU TO ADOPT THE RESOLUTION AND SUPPORT THE PRACTICAL
PROCESS. >> ALIGN STEPS HELP US CARRY
THE CULTURAL HOME SAFELY THROUGH THE RETROFIT AND BACK
HOME TO MISSION STREET WHEN THE WORK IS DONE.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP AND STANDING WITH M.C. CLAY.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS AND SPEAKER WELCOME.
GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD.
>> MY NAME IS JACQUELINE RODRIGUES AND I SERVE ON THE
BOARD OF DIRECTORS OF THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER FOR
LATINO ARTS. I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR
RECOGNIZING CECILIA'S HISTORIC LEGACY AND AFFIRMING ITS FUTURE
DURING THE SEISMIC RETROFIT AT 2868 MISSION STREET.
FOR 49 YEARS CECILIA HAS BEEN A LIVING CLASSROOM IN A CULTURAL
HOME OF THEATER GALLERY DANCE MUSIC STUDIO PODCAST LAB
MISSION GRAPHIC PRINT STUDIO AND ARCHIVES.
AND THE ARCHIVE SERVES THOUSANDS OF RESIDENTS EVERY
YEAR. >> WE WELCOME THE RETROFIT
BECAUSE SAFETY IS ESSENTIAL. JUST AS ESSENTIAL IS CONTINUITY
KEEPING ARTS EDUCATION EXHIBITIONS AND INTEGRATE
IN TWO GENERATIONAL GATHERINGS ACCESSIBLE TO FAMILIES WHILE
THE WORK PROCEEDS AND LONGEVITY ENSURING THAT THIS LANDMARK
INSTITUTION REMAINS ROOTED IN THE MISSION FOR DECADES TO
COME. TODAY'S RESOLUTION ACKNOWLEDGES
THAT TRUTH. >> IT HONORS A PAST BUILT
IN COMMUNITY AND LOOKS AHEAD TO A FUTURE WHERE CECILIA CECILIA
RETURNS TO MISSION STREET SUSTAINED BY ONGOING
PARTNERSHIPS AND INVESTMENT ON BEHALF OF OUR ARTISTS, STUDENTS
AND NEIGHBORHOODS. >> THANK YOU FOR STANDING WITH
CECILIA AND THE COMMITTEE IT SERVES.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> >> GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD.
>> MY NAME IS STACY GUTIERREZ, A MISSION DISTRICT RESIDENT
AND LONG TERM PARTICIPANT AT THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER FOR
LATINO ARTS. MY FAMILY GREW UP AT MCLEAN
MUSIC LESSONS FOR KIDS EXHIBITIONS FOR OUR PARENTS
AND COMMUNITY EVENTS THAT MAKE US FEEL AT HOME.
MICHELLE HAS BEEN PART OF SAN FRANCISCO'S FABRIC SINCE 1977
BECAUSE IT OFFERS SOMETHING IRREPLACEABLE A PLACE WHERE
CULTURE IS LEARNED, PRACTICED AND PASSED ON.
>> THE PLANNED RETROFIT AT 22868 MISSION STREET IS
IMPORTANT FOR SAFETY AND SO IS PROTECTING MICHELLE'S PLACE
IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD. KEEPING THIS INSTITUTION IN THE
MISSION TO SUSTAIN SMALL BUSINESSES ACTIVATES OUR
STREETS WITH POSITIVE ACTIVITY AND GIVES YOUNG PEOPLE A
CREATIVE PATH FORWARD LIKE MYSELF AS THE CITY INVESTS
IN REPAIRS. >> WE ALSO CELEBRATE THE LONG
TERM INVESTMENT. >> MCCLARY REPRESENTS DECADES
OF CLASSES, PERFORMANCES, ARCHIVES AND THE RENOWNED
MISSION GRAPHICS THAT CARRIES OUR HISTORY INTO THE FUTURE.
SUPPORTING UCLA THROUGH THIS TRANSITION AND WELCOMING,
WELCOMING AND HOME AFTER CONSTRUCTION IS AN INVESTMENT
IN SAN FRANCISCO'S IDENTITY AND IN THE WELL-BEING OF
FAMILIES LIKE MINE. THANK YOU FOR RECOGNIZING
MICHELLE'S LEGACY AND FOR AFFIRMING ITS FUTURE IN THE
COMMUNITY THAT IT HAS SERVED FOR NEARLY HALF A CENTURY.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME. OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HI EVERYONE. MY NAME IS JULIE.
I GUESS I'M THE FOUNDER OF SAN FRANCISCO GOOD NEIGHBOR WEEK.
I WANT TO THANK YOU ALL FOR YOUR SUPPORT OF DECLARING SAN
FRANCISCO GOOD NEIGHBOR WEEK TODAY AS SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MENTIONED, WE'RE ALSO KICKING OFF SOCIAL CONNECTION WEEK.
I'VE BEEN IN TOUCH WITH THOSE ORGANIZERS AND REST ASSURED
THAT IN 2026 SOCIAL CONNECTION WEEK AND GOOD NEIGHBOR WEEK
WILL FALL ON THE SAME TIME SO YOU WON'T HAVE TO DECLARE THEM
SEPARATELY. I WANTED TO ACKNOWLEDGE SOME OF
THE EVENTS THAT ARE HAPPENING ACROSS THE CITY AND ALL 11
DISTRICTS RIGHT AFTER THIS I'M HOPPING TO THE START A CLUB
BUILDS UPON AT THE NOOK A COUPLE OF BLOCKS AWAY.
THEN THERE'S A DISCUSSION ON SENIOR HOMELESSNESS AFTER A
MOVIE SCREENING AT THE ROXY. TOMORROW IS THE COUNTRY'S FIRST
GOOD NEIGHBOR HACKATHON THAT I'M ORGANIZING AT UCSF WITH A
LOT OF SPECIAL GUESTS. >> I ENCOURAGE YOU TO COME
FRIDAY. THERE'S A COMMUNITY GATHERING
AT BALBOA HOLLOW SATURDAY THERE'S A CLEANUP EVENT WITH
THE CIVIC JOY FUND AND SUNDAY WE'RE CLEARING WEEDS AT
LAKESIDE LANDING. THANK YOU SO MUCH TO ALL OF YOU
FOR SUPPORTING GOOD NEIGHBOR WEEK.
I ALSO WANT TO SHARE THAT WE STARTED REACHING OUT TO THE
OVER 100 GOOD NEIGHBOR AWARD WINNERS FROM OVER 200
NOMINATIONS THIS YEAR ACROSS THE CITY.
>> HERE'S AN EXAMPLE OF ONE. SHELLY HAS BEEN THE PRIMARY
SUPPORT PERSON KEEPING THE RINCON HILL DOG PARK OPEN,
CLEAN, SOCIAL AND SAFE FOR THE USE OF ALL SOUTH BEACH RINCON
NEIGHBORS WITH DOGS. THIS ALONE QUALIFIES HER AS A
GREAT NEIGHBOR BUT SHE ALSO HAS BEEN A SAFETY NET AND MENTOR
FOR LOCAL UNHOUSED ARTIST WHO DISPLAYS AND PAINTS UNDER THE
FREEWAY ON SECOND STREET. >> I HAVE 200 OF THESE
NOMINATIONS AND I'M LOOKING FORWARD TO WORKING WITH ALL OF
YOU TO ACKNOWLEDGE THEM WITH CERTIFICATES OF HONOR.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. FIRST I'LL GIVE YOU SOMETHING
THEN I'LL ASK FOR SOMETHING. >> DISTRICT FOR THE REST OF THE
BOARD CITY COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO WHATEVER YOU CAN
DREAM UP AS FAR AS WHAT YOU LIKE THIS CITY TO BE TAKE A
LOOK AT SOMETHING CALLED THE CHICAGO PLAN.
CHICAGO HAD A PROBLEM. THEY DECIDED INSTEAD OF ALL THE
PUSH BACK THAT THEY WOULD USE THE EIGHTH GRADE AS A AS A
POINT EVERY EIGHTH GRADER LEARN THE CHICAGO PLAN AFTER A WHILE
THERE WAS NO RESISTANCE. OKAY, THIS IS MY THIRD VISIT I
BELIEVE OVER THE LAST NINE MONTHS, ALMOST TEN MONTHS HAD A
PROBLEM WITH THE LIBRARY AT THREE VISITS TO THE LIBRARY
COMMISSION, NOTHING TO COMMISSIONERS, NOTHING.
>> THE THIRD COMMISSIONER IN AUGUST I MADE CONTACT WITH
THEM GAVE HIM EMAIL. HE SAID HE HAD TO CHECK TO FIND
OUT IF HE COULD TALK TO ME OR NOT.
>> I THOUGHT THAT WAS STRANGE. >> THIS MONTH I RETURNED TO THE
MEETING AND AT ADJOURNMENT THE ENTIRE AREA WHERE ALL THE
COMMISSIONERS WERE SITTING ON STAGE JUST ORCHESTRATED
THEMSELVES TO USHER THE COMMISSIONER OUT THE BACK DOOR
. >> I COULDN'T SHARE WITH HIM MY
POLICY VIEWS ABOUT ALL OF THE THINGS THAT I'VE BEEN GOING
THROUGH. >> COULDN'T SHARE ANYTHING.
STREAMLINING TASK FORCE WILL BE ADDRESSING THE LIBRARY
COMMISSION TOMORROW I'LL BE SENDING YOU SOME THINGS THIS
EVENING SO YOU WILL SEE WHAT I'VE BEEN TALKING ABOUT.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE.
MY NAME IS APRIL MCGILL. I'M THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF
THE AMERICAN INDIAN CULTURE CENTER AND CO-FOUNDER OF THE
AMERICAN INDIAN CULTURAL DISTRICT.
FOR OVER 20 YEARS THE AMERICAN INDIAN CULTURAL CENTER HAS
SUCCESSFULLY LED THE NATIVE HERITAGE CELEBRATION HERE AT
CITY HALL. THIS EVENT IS IN COLLABORATION
WITH OUR TRUSTED NATIVE PARTNERS PARTNERING
ORGANIZATION. THIS HAS ALWAYS BEEN AN EVENT
LED FOR LED FOR US BY US WITH THE FULL SUPPORT
AND RECOGNITION OF EVERY PREVIOUS MAYOR MAYOR'S OFFICE
TO BE INFORMED RECENTLY WITHOUT ANY PRIOR CONSULTATION AND THAT
THE MAYOR HAS DECIDED TO PICK A NEW PARTNER AND THAT A PLANNING
MEETING IS ALREADY SCHEDULED FOR OUR HERITAGE EVENT WITHOUT
ENGAGING HCC OR PARTNERS IS NOT ONLY DISRESPECTFUL BUT IT
DISREGARDS OUR LONGSTANDING LEADERSHIP CONTRIBUTIONS
AND EXPERTISE IN ORGANIZING THIS CULTURALLY SIGNIFICANT
EVENT. WE ARE NOT A ONE SIZE FITS ALL
COMMUNITY OR CITY. WE ALSO REACHED OUT ABOUT
SUPPORTING INDIGENOUS PEOPLES DAY NEXT WEEK AND IT'S BEEN
CRICKETS. OUR NATIVE AMERICAN SUPERVISORS
SHOULD NOT BE THE ONLY VOICE FOR US.
IF YOU'RE IF YOU SUPERVISORS DON'T SEE THIS AS A FORM OF
ERASURE OR ACT OF VIOLENCE AGAINST HCC AND THE AMERICAN
INDIAN COMMUNITY, YOU DO NOT SUPPORT THE AMERICAN INDIAN
COMMUNITY. I WANT TO ALSO SAY THAT WE ARE
IN FAVOR OF ADOPTING THE RESOLUTION FOR THE MISSION
CULTURAL CENTER. THEY'VE BEEN SO GREAT TO ALLOW
US TO USE THEIR SPACE BECAUSE WE ARE THE ONLY CULTURAL GROUP
THAT DOES NOT HAVE THEIR OWN CULTURAL CENTER HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO WHICH IS REALLY EMBARRASSING FOR THIS CITY.
I ALSO WANT TO REMIND FOLKS THAT THE GOLD RUSH BROUGHT
DISEASE RAPE, GENOCIDE AND ENSLAVEMENT TO CALIFORNIA
INDIAN PEOPLE. >> SO PLEASE DO NOT HIGHLIGHT
THE GOLD RUSH. >> IT'S VERY DISRESPECTFUL
AND YEAH, SO SAN FRANCISCO WON'T HAVE A A CELEBRATION FOR
INDIGENOUS PEOPLES DAY NEXT WEEK SO MAYBE YOU ALL SHOULD
JUST STOP SAYING THE YOU KNOW ACKNOWLEDGING THIS LAND
AND DOING THIS LAND ACKNOWLEDGMENT BECAUSE IT'S
USELESS. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> CAN WE HEAR FROM THE NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE?
>> WHAT? GOOD EVENING.
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. >> MY NAME IS HONESTLY AND I'M
THE PROGRAM MANAGER OF THE AMERICAN INDIAN CULTURAL CENTER
. >> CAN YOU SPEAK DIRECTLY INTO
THAT, MIKE? THANK YOU SO MUCH.
>> LIKE MY EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR ABEL SAID, ICC HAS LED THE
CITY'S AMERICAN INDIAN HERITAGE MONTH CELEBRATION RIGHT HERE
IN THIS BUILDING FOR OVER 20 YEARS IN PARTNERSHIP WITH
NATIVE ORGANIZATIONS AS AND WITH THE SUPPORT OF PAST
MAYORS. >> I WANT TO ECHO THAT MOVING
FORWARD WITHOUT OUR INVOLVEMENT UNDERMINES THE NATIVE
LEADERSHIP HERE IN THE CITY AND DISREGARDS THE COMMUNITY.
THIS EVENT IS MEANT TO HONOR. >> THESE DECISIONS AFFECT OUR
VISIBILITY AUTONOMY AND ABILITY TO SHARE OUR CULTURE ON OUR OWN
TERMS. IT IS VITAL THAT THE
CELEBRATION REMAIN LED BY NATIVE VOICES TO ENSURE IT
REFLECTS OUR SOVEREIGNTY, OUR RESILIENCE AND THE LIVED
EXPERIENCES OF THE NATIVE PEOPLE HERE IN THE CITY.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER .
>> I'M MOHAMMAD DUQUETTE ON THURSDAY AND THE PITCHES ARE
PITCH THOUGH HELLO MY RELATIVES A GREAT SHOW WITH A GOOD HEART
. MY NAME IS ELSIE DEBRAY AND I
AM HERE FIRST AS AN OR LAKOTA MANDAN AND HIDATSA WOMAN A
CHEYENNE RIVER SIOUX TRIBAL MEMBER AND A RESIDENT OF SAN
FRANCISCO AND SECOND AS THE COMMUNITY RESEARCH ASSOCIATE
FOR THE AMERICAN INDIAN CULTURAL CENTER.
>> ICC WORKS TIRELESSLY TO ENSURE THE VISIBILITY
AND CELEBRATION OF OUR NATIVE COMMUNITY HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO
AND I'M HERE TODAY TO ECHO THE SENTIMENTS OF MY COWORKERS
AND ARE CONCERNED THAT THERE HAS BEEN AN UNDERMINING OF THIS
LEADERSHIP AND ADVOCACY OF OUR COMMUNITY AND ORGANIZATION
IN THE ONCE VERY COLLABORATIVE PLANNING OF OUR NATIVE AMERICAN
HERITAGE NIGHT AND INDIGENOUS PEOPLES DAY EVENTS.
>> IT IS MY HOPE THAT THE SUPERVISORS GROUP AS A WHOLE
IN THIS BUILDING AND NOT JUST OUR ANTI COUSIN FIELDER WILL
ENSURE THAT WE ADDRESS THESE CONCERNS IN A GOOD WAY AND MOVE
FORWARD IN A WAY THAT HONORS OUR BEAUTIFUL COMMUNITY AND OUR
ONGOING AND UNWAVERING PRESENCE IN THIS CITY.
PALOMA, ARE YOU THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> HOW'S IT GOING GUYS?
MY NAME'S T.J. HOSEY AND I THINK IT'S TIME WE CALLED THE
MAYOR OF SAN FRANCISCO FOR WHAT'S REALLY HAPPENING WHILE
HE'S BUSY TRYING TO STRIP AWAY NATIVE AMERICAN HERITAGE AND HE
STILL HASN'T TAKEN THE TIME TO MEET WITH US TO LISTEN TO US OR
EVEN STAND WITH US OR ON ANY OF OUR FUTURE EVENTS NOT EVEN ON
INDIGENOUS PEOPLES DAY WHICH WAS RECOGNIZED.
IT'S BEEN I DON'T KNOW HOW LONG BUT ANYWAYS THAT SILENCE SAYS A
LOT OUR PEOPLE, OUR CULTURE AND OUR TRADITIONS THAT WE'VE
CARRIED THE CITY'S HISTORY STRAIGHT ON OUR BACKS LONG
BEFORE HE WAS EVEN CALLED SAN FRANCISCO.
YET OUR VOICES KEEP GETTING PUSHED TO THE SIDE.
BUT WHEN A YOUTUBER LIKE I SHOW SPEED SHOWS UP TO CITY HALL
SUDDENLY THE MAYOR'S GOT ALL THE ENERGY IN THE WORLD TO SAY
WHAT UP BE FRONT ROW. HYPE IT UP YOU KNOW CAMERAS ALL
I'LL MAKE SURE HE'S ON THE SPOTLIGHT.
>> WHERE'S THAT SAME ENERGY FOR THE INDIGENOUS PEOPLE WHO BUILD
THE VERY GROUNDS THE CITY STANDS ON THAT IS HARDLY EVEN
RECOGNIZED. WE'RE NOT EVEN ASKING FOR
CHARITY. WE'RE NOT WE'RE ASKING FOR
RESPECT AND RECOGNITION THAT SHOULD ALREADY BE OURS.
YOU CAN IGNORE US. YOU COULD TRY TO ERASE US FROM
THE CALENDAR BUT WE'VE SURVIVED EVERY ATTEMPT LIKE THAT FOR 100
YEARS. AND LET ME MAKE IT CLEAR THE
MAYOR DOESN'T SUPPORT US BUT WE'RE STILL HERE AND STILL
THRIVING AND EVEN WILL KEEP THRIVING LONG AFTER HIS NAME IS
GONE AND ALSO JOE, WHAT ARE YOU DOING HERE?
>> DID YOU GET RECALLED? COME ON.
SO YOU VOTE FRAUD LATER. >> ALL RIGHT.
WELL, THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
JUST SO THE PUBLIC UNDERSTANDS THERE'S NO AUDIBLE SOUNDS OF
APPLAUSE OR APPROVAL. THANK YOU.
YOU CAN SHOW YOUR SUPPORT AS SUCH.
WELCOME, SIR. GOOD EVENING.
I STAND BEFORE THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND MAYOR OFFICE OF
DANIEL LURIE OF TREMENDOUS INFLUENCE VESTED IN ME ON A
SPEAKERSHIP AS CEO OF PROJECT MELLOW AND AMBASSADOR OF
NINTENDO TO PRESENT 20 SPECIAL INDIVIDUALS THE QUINTESSENCE
DUAL ABILITY AS A TRUE LEADER ARTO IS TO COMMUNICATE IF
YOU'RE ABLE TO COMMUNICATE EVEN THOUGH YOU AIR AS A HUMAN YOU
ARE UNSTOPPABLE WORKAHOLIC AND LABOR HOLIC LEADERS HOLD NO
BARRIER FOR THAT. I'M HERE TO PRESENT THE MEMBERS
OF THE ELITE AND TO CHANNEL THE REST OF THE WORLD THE 20
ALLIANCE INTERNATIONAL THEY COMPRISED OF 20 BEASLEY FEMALES
MAINLY ON EASTERN FRONT TO WEAVE SPECIFIC TALENT TO FOLLOW
EXPANSION OF HUMANITY'S CONSCIOUSNESS AND TO LIVE UP TO
STYLE ART CREATE AROUND THE GLOBE THEY ARE 20 ALLIANCE HAVE
SENT OUT AESOP DELUCA MAGGIE WONG MISCHANCE AND OF 2018 OF
SAN FRANCISCO AND MISSED POPULAR A MISS CHINESE
INTERNATIONAL 2019 LUCIA MACK MY MAIN SEAT CAMBRIDGE GRADUATE
OF LAW OF 2014 ACTRESS ON TV BE MISS CHINESE INTERNATIONAL 2016
CO-FOUNDER OF PROJECT MELO ROSE A MEMBER OF BLACKPINK FROM BORN
IN THAILAND TO YOU XU MEMBER OF BLACKPINK JENNIE MEMBER OF
BLACKPINK LISA MEMBER OF BLACKPINK OLIVIA RODRIGO
MUSICIAN ARTISTS OF FILIPINO DESCENT YOU TALA MUSICIAN
IN JAPAN LEGION IN IU POP STAR OF SOUTH KOREA AMANDA STEINBERG
LEAD ACTRESS IN STAR WARS ACCOLADE LADY GAGA MONSTERS
CHOKERS AND MONSTER MILEY CYRUS HANNAH MONTANA A FANIA ARENA
ACTRESS AND SINGER ARIANA CROWNED IT ACTRESS AND SINGER
HANNAH TEAM LEAD OF NEW JEANS AMBASSADOR THANK YOU FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. >> NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
>> HELLO, I'M ELEANOR KLEIN AND I'M A CONSTITUENT OF
DISTRICT NINE AND THE MISSION DISTRICT.
>> I AM A RESIDENT OF 21ST THREE RIGHT NEXT TO OUR
WALGREENS THAT GOT SHUT DOWN. >> AND I WANT TO ADDRESS ALL
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WAS TO TALK ABOUT HEALTH AND HEALTH
CARE ACCESS ACROSS THE CITY. >> AND AS A PRIVATE HEALTH CARE
OWNER, I OR I HAVE PRIVATE HEALTH CARE.
I CAN'T GO TO ANY URGENT CARE IN MY ENTIRE DISTRICT.
>> ALL THE OTHER HEALTH CARE PROVIDERS ARE OUTSIDE OF MY
DISTRICT AND ALSO EVERY SINGLE TIME THAT ANYBODY IS GOING TO
INCLUDING THE OLD PEOPLE WHO CAN'T EVEN WALK WHO ARE TRYING
TO GET PHARMACEUTICALS IN OUR DISTRICT, WE HAVE TO WAIT FOR
LIKE 40 PLUS MINUTES AND THEN MOST PEOPLE ARE STILL TURNED
AWAY AT THE END BECAUSE THEY CAN'T CALL AND GET GET CHECKED
THAT THE MEDICATION IS THERE BECAUSE THE LINES ARE DOWN.
>> SO IT'S NOT JUST A DISTRICT OR NOT PROBLEM.
IT'S A PROBLEM FOR THE ENTIRE CITY TO ADDRESS THE
ACCESSIBILITY OF HEALTH CARE AND THE ACCESSIBILITY OF
PHARMACEUTICALS. >> THANK YOU FOR LISTENING.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER .
>> GOOD EVENING. MY NAME IS HONEST HARLEY BODKIN
AND FEEL FREE TO JUST CALL ME BY MY MIDDLE NAME CHARLIE.
I'M SPEAKING MY PERSONAL CAPACITY TODAY.
I WANT TO THANK THIS BOARD FOR CONSIDERING WAYS TO FUND
AFFORDABLE HOUSING. IS THE MAYOR'S FAMILY ZONING
PLAN MOVES FORWARD? I'M SURE THAT THE SUPERVISORS
HERE TODAY WHOSE CONSTITUENTS ARE MOST IMPACTED BY THE
PROPOSED REZONING HAVE HEARD FROM THE COMMUNITY THEIR
CONCERNS OF DISPLACEMENT, LOSING RENT CONTROL AND THE
LACK OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING. THIS REZONING PLAN MARKS A
HISTORIC SHIFT IN LAND USE IN OUR CITY AND THE LARGEST
SUCH CHANGE IN ZONING IN THE PAST 50 TO 60 YEARS.
IT'S NOW THAT WE NEED MORE CREATIVE IDEAS TO FUND
AFFORDABLE HOUSING AS WE KNOW THAT SIMPLY REZONING WON'T MOVE
THE NEEDLE IN TERMS OF ACTUALLY BUILDING HOUSING FOR SAN
FRANCISCANS DUE TO ADVERSE MARKET CONDITIONS AND TARIFFS
DRIVING UP COSTS. >> BUT ALL OF YOUR IDEAS NEED
NOT BE THAT CREATIVE. ONE SUCH IDEA WAS VOTED ON
AND PASSED BY THE VOTERS IN 2020 IN THE FORM OF PROP I
WHICH LEVIED A PROPERTY TRANSFER TAX ON PROPERTIES
WORTH OVER $10 MILLION. >> THE BOARD AT THE TIME
PROMISED THAT THIS MONEY WOULD GO TO FUND SOCIAL HOUSING
THROUGH THE HOUSING STABILITY FUND.
>> INSTEAD THIS MONEY STREAMS INTO THE GENERAL FUND TO THE
TUNES TUNE OF TENS OF MILLIONS OF DOLLARS EACH YEAR.
>> I'M ASKING YOU AND SAN FRANCISCANS FOR SOCIAL HOUSING
ARE ASKING YOU TO FUND THE HOUSING STABILITY FUND.
>> WE'RE ASKING YOU TO FUND THE FUND.
>> NOW IS THE TIME FOR PERMANENTLY AFFORDABLE PUBLICLY
OWNED BEAUTIFUL HOMES FOR SAN FRANCISCANS FOR ALL SAN
FRANCISCANS. NOW IS THE TIME FOR THE
GOVERNMENT. OUR GOVERNMENT TO TAKE
ADVANTAGE OF THIS OPPORTUNITY THAT THIS COMBINATION OF UP
ZONING AND ADVERSE ADVERSE MARKET CONDITIONS TO BUILD
BUILD, BUILD PLEASE FUND THE FUND.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WE WELCOME THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS JOHN WILLARD.
I'M A LICENSED CLINICAL SOCIAL WORKER AND I'M HERE TO URGE YOU
TO SUPPORT SUPERVISOR FIELDER'S RESOLUTION IN SUPPORT OF UCSF'S
CAMPUS CLINICAL SOCIAL WORKERS .
RIGHT NOW UCSF MAINTAINS A TWO TIERED MENTAL HEALTH SYSTEM.
CLINICAL SOCIAL WORKERS AT THE MEDICAL CENTER ARE PAID FAIRLY
FOR THEIR EXPERTISE WHILE CAMPUS CLINICAL SOCIAL WORKERS
WHO HAVE THE SAME QUALIFICATIONS AND OFTEN TREAT
PATIENTS WITH HIGHER NEEDS ARE SYSTEMATICALLY UNDERPAID
EARNING ABOUT 31% LESS. THESE INEQUITIES ARE DRIVING
TURNOVER, LONG WAIT TIMES AND WORSENING ACCESS FOR SOME
OF SAN FRANCISCO'S MOST VULNERABLE RESIDENTS.
PEOPLE LIVING WITH SEVERE MENTAL ILLNESS, SURVIVORS OF
TRAUMA PEOPLE STRUGGLING WITH ADDICTION AND THOSE FACING
HOUSING INSECURITY. THESE WORKERS ARE HIGHLY
TRAINED PROFESSIONALS WHO DEDICATE THEIR LIVES TO SERVING
MARGINALIZED COMMUNITIES. YET THEY ARE BEING TREATED AS
SECOND CLASS EMPLOYEES WITHIN THE SAME INSTITUTION.
THAT IS UNACCEPTABLE AND IT DIRECTLY UNDERMINES OUR CITY'S
INVESTMENTS IN EQUITY AND MENTAL HEALTH ACCESS.
SUPPORTING THIS RESOLUTION IS A CLEAR STEP THE BOARD CAN TAKE
TO CALL ON UCSF TO END THE TWO TIER SYSTEM, PAY ITS CAMPUS
SOCIAL WORKERS EQUITABLY AND ENSURE CONSISTENT HIGH
QUALITY CARE FOR ALL SAN FRANCISCANS.
I RESPECTFULLY URGE YOU TO SUPPORT THIS RESOLUTION.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
BEFORE THE NEXT SPEAKER BEGINS, I JUST WANT TO SAY IF THERE ARE
ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS THE
BOARD THIS AFTERNOON FOR GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT, PLEASE
GET IN LINE. ALL RIGHT.
>> WELCOME MR. DUFFY. W.R. OUR DUFFY DISTRICT FIVE.
AS HE FACED THE FIRING SQUAD, COLONEL O'REILLY OVER ONE YEAR
REMEMBERED THE DAY HIS FATHER TOOK HIM TO DISCOVER ICE.
HOWEVER, I DON'T BELIEVE ENGAGING IN DOUBLE TALK IS AN
APPROPRIATE RESPONSE TO TURNING AMERICA INTO A ZOMBIE CULT OF
SATANIC POSSESSION. NOW THERE WAS A SUGGEST
IN TODAY THAT THERE IS COULD BE A TIME OR WILL BE A TIME OR
EVER WAS A TIME WITHOUT CONTROVERSY.
AS THE THIRD EAST COAST IRISHMAN TO TALK TODAY, LET ME
SAY THAT THE CONTINUUM OF CARE IS THE GOLD STANDARD FOR PUBLIC
HEALTH INCLUDING SUBSTANCE ABUSE.
>> >> THIS BOARD FACES COMPLEX ISSUES EVERY WEEK AND I DO
BELIEVE IT DOES A BETTER JOB FOR STAFF THAN IF THERE WERE NO
LEGISLATURE AT ALL. FOR EXAMPLE, AT LEAST IT DOES
BETTER THAN THE YOUTH COMMISSION.
MARGINALLY. I DO NOT BELIEVE THAT ELECTED
OFFICIALS FIRST PRIORITY SHOULD BE TO REMAIN IN OFFICE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU, MR. DUFFY.
ALL RIGHT. >> WELCOME TO WHAT LOOKS LIKE
OUR LAST SPEAKER. WELCOME.
>> THANK YOU. AS A DISABLED MEMBER OF THE
PUBLIC, I WANT TO TELL YOU THAT I HAVE BEEN TORTURED IN EVERY
E.R. THERE IS NO COMMUNICATION WITH THE NEW LEADER.
OUR DOCTORS OF 35 YEARS BETWEEN THE DOCTORS DIAGNOSIS THAT KNOW
THE PATIENT AND SO THEY'RE FLYING BLIND AND IMMEDIATELY
JUDGE ME FOR BEING AN ARTICULATE PERSON IS SOMEBODY
WHO'S FAKING IT. I HAVE THREE HOLES IN MY HEAD
12 INCH CHUNK. I'M SEVERELY DISABLED WITH
AMBULATORY CHALLENGES AND CANNOT WALK WHEN I'M JUST
INTIMIDATED AND BEATEN AND TOLD TO WALK.
>> THERE NEEDS TO BE SOUND ORDINANCE IN THE CITY THAT
DON'T INJURE ME ON A DAILY BASIS IN MY HOME AND OUTSIDE MY
HOME AND DISPLACING ME WHEN I HAVE BEEN A VICTIM OF VIOLENCE
FOR FIVE BROKEN BONES AND I'M RECOVERING FROM SEVERE BRAIN
DAMAGE. >> THERE NEEDS TO BE SOME KIND
OF OVERSIGHT FOR THE PEOPLE RUNNING THE HOUSING FOR THE
ELDERS AND THE DISABLED INSTEAD OF PEOPLE CONSPIRING TO DO HATE
CRIMES AND TO BE CULT FIGURES AND STEAL ALL YOUR PROPERTY
AND IN THE PARKS WHERE YOU CAN'T HAVE BE SAFE FROM THE
SMOKING. >> THE LOUDNESS THE BICYCLES
BECAUSE SOME VANDALS HAVE TAKEN THE SIGN DOWN AND BECAUSE WE
ARE NOT EMPOWERING PEOPLE TO GIVE TICKETS TO MAKE THE PEOPLE
PAY THAT ARE BREAKING THE LAWS, WE REWARD BAD BEHAVIOR
AND CONSISTENTLY DO SO. >> WE CONSISTENTLY DISCOURAGE
PEOPLE LIKE ME WHO HAVE LOVE IS ALL I'VE GOT TO GIVE TO GIVE
AND TAKE TO GIVE AND TAKE. PLEASE SUPPORT FUNDING FOR
PEOPLE KEEPING THEIR COMMUNITIES CLEAN INSTEAD OF
EMPOWERING THE PEOPLE TO BE THROWING TRASH AND BEAT
CHILDREN TO HAVE RITES OF PASSAGE TO HAVE THE KIDS NOT GO
TO THE PARKS TO DRINK AND SMOKE AND USE DRUGS UNDERAGE AGE.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> ALL RIGHT. PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED.
>> MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE AGENDA ITEMS 35 THROUGH 39 ITEM 35 THROUGH 39
WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION BUT WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE. A UNANIMOUS UNANIMOUS VOTE IS
REQUIRED FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST APPEARANCE
TODAY. ALTERNATIVELY, A MEMBER MAY
REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST APPEARANCE TO GO TO COMMITTEE.
>> I DON'T SEE ANYONE IN THE QUEUE.
MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS 35
THROUGH 39 AND ITEMS 35 THROUGH 39.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR EYES SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO
AND ENGARDIO EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I AND SUPERVISOR MENDELSON HI
MENDELSON I THERE ARE 11 EYES ALL RIGHT WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY
IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS? I HAVE NONE TO REPORT, MR.
PRESIDENT. >> THEN COULD YOU PLEASE READ
THE IN MEMORIAM? >> TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS
ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR THE LATE MS. NONI WILSON ON
BEHALF OF PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN FOR THE LATE MR. RAVEN SKEETERS
. >> CHERYL THANK YOU MADAM
CLERK. I THINK THAT BRINGS US TO THE
END OF OUR AGENDA. >> DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER
BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY? >> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS
FOR TODAY. THEN WE ARE ADJOURNED